<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the division betvveen the English and Romish church upon the reformation by way of answer to the seeming plausible pretences of the Romish party / much enlarged in this edition by H. Ferne ...</title>
            <author>Ferne, H. (Henry), 1602-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 251 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 112 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41214</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F796</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5674</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12409105</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12409105</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61464</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41214)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61464)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 938:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the division betvveen the English and Romish church upon the reformation by way of answer to the seeming plausible pretences of the Romish party / much enlarged in this edition by H. Ferne ...</title>
                  <author>Ferne, H. (Henry), 1602-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 184, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.G. for Richard Royston ...</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Table of contents: p. [1]-[5] at end.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [6] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Reformation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61464:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61464:1"/>
            <p>OF THE DIVISION <hi>BETVVEEN</hi> The ENGLISH <hi>AND</hi> ROMISH <hi>Church <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PON THE</hi> REFORMATION.</p>
            <p>By way of Anſwer to the ſeeming plauſible Pretences of the <hi>ROMISH</hi> Party.</p>
            <p>Much enlarged in this Edition: By H. FERNE D. D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ACT. 24.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>After the way, which they call Hereſie, ſo worſhip I the God of my fathers, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>J. G.</hi> for <hi>Richard Royſton,</hi> at the Angel in Ivie-lane, 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:61464:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61464:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader,</hi> This Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe was intended for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Satisfaction, but falling under the View of ſome, that were able to judge, and liked well of it, (better than it deſerved) it was thought not unfit for more publick uſe. And the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor (then farre off in the North) was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned, not onely to give his conſent to the putting it forth, but to help it forward him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by prefacing ſomething to it, for the fairer bringing it forth into Open light. Know therefore, (Good Reader) and well conſider it, that theſe are ſuch times as the Apoſtle foretold, <hi>2 Tim. Perilous</hi> (difficult and troubleſome) <hi>times, 2 Tim. 3.1.</hi> Times in which it would be hard for good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to know how to behave themſelves with ſafety; the dangers of theſe daies threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, not onely the outward eſtate or world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:61464:3"/>concernments, but attempting Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Religion it ſelf, and that on the one hand and on the other.</p>
            <p>They of the old Romiſh Superſtition pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Antiquity, and a preſent flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition of a Church: They of the new perſwaſion boaſting ſucceſſe, and holding forth New lights to carry aſide.</p>
            <p>As in the day of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> both the Children of <hi>Edom</hi> and of <hi>Babylon</hi> cried, <hi>Down with it, down with it,</hi> Pſal. <hi>137. They ſaw the trouble of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and were glad that the Lord had done it,</hi> Lam. <hi>1.21.</hi> So it is with the true <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> Church in this Land, now troubled and diſtreſſed. The Enemies on either ſide rejoicing, that the Lord hath done it to us.</p>
            <p>A pitifull thing it is, (and one argument more for <hi>Lamentation,</hi> than <hi>Jeremiah</hi> had for his) that the enemies of a Chriſtian Church, ſhould be ſuch on both ſides, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe themſelves Chriſtians, acknowledge One Saviour, look for one Hope; and though agreeing all in the main, yet becauſe of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent perſwaſions in Religion, can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, yea and rejoice to ſee a Chriſtian Church to fall, and to be (if they might have their will) thrown quite off from the Foundation, on which they profeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb facs="tcp:61464:3"/>to be built, rather than ſee it ſtand there, otherwiſe, than juſt as they doe, and according to their frame.</p>
            <p>How much were it to be wiſhed, and to be prayed for, that the Lord would <hi>roll away this reproach of Aegypt, Joſ. 5.9.</hi> from off the name of Chriſtians, this uncircumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this hardneſſe of heart? that he would take away this <hi>perverſe Spirit he has min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled</hi> among us, (as <hi>Iſa. 19.14.</hi>) from whence ariſe ſuch Debates, and contentions, not onely about the things of Earth, but of Heaven too: the Affairs and buſineſſe of the State, and of the Church too.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> perſwaſion, when I look at thoſe points of Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted between us, which concern not the ſpecial and politick concernments of that Church (ſuch as <hi>Univerſal Juriſdiction,</hi> and that which follows on it, <hi>Univerſal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,</hi> and that which muſt maintain the former, <hi>Infallibility,</hi> and the like) I cannot but think, there might be a poſſibility of ſome peaceable and fair Chriſtian agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Yea, and were there Reaſon and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity in men, inſtead of that pretended <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility,</hi> to agree and ſtay upon the due Authority of free General Councels, and inſtead of the now exorbitant power of the
<pb facs="tcp:61464:4"/>Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to be content he ſhould have onely the Antient <hi>Patriarchal Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy</hi> allowed him in the firſt Generall Councels, I ſhould not despair of agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as to theſe points.</p>
            <p>But when I conſider, how neerly the Guides of that Church take themſelves to be concerned in theſe Politick Intereſſes, and what a numerous ſociety there is of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites devoted to maintain them, I muſt needs ſay, that hope ſeems vain, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them engaged to hold where they are, and to condemn all other Chriſtians, and Churches to the <hi>Gates of Hell,</hi> that will not acknowledge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be the onely Church, againſt which the <hi>Gates of Hell</hi> have not, nor can prevail by any errour in Faith or Worſhip.</p>
            <p>He that will look into the buſineſſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion before, and at the beginning of the Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> will eaſily ſee by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Colloquies held between <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> what agreement ſome points were brought to, and what further conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion might have been, had not the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſes of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> diſturbed all. Or if he look into thoſe Relations and Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories we have of the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> it ſelf, he will ſee by the ſeveral diſcourſes
<pb facs="tcp:61464:4"/>had upon the points controverted, what mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration there was in many learned men, but rendred ineffectual, by reaſon that the <hi>Arcana Imperii,</hi> thoſe forementioned poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick concernments of that Church, as they might not be once diſputed, ſo they wholly over-ruled the other points of Religion, and excluded all Moderation in the Definitions of that Councel.</p>
            <p>All the Chriſtian World ſees, how long the poor distreſſed <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Church has lain under that heavy condition, unpitied by Them of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communion; and how They have ſtood affected to us ſince our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation has ſufficiently appeared by their ſeveral practices againſt us; What hand they had in our preſent troubles is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to ſome; what joy they now take in them, let their own heart tell them; but what advantage they make of them for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of many, that is it we are to take notice of, and to withſtand. I have oppoſed this Defence, ſuch as it is, againſt their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall plauſible pretences: framed indeed both for Matter and Form, moſt-what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſcruples of Thoſe, that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned it; but may generally ſerve to give ſome ſtay in theſe tottering Times to thoſe, that have not a more able hand to hold and keep them ſteady.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61464:5"/>
            <p>As for the Particular Doctrines of the Romiſh Church, ſome of the chief of them, (as <hi>Traditions, Infallibility, Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, Invocation of Saints, Purgatory)</hi> are ſpoken to, as concerning <hi>the Trial of Antiquity,</hi> towards the End of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. Where it is by divers inſtances ſhewn, that they could not be doctrines of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Church. I may happily finde time (with Gods help) to make a fuller enquiry upon theſe, and other their novel Articles; that it may appear, what is juſtly and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily controverted between us, either in matter of Faith or Worſhip: What may be waved, as needleſly quarrelled at, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, as needleſly contended about: And of the controverted Points, which Doctrine, Theirs, or Ours, will upon the triall of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Scripture, prove more Apoſtolical: which upon principles confeſſed by us both, will appear more ſafe and reaſonable, and alſo more agreeable to true Chriſtian hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and piety. But of this hereafter, as it ſhall pleaſe God to give opportunity, and ability.</p>
            <p>It remains, I ſhould ſpeak to that ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing advantage they would make of our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed condition, to the abuſing of unwary Proteſtants into a perſwaſion, that we have
<pb facs="tcp:61464:5"/>no Government, no Communion, no Church. Something is ſaid to it, in the Body of this Treatiſe, upon the point of <hi>Schiſme</hi> and <hi>Diviſion.</hi> But to give the Reader farther ſatisfaction, it muſt be conſidered, Firſt, It is no new thing to ſee a Church under the power of the Sword, oppreſſed by the hand of violence, perſecuted, ſcattered, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the peace, order, and comlineſſe it had: Nor ought any Man to think, that he is not therefore in the Boſome of the Church, becauſe he cannot lie in it quietly and at eaſe, as formerly; or that it is beſt for him to ſtay no longer in the Ship, (as they thought, <hi>Act. 27.30, 31.</hi>) becauſe it is toſſed to and fro, with a heavy and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtorm. The Romaniſt, that judges much of things ſpiritual by the eye of ſenſe, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well like of Chriſtian worſhip, but when it is pompous and highly Ceremonious; nor of a Chriſtian Church, unleſſe it be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conspicuous for outward ſplendour, and undiſturbed order. But then is Truth of moſt price, when it is <hi>bought</hi> at a dear rate, and not <hi>ſold</hi> upon any terms; when it is ſought out with great difficulty, and held upon as great diſadvantages; and then is Faith moſt pretious, when it is moſt tried, and ſtands under the greateſt preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61464:6"/>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider, what has hapned to us, is faln upon us for Trial, and Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation: to the end, that they, <hi>which are approved, might be made manifeſt among us, (1 Cor. 11.19.)</hi> for the <hi>Truth</hi> they hold to, and the <hi>Faith</hi> they profeſſe; and that All might be humbled and corrected, the Sons of <hi>Levi</hi> especially refined and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, <hi>Mal. 3.3.</hi> Our troubled condition therefore does not juſtifie the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor ought to confirm any in the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of that perſwaſion; but it condemns onely our iniquities, in being unanſwerable to that Pea e and Truth we enjoyed: and calls for, not a forſaking of that way of Worſhip and Religion we were in, but of thoſe ſinnes by which wee provoked this wrath.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider, what has hapned to us, has to the ſame end and purpoſe often befaln the Church of God, without a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of it. If the Lord has now <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> this Church <hi>with a cloud in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> it is but what he did to <hi>Zion, Lam, 2.1. If in the indignation of his wrath</hi> he <hi>has deſpiſed both the King and the Prieſt,</hi> it is that which <hi>Jeremiah</hi> lamented in the ſad condition of <hi>Jeruſalem, Lam. 2.9.</hi> If <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed his places of Aſſembly</hi> (as there
<pb facs="tcp:61464:6"/>complained of) it is not the deſtruction of a Church, but the want of that freedome it had of more publick Worſhip and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. Looke we into the Chriſtian Church, how it was trained up for ſome hundreds of yeares in ſuch a low and diſtreſſed condition: under perilous and diſſicult times for the moſt part, which ſeldome afforded them a ſecure liberty of due and orderly aſſembling together. We ſee the Church at firſt falling under perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, and <hi>all of them ſcattered abroad,</hi> but ſome few that held together privately at <hi>Jeruſalem, Act. 8.1.</hi> and <hi>cap. 11.19.</hi> and in the next Chap. we ſee their meetings were very cloſe and ſecret, <hi>cap. 12.12, 13.</hi> And ſo was it often with the Church, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the perſecutions of the firſt <hi>300</hi> years, often put to have their meetings before day, and in caves, or ſecret places; yet ſo they maintained the Communion and being of the Church. Why then ſhould any think it ſtrange to ſee the like diſturbance of peace and order happen to a <hi>National</hi> Church? But to come yet nearer our Caſe; When the Church under the violence of Arrian Emperours was perſecuted, ſcattered, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops driven from their Sees, and all good Chriſtian people (that would not communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb facs="tcp:61464:7"/>with Hereſie and Schiſm) driven from the publick places of Worſhip, &amp; put to meet as they could, and where they could; yet ſo they continued the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the Church.</p>
            <p>Now during thoſe perilous times, there was nothing done in the Way of the Church, for Worſhip or Diſcipline, but tis or may be done in this Church. And if any can ſay, tis not ſo done, he does but ſpeak the neceſſity of Times, or at worſt but the fault &amp; failings of men, not the want of any thing neceſſary in the Conſtitution of this Church. For notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the attempts of violence, there is the ſame Doctrine and power of Diſcipline remaining, the ſame Liturgie and form of worſhip, the ſame Government by Biſhops and other inferiour Paſtors; and were there the ſame Zeal, as was in the Chriſtians of the Antient Church under the Heathen or Arrian violence, there would be no cauſe of complaint, no occaſion of reproach, as there is now with ſome by reaſon of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and Diſcipline, not yet ſo regularly provided for in the preſent diſturbed condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Church.</p>
            <p>Indeed this may be ſaid towards an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, that ſuch has been the Conjuncture of Affairs for theſe laſt years, ſuch the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of Occurrences in relation to Church
<pb facs="tcp:61464:7"/>and State, that it made the Times very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult for thoſe that had lawfull power to know, or reſolve how to uſe it lawfully, and to the beſt advantage. The Windes in this ſtorm have blown ſo contrary and from ſuch ſeveral quarters, and the Waves, which beat upon the Ship, have been ſo broken and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, that it was hard for thoſe that were at the Helm to ſtear, or bear up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. And if our Pilots tired out with the ſtorm, did think it beſt (as they did, <hi>Act. 27.25.</hi>) to <hi>let the Ship drive</hi> a while, out of hope the Winde would ceaſe of it ſelf, or ſome other more favourable blaſt ariſe from ſome other quarter: This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed might be prudence for the then preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Exigency; yet muſt not they or any elſe, becauſe the ſtorm lies ſtill upon us, think (as they did, <hi>Act. 27.30.) of flying out of the Ship,</hi> But rather take courage <hi>after long abſtinence,</hi> and provide for ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as well as the difficulty and diſtreſſe of the Times will permit.</p>
            <p>There laid a heavy ſtorm upon the Church, when it was under the Heathen, or Arrian violence; yet if compared with the condition of our Times, it will appear to have been in better capacity of holding the Communion more regular and distinct, by
<pb facs="tcp:61464:8"/>reaſon the oppoſition was more regular, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and apparent: The Civil power was the ſame, no alteration of State to trouble them, but only the will of the Prince chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and for the time bent againſt them: the buſineſſe alſo of Religion was clear, and eaſie to reſolve, for, whether we conſider the Heathen Superſtition, or the Arrian Hereſie: both ſo apparent, that the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of compliance were leſſe forcible, and ſo the means of holding Chriſtians together, in a diſtinct Communion more ready and eaſie.</p>
            <p>The condition of our Times hath indeed been more difficult, which though it might perſwade forbearance a while, and excuſe it: yet now it calls for the more courage and zeal, in providing for that which ſeems to have been too long neglected, (a more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Church-way of Communion and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip) that which the Apoſtle calls for, and mindes the ſcattered Hebrews of, Not <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the aſſembling of our ſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as the manner of ſome is,</hi> Heb. <hi>10. ver. 25.</hi> as the manner of too many among us is, who are either careleſſe of meeting at all for divine worſhip, or indifferent where or with whom they meet: nothing ſcrupling that <hi>promiſcuous</hi> Communion, which is yet
<pb facs="tcp:61464:8"/>ſeen in too many places, and ſhould (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) be provided againſt. If any ask how? how, but by the power of the <hi>Keyes,</hi> which the Sword of violence cannot cut in ſunder, nor the Church looſe, unleſſe they that hold them, caſt them away? The uſe of that power is to ſeparate or <hi>take forth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious from the vile, (Jer. 15.19.)</hi> the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Sheep from the violent Goats, the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Chriſtian from the factious Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick: And <hi>he that is filthy let him be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſtill, (Revel. 22.)</hi> and he that will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn, let him mock on ſtill, but God is not mocked. And were this done, as it might be done according to the preſent diſtreſs of theſe Times, there would be no occaſion for the Adverſaries to mock, or for other to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain (as the Prophet <hi>Iſa.</hi> in the behalf of <hi>Jeruſalem, ch. 31.18.) There is none to guide her of all the Sons whom ſhe hath brought forth, neither is there any that taketh her by the hand, of all the Sons that ſhe hath brought up.</hi> But the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries <hi>that have afflicted her,</hi> and ſaid to her, <hi>Bow down, that we may go over,</hi> would for their mocking have cauſe to fear what the Lord threatens at the <hi>23 ver. I will put the cup of trembling into their hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61464:9"/>
            <p>And now Good Reader, if thou beeſt (or wouldſt ſhew thy ſelf) a good Church-man, that is a good Chriſtian, <hi>abhorring Idols,</hi> and hating to <hi>commit Sacrilege,</hi> deſiring to keep thy ſelf pure from Superſtition in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip, and from Faction and Schiſm in Church-Communion: <hi>Beware</hi> then of falſe Teachers, <hi>Beware of the Conciſion, (Phil. 3.2.)</hi> both New and Old; Suffer not thy ſelf to be cut off from thy former Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, either by any new Sect, or by the cunning of any <hi>Romiſh</hi> perſwaſion: Let not theſe troubleſome Times, which are for thy tryall, and manifeſting of what is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved in thee, be unto thee an occaſion of falling. God, whom thou ſerveſt in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is able to make thee ſtand. To his grace I commend thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>HEN: FERNA.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61464:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of the Diviſion between the</hi> Engliſh Church <hi>and</hi> Romiſh <hi>upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T cannot be denied, that every Chriſtian is bound to learn and know upon the beſt Evidence he can, what it is that God will have him believe to Salvation, and how he will be worſhipped by him. To this he ſtands obliged, both by the end of his hope, Salvation, if he will attain to that, and by his Vow, at
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61464:10"/>his entrance into Chriſtianity, the promiſe he made, <hi>to Believe, and Doe all,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now when differences are among Chriſtians about Faith and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, we are more concerned to uſe care and diligence in ſeeking after the Truth: not to follow all Guides, or take all on Truſt, but, as S. <hi>Jude</hi> bids us, <hi>Earneſtly to contend for the Faith once delivered,</hi> Jude ver. 3.</p>
            <p>Many years have we contended with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> about the Faith once delivered, impleading her of innovating in Belief and Worſhip to the introducing of groſſe Errors, and Superſtitions: And ſtill we have more cauſe to contend with them of that Church, becauſe more buſie now in working upon the diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the Times, and in drawing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſome unwary and unſtable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, by plauſible pretences of ſeeming advantage to the Romiſh
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61464:10"/>Church, in compariſon of the now diſturbed condition of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our work is therefore to ſtrive with them, not out of the ſpirit of contention, to the multiplying of Controverſies, or enlarging the Rout which (God knows) is too wide al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: but only to the neceſſary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our ſelves, our Faith and Worſhip, of which we are alwaies ready to give an account. And as to the charging of them, however they deal with us, we are willing to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe in them, what is excuſable: Yet ſo as to make appear, what is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in their general plauſible preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and what is hurtful or deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the Catholick Faith, in their particular Doctrines.</p>
            <p>This is certain and not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, that a Doctrine of Faith was delivered, the true Profeſſion of which, makes or conſtitutes a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61464:11"/>Church: alſo that there is and will be, to the Worlds End, muſt not be taken as the Romaniſts doe, as if one and the ſame Church of one deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, as <hi>Roman,</hi> or <hi>Epheſian,</hi> or <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſhould doe it; or, as if thoſe Paſtors, which are chief in place ſhould doe it; but that it ſhall be done in ſome part or other of the Catholick Church, and by ſuch of the Paſtors in the Catholick Church, as it pleaſes God to uſe for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his Truth: a Church, in which, and by which (as the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of Truth) that doctrine ſhall be preſerved and upheld: and in that Church a ſucceſſion of Paſtors and Teachers to deliver down that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Faith once delivered by our Lord and his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>The Romaniſt, when he is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for his faith, is not willing to come to the Trial of particular Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, but rather ſtaies in the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61464:11"/>of <hi>a Church, a viſible ſucceſsion,</hi> and the like, ſeeking by theſe (which make a plauſible noiſe to the Unwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) to prove the continuation of the Doctrine rather, than to defend his Church by the Doctrine ſhe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; and to make a clamour of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion</hi> and <hi>Schiſme</hi> (odious Names) rather than to examine upon due conſideration of that purity of Faith and Worſhip (which every Church ought to hold) where the cauſe is, and whoſe the fault, that we now ſtand divided.</p>
            <p>Wee begin with the Generalls. Where, upon the ſeeming advantage of the former pretences, they charge us with ſetting up a New Church, when we reformed; and as conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to that, with Schiſme or breach of Communion. We deny that we ſet up a New Church, or made a Schiſme, or that we ſtand guilty of this breach of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:61464:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>We ſet not up a new Church, but were the ſame Christian Church before and after the Reformation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN order to the firſt, they uſually put the queſtion, <hi>Where was your Church before</hi> Luther? A Queſtion that carries a charge very plauſible to the unlearned, who cannot diſtinguiſh between the <hi>face,</hi> and the <hi>body</hi> (or rather <hi>ſoul)</hi> of a <hi>Church:</hi> between that which <hi>makes a Church,</hi> and that which <hi>makes it ſuch a Church.</hi> We anſwer therefore, our Church was there where now it is, and where it alwaies was; the ſame Chriſtian Church, as before the Reformation, having loſt nothing that made it ſo. But ſay they, <hi>The Church in</hi> England <hi>before the Reformation was their Church, holding and practiſing what they did.</hi> Be it ſo, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> generally held and practiſed ſo, yet may it remain the ſame <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> when it ceaſed to hold and practice ſo. For we may likewiſe put the Queſtion to them, <hi>Where was your Church for divers Ages of the Primitive and firſt Times?</hi> They will anſwer, <hi>where it is now, at</hi> Rome <hi>and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</hi> But we ſay, <hi>that was our Church, holding and practiſing (for the main) as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61464:12"/>we.</hi> For <hi>where was there for thoſe firſter Ages, a Romiſh Church holding and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the Canon of the Scripture, as they doe now? or pretending to an Infallibility, as now? or challenging <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as now? where was there a Romiſh Church for</hi> 500 <hi>years, that held Purgatory a point of Faith? that taught Invocation of Saints for Catholick doctrine? or that pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed it in the publick Liturgie for about that time? or that taught, or practiſed I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage-worſhip for a longer time? or where was a Roman Church that taught and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned Communion under one kinde, for a</hi> 1000 <hi>years?</hi> This is moſt notorious to them, that are but reaſonably acquainted with Antiquity. Nor is Cardinal <hi>Peron</hi>'s 18 <hi>cap. lib.</hi> 1. againſt the King, touching <hi>the Agreement of the Antient and Modern Church,</hi> any proof againſt it, but a flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh only. Now if they, notwithſtanding theſe and many other errors and corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions by (degrees crept in upon that Church) will ſay, <hi>Their Church is ſtill the ſame with the antient Roman Church,</hi> they muſt give us leave to ſay with more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: We, notwithſtanding we have caſt off thoſe corruptions, are the ſame Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church; yea, and ſay it with more
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61464:13"/>truth and advantage, in as much as that which made the <hi>Romiſh</hi> or <hi>Engliſh Church</hi> before the Reformation to be a Church, we have retained, without the accrewing corruptions, and ſo much more like the Church which was at <hi>Rome,</hi> and in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in the firſt and purer Ages. We ſay therefore, we are the ſame Chriſtian Church, having loſt nothing that made us ſo, but only caſt off many things, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered our being ſo, <hi>viz:</hi> thoſe many errors &amp; ſuperſtitions that tended to the deſtruction of that Chriſtian faith, which made us a Church. As a man recovered from ſome peſtilential or dangerous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, is the ſame man that before, has loſt nothing that made him ſo, only now freed from the corruption, that endangered his being ſo. We ſet up then no <hi>new Church,</hi> but <hi>reformed</hi> that which was, <hi>freeing</hi> it from former <hi>corruptions.</hi> And this makes a <hi>different Church,</hi> but not a <hi>New Church;</hi> a different Church I ſay, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>accidental</hi> differences, by which the ſame body may differ from it ſelf at ſeveral times, and the parts of the ſame body from one another at the ſame time: ſo one Church may differ from it ſelf at ſeveral times, &amp; from other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61464:13"/>yet they and it be parts of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church; but not according to <hi>Eſſential</hi> differences, which conſtitute a <hi>Church</hi> as part of the <hi>Catholick,</hi> and make it differ from another, that is not ſo. The <hi>Engliſh Church</hi> differed from it ſelf as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after Reformation, yet the ſame Chriſtian Church; only before it had a Romiſh face, and garb, and apparel ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and a body full of ſpots and ſores: After, it appeared otherwiſe, yet ſtill the ſame body, the ſame Church, not loſt any thing of that which made it ſo; but only caſt off acceſſory accidental corruptions.</p>
               <p>For thus it ſtood between the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Reformation. They were both parts of the Catholick Church, both built upon the ſame foundation, that Catholick Faith, which had been delivered down in all Ages: that into which they and we are Baptized into, (they not yet daring to baptize into any points of their new faith) that which they and we yet agree in, which makes them a Church, and part of the Catholick, becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that Faith ſtill, though clogged with many dangerous errors and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions in belief and practice. While the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61464:14"/>Church of <hi>England</hi> was in Communion with them, it alſo admitted of many ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtructures, Hay, ſtubble and worſe: Errors &amp; ſuperſtitions, which by degrees crept upon the Foundation, and paſſe at this day in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (to the great abuſe of poor Chriſtian Souls) as Catholick Faith. The work of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was to retain the foundation, and whatever was Chriſtian and Catholick, &amp; only to throw off the ſuperſtructures, that burdened and ſhaked it.</p>
               <p>Theſe errors and ſuperſtructures after they appeared, were complained of in all Ages, by many that ſtill held Communion with the Romiſh Church; and Hiſtory alſo aſſures us of many in ſeveral Ages, that did actually caſt them off, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves to be put out of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Communion, rather than admit of them; and how many thouſands more muſt we ſuppoſe to have been not recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, when 7000 were in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not ſo much as known to <hi>Eliah?</hi> This we note, not as if wee were bound to ſeek the Church only in thoſe Reformers, which were of a divided communion from <hi>Rome,</hi> or to deny the Church to be in thoſe of the Romiſh Communion, but to ſhew,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61464:14"/>that however thoſe errors were for ſome Ages delivered, as Catholick Doctrine, by the greater and more prevailing party in that Church, yet were they not held for ſuch by many that continued in that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and rejected actually by many thouſands beſides.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The demand of Profeſſors in all Ages. We can ſhew it better than they.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen therefore they call upon us to name Profeſſors of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant faith in all Ages; though it belongs to them rather to ſhew the Profeſſors of their faith in all Ages, (their part being the affirmative, aſſerting what we deny) and it be a thing they are not able to doe for the five firſt and beſt ages (as was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove inſinuated) yet we anſwer them: If by ſuch Profeſſors they mean thoſe that held a diſtinct communion from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, it is not neceſſary to name ſuch, becauſe the faith was preſerved ſtill in that Communion, though with a great mixture of errors: yet after thoſe errors and corruptions grew to a height, we can
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61464:15"/>give examples in all Ages after, of ſuch Proteſtors againſt them, divided from the Romiſh Communion, and perſecuted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of them; and more abundant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples happily of ſuch we might have had, but that little is come down to us of thoſe poor Chriſtians, beſide what hath come from or through the hands of their profeſſed Enemies. Now in thoſe examples we have ſo many inſtances, not of new Churches ſet up, but of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer reformed; and repreſentations of the Catholick Church in ſome part more pure, in ſome part (and that generally the greater) more unſound.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it is not neceſſary, there ſhould be ſuch, ſo profeſſing in all points as we doe: For here is a latitude of Truth, and ſeveral degrees of Purity, within which God is pleaſed to preſerve his Church, as both Reaſon, and Experience, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There might be ſuch ſo profeſſing, though not ſo viſible and known as to be recorded.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There were ſuch, ſo farre as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Truth and purity in doctrine in ſuch a degree was neceſſary for the continuance and propagation of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61464:15"/>Church: Elſe what could <hi>Eliah</hi> have ſaid, if he had been challenged to ſhew Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors at that time within the Kingdome of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> or after, if they that held the true worſhip in King <hi>Ahaz</hi> his time had been challenged to ſhew them in the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> or <hi>Judah?</hi> for as to his point of preſervation of neceſſary Truth and due worſhip, there is no difference betwixt Jewiſh and Chriſtian Church, the continuance of Gods Church being as neceſſary before Chriſt as after. But we may ſee how the Romaniſts are fain to plead for their Faith and Religion by the uncertain Records of Hiſtory rather than by the known and confeſſed Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Prophets and Apoſtles; yea, to hang all upon a negative Argument from the Records of Hiſtory, rather than to reſt upon that which is poſitively af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in Scripture; For thus runs their Argument. We doe not ſee this or that doctrine profeſſed in all Ages, therefore it cannot be Apoſtolical; whereas it is farre more ſafe to argue, This Doctrine or Religion we ſee is Apoſtolical, plainly delivered in Scripture, therefore it was profeſſed in all Ages; profeſſed I ſay, though not alwaies ſo numerouſly and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61464:16"/>openly, as they expect; nor ſo fully as is by Proteſtants in all points aſſerted: yet at leaſt ſo profeſſed as was neceſſary to the preſervation of <hi>ſaving Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and continuance of the Church. Their nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Argument is farre more forcible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves, their Doctrines being Affirmatives, and they bound to ſhew them profeſſed in all Ages: Whereas our difference from them being in the Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of what they erroneouſly affirm, muſt needs ſuppoſe the Errors in being before there could be any Proteſtors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; and render it a vain chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, to ſhew Proteſtants, as Proteſtants in all Ages; when as many Ages paſſed before the Errors got head, againſt which they proteſted. And for thoſe Ages in which the Errors prevailed: what if Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories have not recorded, what if Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians that wrote then, did not ſo much as know thoſe who were free from ſuch Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors? which is very poſſible, when <hi>Eliah</hi> knew not of any in his time, and yet there were 7000: what then becomes of their Faith, that make this their chief plea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Proteſtants?</p>
               <p>But if by Profeſſors in all Ages they mean ſuch as diſſented &amp; complained of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61464:16"/>the prevailing Errors, though it be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible there ſhould be ſuch in all Ages ſimply, becauſe thoſe errors were not at all for many Ages, yet ſuch are found (as we ſaid) in all Ages after the Error ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared; and how many more ſuppoſe we to have been, which are not recorded; or to have written againſt ariſing Errors in that Church, whoſe Writings are not come down to us?</p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>England,</hi> when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God more openly to diſcover the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and to touch the ſpirits and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of Men, did accordingly caſt them off? only the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acknowledge them to be ſuch, nor amend any thing: but having for many Ages challenged Univerſall Juriſdiction over all other Churches, and prided her ſelf, as the only Catholick Church, and Infallible Guide, ſhe did withall render her ſelf altogether incorrigible, without hope of reformation and amendment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:61464:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>How they and we are ſaid to differ in Eſſentials.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SOme Exceptions they make againſt this, that hath been ſaid. 1. From the expreſſion uſed by ſome Proteſtants, that we and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> differ in <hi>Eſſentials;</hi> thence I have heard ſome of them make this fallacious argument. If differ in Eſſentials, then have the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants made a new Church eſſentially dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from that which was. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The fallacy is in the word <hi>Eſſentials,</hi> which is taken either properly, for Doctrines of Faith belonging to the conſtitution of the Eſſence or beeing of a Church, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly for ſuch as endanger it, working to the diſſolution of it, tending to the corruption, &amp; deſtruction of the Eſſence and beeing of a Church: In this latter ſenſe the Doctrines of Error and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, wherein they differ from us, are termed <hi>Eſſentials,</hi> being no light matters, (as thoſe of Rites and Ceremony) but ſuch as concern the Eſſence or being of a Church: not <hi>conſtitutivè</hi> indeed, and in the affirmative <hi>(i. e.)</hi> not ſuch as are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61464:17"/>to be held and aſſerted by every Church, but <hi>deſtructivè</hi> rather, and in the nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, that is, ſuch as are to be denied and avoided by every Church, as it tenders its own beeing and preſervation. Even as a man, that is in company with infected perſons, is concerned, as he tenders his life, to avoid the contagion, or to free himſelf from it, if tainted; So ſtill the difference of this Church from what it was under the Papacy, is as of the ſame body once infected, now ſound, once diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed, now recovered.</p>
               <p>The Church of the <hi>Galatians</hi> was farre gone in the way of the <hi>Moſaical Law</hi> to the endangering of the Goſpel, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in a manner they were removed to another Goſpel, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.6. and that he was afraid of them, <hi>cap.</hi> 4.11. The Churches of <hi>Pergamus</hi> and <hi>Thyati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a</hi> were ſo far corrupted, that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan is ſaid to have his ſeat there, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.13. and thoſe that taught the doctrine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and thoſe that held the doctrine of the <hi>Nicolaitans, v.</hi> 14, 15. And <hi>Jezabel</hi> was ſuffered to teach in <hi>Thyatira,</hi> and to ſeduce the ſervants of God, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. Now when theſe Churches were reformed, the ſeducing Teachers and falſe doctrines
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61464:18"/>caſt out, were they New Churches ſet up? or could thoſe that ſtill adhered to the Law, or new Goſpel in <hi>Galatia,</hi> or to the falſe doctrines in <hi>Pergamus</hi> and <hi>Thyatira,</hi> challenge the reformed party of Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? ſo was it with this Church before and after the Reformation, having parted with nothing, that belonged to the <hi>beeing</hi> of a Church, or to the <hi>Faith once delivered,</hi> but onely caſt out thoſe falſe doctrines that had ſo generally prevailed in it, while it was in communion with the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They object, We caſt not off Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors or Superſtitions, but the true Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Indeed it concerns them to make the World believe (if they can) that their New Faith was alwaies Catholick, and that we for denying it are Hereticks. But the clearing of this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the examination of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar doctrines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61464:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Particular Churches may reform; Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when a General Councel cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="3">3. THey ask what Authority we had to reform the Church, and tell us, we ſhould have expected the determination of a General Councel, and not been Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in our own Cauſe. <hi>Anſ.</hi> We took not upon us to reform the Church, but had a neceſſity and duty upon us to reform our ſelves. Neither did we undertake to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon other Churches, but purge our own. And as we were a <hi>party</hi> in the <hi>cauſe,</hi> ſo was the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>faction;</hi> and as we would not have been Judges in this <hi>cauſe,</hi> could we had a <hi>competent Judge,</hi> ſo was <hi>not</hi> he with <hi>his faction</hi> fit to be a <hi>Judge</hi> in the <hi>cauſe.</hi> Indeed a <hi>lawful</hi> and <hi>free General Councel</hi> of the <hi>whole Church,</hi> ſetting <hi>ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> before them as their <hi>Rule,</hi> had been the only and <hi>competent Judge;</hi> but ſeeing ſuch a <hi>Councel</hi> was not to be had, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, (not a <hi>General</hi> one, becauſe of the <hi>diviſion</hi> of the <hi>Eaſtern Church</hi> from the <hi>Weſt,</hi> nor a <hi>lawful</hi> and <hi>free</hi> one, becauſe of the exorbitant power of the Pope and his Dependants) it remained we ſhould
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61464:19"/>uſe the means left us, and doe it by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial and National Synods, keeping the ſame Rule, the Word of God, Which <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> with other wiſe learned men allows, and calls it <hi>reformari per parte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> when the Church reforms it ſelf by parts; and to this, provincial Councels doe ſuffice, <hi>Gerſ: de Concil: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nius obed:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo we reade, the Emperour with other Kings and Princes, who called for a General Councel to compoſe differences in Religion, thought it reaſonable up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the tergiverſation of the Pope, to doe it by Provincial Synods in their ſeveral Dominions, and ſo they threatned the Pope they would do, if he would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to a Councel. A Councel, and the rame of Reformation were alwaies for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable to the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the dread of a General Councel, and the fear of ſuch Provincial Synods, Pope after Pope hung tormented for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers yeares, uſing all the artifices as might be, to ſatisfie the Princes, and yet to keep off both General and Provincial Synods; till Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the third aroſe, a man of Spirit, and cunning, who turned the fear of a Councel into the hope and expectation of advantage by it; And ſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61464:19"/>indeed he and his dependants ordered the buſineſſe at <hi>Trent,</hi> that nothing could there be determined without his privity and direction; that in the end both Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and People, inſtead of relief, they expected by a Free Councel, found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more hampered and enſlaved by the pretended General Courcel of <hi>Trent.</hi> Where divers points, which before were more free to opine in, or have freedome of opinion in, were defined Articles of Faith, and all hope excluded of gaining what divers Princes made no queſtion to carry at the beginning, <hi>viz:</hi> Communion in both kindes, Prieſts marriage, Service in a known tongue, and ſome other.</p>
               <p>The Princes and the People were very ill ſatisfied with this dealing; the <hi>French</hi> did not of many years receive that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, yet did not proceed to make uſe of a national Synod (happily becauſe of the troubles in that Kingdome) but the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Nation would not be ſo fooled; for ſeeing aforehand what could be expected from the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> they made uſe of that Power, which God has left in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Church of judging for it ſelf according to his word: eſpecially when the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church ſtands ſo divided and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61464:20"/>with faction, that the chief remedy of all, a Free General Councel, cannot be had.</p>
               <p>What God ſpake to his people by the Prophet <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Though Iſrael tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe, yet let not Judab ſin,</hi> tells us, a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church may and ought to reform, though others will not; and the examples of many Provincial Councels in this point of declaring, and caſting out errors, cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping upon them, warrant what we have done. For if Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and the other Biſhops in a Provincial Synod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared againſt, and rejected the uſurped claim of the Pope in point of Appeal, why might not the Engliſh Church under <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. caſt out his uſurped power here? And if the Provincial Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod of <hi>Laodicea</hi> declared againſt, and condemned the worſhipping of Angels then on foot, why might not we alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt worſhip of Saints and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges prevailing here?</p>
               <p>If it be ſaid, it was not done here by a juſt Provincial Synod, but the moſt of the former Biſhops were againſt the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and diſplaced. <hi>Anſw.</hi> We need not tell them how the buſineſſe was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried at <hi>Trent,</hi> how ſome were ſent away,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61464:20"/>ſome kept back, others, and they but Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tular Biſhops, ſent in; and all to make up a <hi>major</hi> part; which the Hiſtories of that Councel witneſs. And <hi>Dudithius</hi> an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garian Biſhop, and one of the Orators for that King, complained of it, as it is to be ſeen in his advices and Letters from thence. But we ſay, that in that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation under <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. and Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> is more largely purſued in my I<hi rend="sup">ſt</hi> Part, <hi>Chap:</hi> 2. there was no diſplacing of Biſhops, but all paſſed with a general conſent. And upon that Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation or Ejection of the Popes uſurped power, aroſe the firſt diviſion of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh and Romiſh Church. In that which followed under Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the buſineſſe of the Synod was regularly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by the Major part; the diſplacing of the Biſhops, that were put out, being before, and that upon the denyal of the Oath of Supremacy, and their conſpiring together to refuſe to Crown the Queen. I will conclude this point of our Reforming with the ſaying of Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> lib. 2. Ep: 3. <hi>Si quis de Anteceſſorib: &amp;c. If any of thoſe that went before us did through ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, or ſimplicity not obſerve and hold this, which the Lord by his example and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61464:21"/>doctrine hath taught, it may be pardoned them through the Indulgence of God;</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis non poterit ignoſci, &amp;c. <hi>but to us it cannot be pardoned, who are now admoniſhed and inſtructed of the Lord.</hi> So ſay we, If any went before us in the Communion and Errors of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> through ſimplicity of heart, we deny him not mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with God; but we could not expect it, if being better inſtructed of God we had not amended our known errors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>We not guilty of Schiſm. The guilt of the breach lies on the Romaniſts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THus farre of our <hi>Reforming,</hi> Now of that which followed upon it, <hi>breach of Communion.</hi> And here they charge us with Schiſme. When I ſay breach of Communion followed upon our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, I doe not take the charge and guilt of it upon us, or imply that it followed as the proper effect does upon the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate cauſe; but followed accidentally, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionally, and is to be imputed to ſome cauſe elſe; not our reforming, but their default. They gave us cauſe by Errours
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61464:21"/>and Superſtitions thruſt upon us, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form; They, when We and all Nations called for Reformation, remained incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible; We did our duty, they would not doe theirs; Diviſion of Communion ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily followes (by reaſon thoſe Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours were not only in belief, but in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice and worſhip too) not upon our leaving the Errours, but upon their not leaving them; not upon our going for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but becauſe they would not come on: As when communicating of Infants, was believed as neceſſary, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly practiſed through the Catholick Church, we muſt underſtand it, as gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally believed and practiſed, or more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, than was any Romiſh Errour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Reformation for many ages, that National Church, which firſt reformed it ſelf in that belief and practice, did it juſtly without expecting a General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, and as to that belief and practice ſtood divided from other National Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or parts of the Catholick, till they ſhould reform too; indeed there followed no breach or diviſion upon it, becauſe they all reformed.</p>
               <p>That ſaying of S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſo much in the Mouthes of Papiſts, <hi>Nulla neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:61464:22"/>&amp;c. <hi>there is no neceſſity of dividing from the Church,</hi> was true many waies, but no way againſt us.</p>
               <p n="1">1. True in regard of the occaſion upon which it was ſpoken, <hi>viz:</hi> the ill lives of many in the Church; no neceſſity of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding or leaving Communion for that.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In regard of the Perſons againſt whom it was ſpoken, <hi>viz:</hi> the Donatiſts; they had no neceſſity, or juſt cauſe of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In regard of the Catholick Church; there is no neceſſity of dividing from that, for they that divide from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, doe break with it either upon the point of Faith or Charity, <hi>i. e.</hi> they either depart from that one Faith held in the Catholick Church; or hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Faith, doe break with it for ſome cauſe or matter externall to that one Faith, and for it uncharitably condemn all others, as not belonging to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church. So did the Donatiſts. We did neither. For our ceaſing to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with the Roman Church (which yet is but a particular, not the Catholick Church) was upon the preſerving and keeping entire that Catholick Faith once delivered, which being the chief bond
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61464:22"/>of Uniay of the Catholick Church, and being by us preſerved together with the bond of Charity in not condemning them, as no part of the Catholick Church, we cannot be therefore ſaid to divide from the Communion of the Catholick Church; or to be cauſe of that Diviſion, which followed upon our endevouring to preſerve that Faith entire; but they are the cauſe of it, that would not, and yet would condemn us.</p>
               <p>Our defence then in generall ſtands thus. We had juſt cauſe to reform, and ſo had they; We in Reforming did what we ought: if they had done what they ought, and had cauſe to doe, no breach or diviſion had followed. And further, We in doing what we ought, preſerved the Faith entire, together with Charity. They would neither caſt off their Errors, which clogged and corrupted the Faith, nor retain Charity; but cut us off (as much as in them) from the Catholick Church. It is clear then to whom the Cauſe of this Diviſion muſt be imputed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:61464:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>How neceſſity of dividing Communion ariſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt that it may more particularly be underſtood, what we did, and what cauſe or neceſſity we had of ſo doing: We muſt conſider, that the neceſſity of abſtaining from the Communion of this or that Church, does not preſently ariſe upon Errours or Superſtitions ſuffered or taught in that Church, and held or practiſed by many in it: No, though they be groſſe Errours, and may be damnable to them, that careleſly ſuffer themſelves to be ſeduced into them. Such were the ſeducing doctrines ſuffered and taught in the Churches of <hi>Galatia, Pergamus,</hi> and <hi>Thyatira</hi> (Chap. 3. as aboveſaid) yet was not any therefore neceſſitated to divide from their Communion.</p>
               <p>But then the neceſſity ariſes, 1. When the Errour is directly Fundamental, as in the <hi>Arian</hi> hereſie; for which all true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks held themſelves obliged to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from their Communion. We doe not charge the Roman Church upon that ſcore, in the cauſe of this diviſion.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:61464:23"/>
               <p n="2">2. When the Errour and <hi>Superstition</hi> is in the practiſe, that concerns the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Sacraments, the publick ſervice, the Form and Worſhip (in all which ſtands the exerciſe of the external Communion) ſo that men, truly informed and convinced of thoſe Errours and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, cannot communicate with good conſcience, there ariſes a neceſſity of abſtaining from ſuch practiſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently from Communion with that Church, ſo far as to ſuch practiſes, yet ſo as holding it a part of the Catholike Church. This, I ſay, is a dividing from ſuch a Church in the external Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, by ceaſing to practiſe and hold ſome things, which it doth, but a joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with it in the Catholike, of which we hold it ſtill a part, as we alſo are. And this may give ſenſe to that diſtinction, of forſaking the Errors, but not the Church, <hi>i.e.</hi> not forſaking, or caſting off that which makes a true Member of the Church, or not breaking with the Church upon the point of true Faith or Charity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When ſuch Superſtitious practiſes, together with Errours in belief (in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves groſs and palpable, and to the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe or wilfull, damnable) are not onely
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61464:24"/>taught and permitted in a Church, but impoſed alſo, and required, as a condition of Communion (ſo that they which ſhall not ſo profeſſe, or practiſe, are ſentenced as Hereticks, and excommunicated) there is juſt cauſe and neceſſity of dividing from the Communion of ſuch a Church.</p>
               <p>Now in both theſe reſpects we charge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with the cauſe of our Diviſion, and that we were thereupon neceſſitated to abſtain from her Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, yet ſo as holding her then, and ſtill a Church; and being then, and ſtill ready to hold Communion with her: Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the duty of true Members of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, in caſe ſhe would provide for the ſecurity thereof by a tolerable Reformation.</p>
               <p>So our defence ſtands upon theſe two Aſſertions. That ſuch a cauſe is juſt and neceſſary: and that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> gave it, and we had it; which two make up the two Propoſitions of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It is lawfull to abſtain from the Communion of that Church, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires unlawfull and ſinfull conditions of her Communion; but the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> requires ſuch. Or thus. All men ought upon true conviction to forſake
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61464:24"/>their known Errours and ſins; but we knew them, and were truly convinced of them, therefore in forſaking them we did what we ought.</p>
               <p>The firſt propoſition in both theſe forms ſtands as undeniable, or elſe it muſt be granted, that we may be bound to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue under a neceſſity of ſinning, and that knowingly. So the whole buſineſſe reſts upon the ſecond propoſition, that ſuch was our Caſe, and ſuch the Cauſe that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> gave; which muſt appear by examination of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular doctrines of Belief and Practiſe, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned all the members of that Church.</p>
               <p>Now that they containe ſuch Errours and Superſtitions, as before mentioned, we are ready to demonſtrate both by Scripture and the beſt Antiquity. But it is our purpoſe and work in preſent, to diſcover and take away the general pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and plauſible allegations they make for themſelves, or againſt us in this Cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:61464:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Sectaries cannot make the Plea that we doe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AGainſt our Defence ſo ſtated, they uſually reply; If Proteſtants upon Apprehenſion, or conviction of Errours and Superſtitions in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had juſt cauſe to forſake her Communion, then may Sectaries juſtly forſake the Communion of the Proteſtants Church. For they alſo ſay, and are many times perſwaded and convinced, that <hi>that</hi> Church impoſes on them ſuch Errours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Set the Termes aright, and the fallacy, or ambiguity of this captious reaſoning will appear. If by our appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion or conviction of Errours in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> they mean onely our ſaying, pretending or thinking to be ſo: then the conſequence is good (for Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries doe pretend they are convinced, and many times verily think ſo) but the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption then is falſe; for we did not upon ſuch bare apprehenſion or decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving perſwaſion forſake the Communion of that Church; but upon a true and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent conviction of known Errours and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61464:25"/>Sins (which we were bound to commit in that Communion) demonſtrable by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Antiquity. Which conviction Sectaries have not; nor doe they at all pretend to confirme, what they ſay, by the practice of Antiquity. Make the Caſe like, and it will follow alike in both; If we had given them the like cauſe, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> gave us, they might alſo forſake our Communion: If they had the like conviction as we had, they might as juſtly doe the like. But ſeeing the caſe is unlike, both in regard of our giving them cauſe, and of their apprehenſion or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, it will not follow they can have juſt cauſe of Diviſion or Revolt. See of this more below, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>It is not then their ſaying or thinking, that we impoſed ſinfull conditions of Communion, and that they are convinced of it, which will juſtifie them, or prejudice us. For ſome mens miſtaking of Errour for Truth, muſt not make other men give over to ſtand to truth, and plead it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Errour; or perſwade them, they are alſo miſtaken, and cannot know the Truth when they doe know it evidently.</p>
               <p>Heretikes of old (as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide cap.</hi> 23. <hi>prope finem.</hi>
                  </note> appears by Saint <hi>Iren. Tertul.</hi> and <hi>Auguſt.</hi>)
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61464:26"/>ſheltered themſelves againſt Scripture by plea of Traditions: Now does the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> think it unreaſonable to defend it ſelf by unwritten Traditions, becauſe Heretikes pretended them? And yet I hope its more poſſible for us to make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the truth of what we ſay, by that which is written in Scripture and Fathers, than for the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to make the truth of what ſhe ſaies to appear by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written Traditions: the truth of which Traditions it is not poſſible for her to make appear.</p>
               <p>It is not therefore ſaying or thinking, that muſt carry it on any ſide, but the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videncing and proving of what is ſaid. That we undertake to doe from point to point: as the clear demonſtration, that we had juſt cauſe, and were truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of it, and had rebelled againſt Light, and grievouſly ſinned, had we ſtill continued in known Errour, and wilfull Sin: the inſeparable condition of Roman Communion, to them that have means to know the Errour and Sin.</p>
               <p>But they object alſo, That the way of our Reforming, and Dividing from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the plea we make for it, leaves men to their own reaſon and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61464:26"/>judgement to make uſe of it againſt the Church, and ſo opens a gap to Hereſie and Schiſm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> It is not any thing we have done, or yet hold, that gives them juſt cauſe to object this to us; but the chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging of Infallibility to their Church, neceſſitates them to lay ſuch a charg upon all that will not blindly reſign up reaſon, judgement and faith to the dictates of their Church. We will firſt ſpeak of the uſe of Reaſon and Judgement permitted to them that can uſe it; then of the uſing it againſt, or diſſenting from the Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of the uſe of Reaſon and Judgement in private men.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>REaſon and Underſtanding is that Light, which he, <hi>that lightens every man that comes into the World, Ioh.</hi> 1.9. puts into the mind of man to ſee, and judge thereby, what to believe, and what to doe. Now though we leave not men wholly to their own Reaſon, yet muſt we leave them the uſe of it, ſo far as is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61464:27"/>to the aſſent, which Faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires; and we leave it them, not in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the publick Judgement of the Church, but to the blind obedience of an implicite Faith, that ſees no other ground or motive of believing and practiſing, than becauſe the Church ſo commands. If the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> impoſe the hard con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition on them that come over to her (as <hi>Nahaſh</hi> the <hi>Ammonite</hi> on them of <hi>Iabeſh Gilead,</hi> that would come out to him, 1 <hi>Sa.</hi> 11.2.) to thruſt out their right Eye, the Eye of their ſpiritual underſtanding (by which they diſcern and judge of <hi>Spiritual things revealed of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13.15.) and onely leave them the eye of common ſenſe to diſcerne what it is the Church doth practiſe, or what it defines, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further enquiring about the will of God, how conſonant that practiſe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition, that worſhip or belief is to it. If, I ſay, ſhe can impoſe this hard condition, we cannot; but muſt ſay:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That no man can believe any thing truly with ſuch a free and full aſſent as faith requires, nor doe any thing in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or practiſe of life, with that faith or due perſwaſion of the lawfulneſſe of it, which the Apoſtle requires <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:61464:27"/>unleſſe he be convinced of it in his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as in the ſame <hi>chap. v.</hi> 5. <hi>Let every one be fully perſwaded in his own mind:</hi> concluding by the due uſe of his reaſon, that its Gods revealed will he ſhould ſo doe and believe. For the Apoſtle ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that of perſwaſion in and about things indifferent ſhews it is much more neceſſary in matters of Faith and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Nor can this be eluded by ſaying, It is ſufficient for ſuch a perſwaſion, that a man knows the Church ſaith ſo, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon concludes that God ſaith ſo; for there is more in the Apoſtles ſaying, <hi>The Spiritual man judgeth all things,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. For that <hi>judging</hi> is not a receiving of things propounded by the Church, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out examination, but implies a diſcerning of them to be the things of God, before he receives them for ſuch by true faith; and the laſt reſolution or ſtay of Faith is not upon the Churches ſaying ſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Gods people are not left to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſeeke out that revealed Will of God; but he has appointed Guides and Paſtors in his Church, in every National Church to propound and demonſtrate that Will of God out of his Word. To this end were <hi>Paſtors and Teachers</hi> given,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61464:28"/>
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>that we ſhould not be carried away with every wind of doctrine,</hi> ver. 14.</p>
               <p>Theſe have <hi>publike judgement</hi> to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and judge for others, for they muſt give account for others; but private Chriſtians have their <hi>private judgement,</hi> or, <hi>judgement of Diſcretion</hi> for themſelves onely, which is in the diſcerning and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving to themſelves, as the will of God, what is delivered, and propounded to them for they muſt anſwer alſo for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and live by their own faith; which cannot be without allowing them due uſe of their reaſon and judgement, to ſee the evidence of that to which they muſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Therefore we ſay alſo, the Guides and Paſtors of the Church doe guide and teach not Infallibly, but Morally, by way of doctrine and perſwaſion, <hi>by manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Truth, commending themſelves to every mans conſcience,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When that is done, They doe not leave men to themſelves, but as Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the Church doe by power of the Keyes judge and bind the Gainſayers, and caſt the Refractory out of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. So then the Guides of the Church have the <hi>power of Publike Judgement,</hi> to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61464:28"/>judge and define for others in matters of faith and worſhip; and <hi>power of Iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> to judge, cenſure, and caſt out the diſobedient; and to private men is leſt onely the <hi>Iudgement of diſcretion,</hi> without which they cannot come to beleeve, or ſerve God, as they ought, with <hi>reaſonable ſervice,</hi> Rom. 12.1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of diſſenting from the publike Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw for the uſing their reaſon and judgement againſt the Church, or their diſſenting from the definitions and practiſe of it, we give no encouragement to that.</p>
               <p>We 1. teach all Inferiours, whether People or Prieſts, when they finde cauſe of doubt or queſtion againſt ſuch defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or practiſe, to miſtruſt their owne reaſon, and rather relye upon the publick Judgment than their own in every doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full caſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That they which doubt ſtill ſeek re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folution and ſatisfaction from their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, modeſtly propounding their
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61464:29"/>doubts and reaſons, and conſcionably u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all means to rectifie their judgment, and ſatisfie their Conſcience.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If they cannot find ſatisfaction ſo, as inwardly to acquieſce, yet to yeeld ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal obedience, &amp; peaceable ſubjection, according as the condition of the matter queſtioned will bear. In a word, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire all that ſubmiſſion of judgement and outward compliance that may be due to an Authority, not infallible, yet guiding others by an infallible Rule, and moſt highly concerned to guide them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, as being anſwerable for their Soules.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We tell them the danger of gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying, that they are to anſwer it to God and his Church; That if they cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the reaſon of their diſſenting, to the judgement of the Church, they muſt expect to undergoe the Cenſures of it. For the Church ſtanding ſo obliged to anſwer for Souls, and to preſerve Peace and Unity, and having therefore the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of <hi>Authority and publick judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> above all private perſons, it is alſo moſt reaſonable it ſhould have the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, in the conteſtation with private perſons, and in the iſſue of ſuch a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61464:29"/>to proceed according to its own judgement, and uſe the power it has, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that ſtand out; And then is there a further anſwering it to God.</p>
               <p>Thus it ſtands between every Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church, and the Members of it, betweene Superiours and Inferiours in it: and in ſome proportion between every particular or National Church and the Catholick Church, in receiving and holding the Definitions of Generall Councils, and the Generall Practiſe of the Church. Tough here a Nationall Church hath the advantage above pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons, in the point of Judgement and diſſenting. Yet where it does diſſent from other Churches generally erring, it ariſes firſt from the uſe of reaſon and judgement in private perſons, diſcovering the errours (for ſome in all Reformations muſt ſpeak firſt) and propounding them; which being approved by the Judgement of that Church, the Reformation follows as an Act of publick Judgement, or as an Act of a National Church, which though inferiour to the Catholick, yet hath it judgement within it ſelfe for the receiving and holding the Definitions and Practiſes of the Church-Generall,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61464:30"/>and may have poſſibly juſt cauſe of diſſenting and reforming; and can doe it regularly, according to the way of the Church by Provinciall Synods, which private perſons diſſenting from her can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe. And this is conſiderable in the Engliſh Reformation, which as it was upon publick Judgement of a Nationall Church in Provinciall Synods, ſo will it not prove a diſſenting from the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, or definit ons of true Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councils; but of that more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, when we come to triall by Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: And of this reſpect or ſubmiſſion due from every Particular Church to the General, as it concernes the Act of this Nationall Church in the Reformation, more largely in the firſt Chapter of my later Book. For the preſent we are to ſpeak of the poſſibility of diſſent of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours from Superiours, and the uſe of reaſon and judgement neceſſary to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:61464:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Poſſibility of juſt diſſenting.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ſubmiſſion and obedience ſpoken of as due to Superiours, and their Judgement, ought to take place in all caſes, where there is not ſomething clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt them, that confeſſedly excels the Authority and Judgement of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Governours: as evidence of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, demonſtration of reaſon, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable conſent of Primitive Times, the pure Ages of the Church.</p>
               <p>Now that ſuch a caſe, or ſuch a cauſe of uſing private judgement even to a diſſenting from the publike, may happen, Reaſon and Experience tells us. Becauſe it is poſſible, that ſuch as have chief place in the publike Judgement (National or General) may neglect their duty (at leaſt the greater number of them to the overbearing of the leſſe) and through prejudice of Faction, or other wordly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, may faile in determining and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the Truth. (For the promiſe of guiding them is conditional upon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming duty, and that is not alwaies certaine in the greater part) to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61464:31"/>of falſe Belief, and falſe Worſhip; So that it comes to be <hi>Error manifeſtus,</hi> appearing ſo to be, both by the Word of God, and the conformable beliefe and practiſe of the firſter Ages of the Church. Here is place for Reaſon and Judgement of Inferiours to diſſent upon ſuch Evidence, after modeſt propoſall, and demonſtration of the Errour. And to this in part accords the conceſſion of <hi>Bell. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Concil.</hi> Inferiours may not judge, whether their Superiours have lawfully proceeded, <hi>niſi manifeſtiſſimè conſtet intolerabilem errorem committi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now when I ſpeak of private Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment diſſenting from the publick Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or generall practiſes of the Church, and of the preſervation of Truth, and the Faith thereby, I doe not ſpeak of the Reaſon or Judgement of the People or Laity divided from all their Guides and Paſtors, but I include theſe; who (of what ranke ſoever) diſſenting from the publick, either definition or practiſe, are as men of private judgement in ſuch a caſe. Theſe, I ſay, I alwayes include in ſuch a juſt diſſenting or falling off from any erroneous belief or practiſe prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Church. For it cannot be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61464:31"/>that God, who promiſed to be with them, and guide them, ſhould take away his Truth from all the Guides and Paſtors of his Church, and preſerve it by the Judgement and Conſcience of Lay peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but that ſtill, however they which have chiefe place in the Church prove corrupt, ſome Guides and Paſtors (though of leſſe number and place) ſhall be they that ſhall detect the prevailing Errours, and preſerve the Truth: and this by due uſe of Reaſon and private Judgement. Experience alſo tels us, what they have proved that have been in chiefe place; that have ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chair, and in St. <hi>Peters;</hi> how many Hereticks at ſeverall times among the Popes; how a whole ſucceſſion of Monſters through the tenth Age; of which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> complaines, and <hi>Baronius</hi> cryes out, <hi>Quae facies Rom. Eccleſiae!</hi> when infamous Strumpets diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of Biſhopricks, yea thruſt their Paramours <hi>(Amaſios ſuos)</hi> into <hi>Peters</hi> Chaire! What Cardinals then made? what Biſhops then ordained by ſuch Monſters? and <hi>ſtertentibus omnibus, all in a manner being aſleep,</hi>—So he. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience alſo tels us how groſſe Errours have prevailed over the Church: as for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61464:32"/>example: The <hi>Millenary</hi> belief ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, that <hi>Iuſtine Martyr (contra Tryph.)</hi> ſaith, All that were in all points, or throughly Orthodox Chriſtians held it. So alſo the giving of the Communion to Infants after Baptiſm, as neceſſary to their ſalvation, generally held and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in the whole Church for many Ages. I mean more generally than the Romiſh errors have been.</p>
               <p>Now if there were not place for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting by the uſe of private judgment (for ſome one perſon muſt ſpeake firſt in the diſcovering ſuch Errours) there would be a neceſſity of the Churches continuing in Errour. But both thoſe Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours were reformed; and he that ſpake firſt in diſcovering the untruth of them, did it upon the uſe of his private judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, examining the beliefe and practiſe of the Church, &amp; ſhewing the error of it.</p>
               <p>It may be they will ſay, thoſe two Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines were not defined by the Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> by any General Council. So indeed they often excuſe their own Doctors, when they ſet their private judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the generall ſtreame of Antiquity: and by the like equity they might receive our plea; That the beliefe and practiſes
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61464:32"/>we forſooke were not Doctrines defined by the Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> by any lawfull Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council.</p>
               <p>But what if thoſe two had been defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? then no man (will they ſay) ought to have queſtioned them, or uſed his private judgement againſt them. But then muſt we ſay, if any thing be defined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs, the Church muſt continue in errour, and an after General Council cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it. But if things before defined may be corrected or reverſed by the like Authority, how can it come about but by the diſcovering of the former errour, and that upon the uſe of private Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, examing the definitions, and ſhewing the error to the Church? And that which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> grants (as I ſaid a little before) <hi>Niſi manifeſtiſſimè conſtet errorem ïntolerabilem committi,</hi> ſuppoſes ſuch error may be committed and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. But how can this later come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, but upon the uſe of private Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Inferiours? and while the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of Trent</hi> was not received in <hi>France,</hi> was it not upon the uſe of their Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt that Council, which with the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> paſſeth for General? or how can Moderate Papiſts think the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61464:33"/>of the Catholick Church to be the beſt confirmation of the Decrees of a Council, if not allow private Judgement in the examining and receiving them? And ſeeing a General Council hath its power from the diffuſive Catholick Church, of which it is the repreſentation, however the Definitions of it may have more form of Law, yet not more weight to preſſe the judgement or conſcience, than what is generally believed and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed through the whole Church, as that of Infant Communion was.</p>
               <p>We therefore leave men no otherwiſe to their reaſon and judgement, than rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and neceſſity enforceth, no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than Chriſt and his Apoſtles left them. Reaſon enforceth it (as we heard) both in regard of the Church, which cannot elſe be reformed from prevailing errours; and in regard of every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Man, who is to give account of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, is to be ſaved by his own Faith, and periſhes upon his own ſcore. They were not excuſed if ſeduced by their Prophets and Teachers, as <hi>Iſa</hi> 9.14, 15, 16. <hi>The Leaders of this people cauſe them to erre, and they that are led are deſtroyed</hi>—Alſo, <hi>Head and Tail, ruſh, and branch,</hi> both cut
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61464:33"/>off, and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.6, and 8 Thoſe that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh through the Prophets default, <hi>their blood</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>is on their own head.</hi> Anſwerably, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.14. They are not excuſed that blindly follow their Leaders, <hi>both fall into the ditch.</hi> The Romaniſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject this, as not applicable to the Guides of their Church, anſwering in effect as the Phariſees (who alſo had chief place in the Church) <hi>are we alſo blind?</hi> Joh. 9. and we may reply, as our Saviour did; <hi>You ſay, We ſee, therefore your ſin remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;</hi> therefore your blindneſſe is more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureable.</p>
               <p>Again, our Saviour and his Apoſtles left men the uſe of their reaſon and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in diſcerning what is taught them in and by the Church: For they enjoyn the uſe of it as a duty; as when our Saviour bids, <hi>Search the Scriptures.</hi> Joh. 5.39. <hi>And take heed how you hear,</hi> Luk. 8.18. <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets, and by their fruits ye ſhall know them,</hi> Mat. 7.15. <hi>And beware of the Leaven of the Phariſees,</hi> Mat. 16. v. 11. that is, <hi>their Doctrine,</hi> ver. 12. Now ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this laſt place, that which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.2. <hi>The Scribes and Phariſees ſit in</hi> Moſes <hi>Chair, all therefore that they bid you obſerve, that obſerve and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61464:34"/>doe:</hi> How can theſe be reconciled <hi>(obſerve whatſoever they teach, and yet beware of the Leaven of their Doctrine)</hi> without al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Judgement of diſcretion in the hearer? So the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. forbids the receiving of any other Goſpel, though preacht from Heaven by an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel. How ſhould the <hi>Galatians</hi> know a difference 'twixt the Goſpel and Faith once delivered, and any other new one, but by uſing Reaſon and Judgement? To the ſame purpoſe he bids, <hi>Prove all things, hold fast that which is good,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.21. <hi>Try the Spirit,</hi> 1 Joh 4.1. The Romaniſts anſwer, that theſe Precepts of <hi>Proving</hi> and <hi>Trying,</hi> are ſpoken to the Guides of the People. We ſay, that is true, to them chiefly ſpoken, and yet to the People too: to the Guides and Paſtors in order to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming and caſting out Errors prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (in which reſpect we plead for uſe of Reaſon and Judgement to be allowed, not to the people ſo much, but to their guides) alſo in order to the keeping out Errours, which falſe Teachers would bring in, to the ſeducing of the people; for their Guides are to judge for them. But ſtill that <hi>Proving</hi> and <hi>Trying,</hi> that <hi>taking heed</hi> belongs alſo to the People, and implyes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61464:34"/>their uſe of Reaſon and Judgement, not in order to Reſorming or Judging for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but in order to their own believing, or receiving what is taught &amp; propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to them. The Apoſtle calls to them, <hi>Iudge what I ſay,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.15. <hi>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udge in your ſelves,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. <hi>And the spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al man judgeth all things,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.15. He ſpeakes of things taught in the Church, and of the Spiritual mans judging them, in order to his own beleeving; to which purpoſe, Saint <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 2.27. <hi>The Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſhall teach you all things,</hi> viz. ſo as to underſtand all things neceſſary to their Salvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>How far the Romaniſts leave men the uſe of their Reaſon and Judgement.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SEE we now what uſe of Reaſon and Judgement the Romaniſts allow to Men. They ſpeake to the Reaſon and Judgement of Men, whom they would bring in unto them, uſe Motives and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to perſwade their Religion, and the Authority of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But if they ſuffer themſelves to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61464:35"/>to embrace that Authority upon ſuch Reaſons and Motives, they muſt then reſigne up their Reaſon and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wholly. Thus have they leave to uſe their ſight in finding out that Church, but when they have found it, then they muſt follow it blindfold, or looke but one way, that way onely that that ſhe directs, and take all upon truſt of her Infallible guidance. They will ſay they commend the Definitions of the Church to the judgement and conſciences of the people, alleadging Reaſons, and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies from the Scriptures and Fathers; and this in order to better perſwaſion; ſo far it is well. But then their Reaſon and Judgement is abſolutely bound to look that way onely, and to ſee nothing againſt the definition of the Church: No, though ſhe defines it is not againſt Chirſts inſtitution to allow the people the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but in one kind: or that it is lawfull to adore Images, as ſhe has done in her Council of <hi>Trent.</hi> A man had as good ſpare his labour in uſing his Reaſon and Judgement to examine their proofs, as having done all, to be abſolutely conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and bound up. Which no queſtion goes very hard with many of their more
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61464:35"/>learned Men, who ſee more reaſon and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence againſt, than for what they are bound by the Church to believe and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; and ſo are ground between the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of their Church, and the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Conſcience, as between the upper and nether Milſtone. Hence that conſcionable cunning of the <hi>Belgick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitours,</hi> who in their <hi>Index Expurgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> 1571. confeſſe, when they meet with the Antients ſpeaking otherwiſe than their Church, <hi>quovis commente</hi>—they uſe any ſhift to remedy it.</p>
               <p>We read how it fared with ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines in the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi> Who (while their Articles were under delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration undefined) honeſtly propoſing their doubts and arguments againſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſenſe of the prevailing party, were cryed out on as <hi>Lutherans;</hi> and ſome of them not ſuffered to ſpeak more, were ſent away: ſo free was that Council! What ſhall we think now after the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are made, but that mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, judgements, tongues are bound up, not to doubt, think, or modeſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound any thing againſt them without the note of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and danger of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:61464:36"/>
               <p>But ſee we what follows upon their Conceſſions: To finde out the Church they allow (as we heard) the uſe of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Judgement. Now that muſt be by examining her marks; and ſeeing a chief marke of the Church is <hi>Sanctitas doctrinae</hi> (as <hi>Bellar.</hi> and others doe truly acknowledge) it implyes a judging of all her Doctrines, before a Man can truly know by the purity of them, that this is the Church.</p>
               <p>Again, when the Church is found out, yet ſtill the queſtion remains, whether it be Infallible? there alſo muſt the uſe of Reaſon and Judgment be allowed; for no reaſon it ſhould be taken upon her own word, that ſhe is the onely Infallible guide. Therefore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to ſay (though untruly) that the Infallibility of the Romiſh Church, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils and Popes, ſtands upon <hi>apertas pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſiones,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of this at large below; Chap. 27.</note> naming <hi>Act.</hi> 15. <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum eſt Spiritui ſancto &amp; nobis,</hi> and <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. <hi>Rogavi pro te ut non deficiat fides, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de verbo Dei, cap.</hi> 14. Now if theſe places, and all other they bring to that purpoſe, be acknowledged ſo plain, that it is eaſie for any man, uſing his Reaſon
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61464:36"/>and Judgment to ſee this priviledge of the Roman Church in them (when as indeed no reaſonable conſequence can draw it out of them) who cannot but juſtly ſay, the places of Scripture we bring againſt their Errours are more open and plain to him that will duly uſe his Reaſon and Judgement?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of knowing the Church by the marks of</hi> Eminencie, Perpetuity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>CArdinal <hi>Perron,</hi> in his firſt book, <hi>cap.</hi> 5. and 6. againſt the Kings Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſeems to cut the buſineſſe ſhorter, and to leave men the uſe of Reaſon and Judgement in knowing the Church, not by examining her Doctrines, but by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering her external, and more ſenſible marks, ſuch as are eaſie and proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to every mans capacity, <hi>viz. Eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, Amplitude, Perpetuity,</hi> or <hi>Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> and the like. And when the Church is known by theſe, then a man is to know by her the ſenſe of places of Scripture, which need interpretation. But what he ſaith for this eaſie diſcovery of the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61464:37"/>out of Scripture, <hi>A City on an Hill can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be hid,</hi> Mat. 5. was ſpoken by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the Apoſtles, and their preaching of the Goſpel; and if applyed to the Church, it does not prove ſhe can alwaies be known by theſe marks. Nor does St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s application of that Scripture, to the knowing of the Church in his time, imply the Church ſhall alwaies be ſo. Not ſo now, when it ſtands divided by <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt,</hi> the Eaſtern Church chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging theſe marks as well as the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern; Unleſſe it come ſhort of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church in <hi>Eminencie</hi> of outward ſplendor, when as it is more Chriſtian— like to continue under preſſures ſo many yeares; the Romiſh Church may be emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for pomp, and have more of the world in it, but the Greek Church is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent for ſufferings, and has had more of the Croſſe. Now ſeeing the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, which has theſe marks, is in the Roman account heretical, and the Roman Church likewiſe condemned by the Greek, how ſhall a man know which of theſe to joyn to, but by examining their Doctrine, and judging of it?</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cardinals</hi> ſimilitude of a Teſtator (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ordaining one to be the Interpreter of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61464:37"/>his Teſtament, that has a name common to others, and therefore aſſigning marks to know him by, ſo clear that they need no Interpreter) cleares not the buſineſſe. For did ever any hear of an Executor, or Interpreter of a Teſtament markt out by his gray head or <hi>antiquity,</hi> by tallneſſe of ſtature, <hi>amplitude,</hi> or <hi>eminencie</hi> of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or eſtate, when his proper name and habitation would readily and ſufficiently diſtinguiſh him from all others? So had God markt out unto us in his Teſtament, that Church, which ſhould in all Ages be the infallible Interpreter of his Will, by the name <hi>Roman,</hi> and place of habitation, and in ſtead of <hi>a City built on a Hill</hi> (the Scripture ſo oft repeated by the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal)</hi> ſaid, <hi>a City built on ſeven Hills,</hi> there needed no more to doe, but ſubmit Reaſon and Judgement to all which that Church commanded.</p>
               <p>But ſeeing he has not done it, no not when occaſion of mentioning ſuch a priviledge, had any ſuch belonged to that Church, (I meane when St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to the <hi>Romans:</hi>) it is plain he has left us to know his Church by her Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine agreeable to his Word; for ſo muſt we hear the voice of the Sheepherd, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61464:38"/>when Churches of ſeveral Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions may challenge the former markes, the Greek as well as the Roman.</p>
               <p>Now what hath been ſaid againſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church by theſe markes, is not ſpoken, to deny the Roman (which chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges them) to be a Church, but that they mark her out for ſuch a Church as the Cardinal would have us take her for; ſuch a Church as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>viz. the Catholike Church,</hi> the Church, in which onely the Paſtors voice is to be heard, for what ſhe pretends to by theſe marks alone, ſhe muſt allow to the Greek Church alſo. It is not theſe barely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſideration of doctrine, that could marke her out for a true Church, but that ſhe ſtill together with theſe holds the foundation. And in regard of that we acknowledge the Paſtors voice was ſtill heard in her, yet ſo that the voice of falſe Shepheards have often out-cryed him, yea, cryed him down in many points of high concernment to his ſheep. Yet by Gods providence his voice was ſtill heard, and his Word or Scripture ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, whereby the voice of falſe Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards might be diſcerned from the true one, the Errors and Superſtitions prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61464:38"/>known from the Truth and faith once delivered.</p>
               <p>When the voice of the great Paſtor (<hi>except ye eat the fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.) was generally miſtaken in the Church, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applyed to the communicating of Infants, there was enough of his voice and word ſtill heard in the Church to diſcover the Error, and reſtore the Truth. When Image-worſhip was cryed up by the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Nicene Council,</hi> and advanced in the <hi>Weſt</hi> by the Romiſh Biſhops, yet was there enough in the word and voice of the Shepheard (known in the Church) to condemn it in the Council of <hi>Frankford,</hi> and elſwhere. When Pope <hi>John</hi> 22. defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the place of faithfull Souls to be out of Heaven till the Reſurrection, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned it to be profeſſed by thoſe that took degrees in the Univerſities: yet was there enough ſtill in that Church to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn it in the Council of <hi>Florence.</hi> When the voice of the Shepheard in thoſe places, <hi>Feed my ſheep,</hi> Joh. 21.16. <hi>Thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and upon this Rock</hi>—Mat. 16.18. <hi>I have prayed for thee</hi>—Luk. 22.32. was miſtaken, and miſ-applyed for ſome Ages, to advance the Popes Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and power over all, there was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61464:39"/>ſeen by the Council of <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Conſtance</hi> to define the contrary, and conclude a Council to be above him. And however the noyſe again is greater in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for the Pope than a Council, yet is there enough ſtill heard in that Church by the <hi>French</hi> generally, and all moderate <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> to know the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth of it. So we ſay, whatever becomes of the Cardinals marks, <hi>Eminencie, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie,</hi> &amp;c. (by which he would have her marked out for the onely Church, in which the Paſtors voice is to be heard) the Romiſh Church hath failed in her doctrine, cryed up Errours and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet ſo, that the Paſtors voice hath been heard, and his word ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved there, that enough to diſcover them.</p>
               <p>And now to ſome applying of what hdth been ſaid touching uſe of Reaſon and Judgement, to our Caſe of Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. We examined the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> by the Marks, <hi>Eminencie, Antiquity, Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion;</hi> We ſee they agree not to that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, nor that in Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as he applyed the like Marks to the Catholike Church: Nor doe they imply that Church, where barely found, to be
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:61464:39"/>a Church deſigned by God, to remaine uncorrupt, much leſſe to be the Infallible Interpreter of his Teſtament.</p>
               <p>Alſo we examined that Church by that maine mark of <hi>Sanctity of Doctrine</hi> (u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our Reaſon and Judgement (which they allow in this point) and that the judgement of a National Church) and found her ſo far from being Infallible, that ſhe was groſly corrupted in her Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and Worſhip: Of which we had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent conviction from the evidence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boveſaid, to wit, Scripture and Primitive practiſe, either of which excels the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and authority of the preſent Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Our way opens not a gap to Sectaries.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw to the laſt part of the Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>The opening hereby of a Gap to all Hereſie and Schiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Due uſe of Reaſon and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment does it not; Sectaries that are gone out from us, cannot, 1. Pretend to ſuch a way of Reforming the Church, or to ſuch a Judgement as our Reformation was
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:61464:40"/>brought about by; they wanting the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which is needfull to it in every National Church. They as Members of this Church owed obedience and ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Government and Governours thereof, by divine precept; and could doe nothing as to a Reformation more than private men; whereas the Church of <hi>England</hi> (if under the Patriarchate of <hi>Rome,</hi> according to Eccleſiaſtical Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non; which would not have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended about; yet) ſtood not bound to the uſurped power thereof; but being a National Church, might juſtly eject that Uſurpation, and make Reformation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſelf of all Errors, maintained by that pretended Power and Authority.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As for that, wherein they diſſent from this Church, they cannot pretend to ſuch Evidence we ſpoke of; they doe not at all pretend to the practiſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the firſt Ages, nor have they plain and evident Scripture, but places unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly wreſted. The Evidence required in diſſenting from Authority, is ſuch as by expreſſe words, or direct conſequence is apparent to all that can uſe their Reaſon without prejudice of ſelf-intereſt or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. But we muſt note a different evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:61464:40"/>in regard of things propounded by the Church, as matters of Faith and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip— and things enjoyned, as circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials of Worſhip, or pertaining to Order, Diſcipline. In the firſt ſort the Church indeed ſtands bound to ſhew them evidently out of Gods Word, to be ſuch, before they can be received by faith and full aſſent for ſuch; becauſe it is the office of the Church, or Governours thereof, not to make ſuch, but to declare and propound them: But they that will charge the Church in thoſe Propoſals with Hereſie, Superſtition, or Idolatry, muſt have the full and apparent evidence aforeſaid. In the ſecond ſort, Things Circumſtantial, and of Order, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded only for ſuch by the Church, they that diſſent and refuſe to yeeld obedience, muſt have moſt cleare evidence that ſuch things are unlawfull and forbidden by Gods Word, becauſe that Word of God moſt evidently gives power to the Church, to make, conſtitute, and ordaine ſuch things, and expreſly commands obedience to Superiours. Now for the things which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> propounded and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed as matters of Faith and Worſhip; as ſhe had not evidence for them out of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61464:41"/>Gods Word, which was enough for our refuſing them as matters of Faith and Worſhip, ſo we had ſufficient evidence of Scripture and Antiquity againſt them. Whereas all that this Church of <hi>England</hi> propounds as matter of Faith and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, is moſt clear by Scripture, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Antiquity: So that it is moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable for our Sectaries to deny it, and impoſſible for them to have evidence againſt it. Much leſſe is it poſſible for them to be convinced out of Gods Word of the unlawfulneſſe of circumſtantials and matters enjoyned, as of Order, and to have as apparent evidence for that conviction, as Gods Word gives them for obedience to their lawfull Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Their pretending to be convinced in their judgement, hinders not the Church of which they were members, to uſe her own judgement, and accordingly to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by cenſure and excommunication, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid above, <hi>cap.</hi> 9. And hereby was this Church held together in Unity, no Sect or Hereſie breaking forth which was not preſently cruſhed, till force of Arms bore down the free uſe of Eccleſiaſtick Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and emboldened men to contemn it
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:61464:41"/>If therefore Sectaries ſhall ſay to us, you allow us to uſe our Reaſon and Judgment in what you teach us. True, ſay we, for your own ſatisfaction, but not to abuſe it againſt the Church. But we doe not, ſay they, abuſe it, but have conſulted our Guides, and uſed all meanes we can for ſatisfaction. We tell them, you muſt bring evident Scripture and Demonſtration a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt publick Authority of the Church, &amp; having modeſtly propounded it, attend the judgement thereof, to which if you cannot aſſent inwardly, yet yeild an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erhal peaceable ſubjection, ſo far as the matter queſtioned is capable of it, (which I adde becauſe the matter queſtioned may be not ſo much in belief and opinion, as in worſhip and external practiſe:) For that muſt neceſſarily diſcover it ſelf: and if it be ſuch in any Church, that a man cannot in conſcience comply with, and therefore cannot yeild external ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſo far as to doe or perform the ſame worſhip or practice; yet ought he ſtill to yeild a peaceable ſubjection, in not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting or reviling, but quietly ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (if need be) for the ſame un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Authority. But you that diſſent from the Church of <hi>England</hi> have no
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:61464:42"/>ſuch cauſe for any thing belonging to the ſubſtance of Worſhip: And as for Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantials and matters of Order, ye ought to ſhew as direct Scripture againſt the particulars, as that which commands you to <hi>obey them which are over you.</hi> And if your miſ-informed conſcience bade you forbear to ſubmit to the doing of things enjoyned, yet ſhould you have had ſo much conſcience of the expreſſe precept commanding obedience to Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, as to forbear reſiſtance and force, and to have rather quietly and peaceably ſuffered under the cenſures of the Church, and power of Authority ſet over you; and you cannot but think it reaſonable, that the Church, which is entruſted with others as well as you, and hath the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of Authority and publick judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhould upon the not-appearing of your pretended evidence, maintaine her Judgement and Authority, and proceed againſt you, as the preſervation of Peace and Unity requires. And thinke not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are allowed to uſe your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Underſtanding in order to your beleeving and reaſonable ſerving of God, you are therefore allowed to uſe force in order to the maintaining of your diſſent
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:61464:42"/>from, and diſobedience to Authority: For that God whoſe Truth and Service ye ſo much pretend, is <hi>the God of Order and Peace</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33.) not the Author of Confuſion; ſuch as your violence has wrought in this Church and Land.</p>
               <p>No other meanes or remedy has the Church to preſerve Unity, than by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrating the Truth to every mans conſcience, and cenſuring or caſting out the Refractory. Nor other feare can ſhe caſt upon her children to keep them in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, than the loſſe of her Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and their Anſwering it to God. Nor was there any other Remedy in the Antient Church, while deſtitute of help from the Secular power, I meane no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Remedy proper to the ſociety of the Church, to keep men in her Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Their vain pretence of Infallibility.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre the Romaniſts lay hold on a ſeeming advantage by pretence of an Infallible guidance in their Church, telling their Proſelytes, that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61464:43"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:61464:43"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:61464:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:61464:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:61464:45"/>acknowledge their Church fallible in her Propoſals, and therefore muſt leave men to their own reaſon and judgement, but our Church is infallible in her Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. How we Proteſtants leave men the uſe of their Reaſon and Judgement, rather than leave them to their Reaſon &amp; Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, has been ſhewn already; and to the Romiſh pretence of Infallible guidance, we ſay ſtill, could it be made good, there would be no more to doe, but every man upon underſtanding the terms and ſenſe of her Definitions, to ſubmit his Reaſon and Judgement without farther enquiry, how conſonant they are to Gods revealed will, and what warrant he has from thence to aſſent and believe them. But here's the weakneſſe and vanity of that pretence: This Infallibility which is pretended as the ground of all their belief, has no ground it ſelfe to be believed (
<note n="*" place="margin">See below Chap. 27. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> as we ſhew by many moſt evident arguments) and that which is alledged to take away mens Reaſon and Judgement, muſt allow every man his Reaſon and Judgment in the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of what is brought to prove it, as was ſhewn above, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it will be harder to make men believe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:61464:45"/>that pretence of Infallibility, than to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the propoſals of Truth, from Guides that pretend not to it, but onely to the demonſtration of that Truth by an Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Rule.</p>
               <p>Hence it is eaſie to ſee, which is more reaſonable and likely to keep men in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Church; Open and plaine dealing with them in the buſineſſe of their ſalvation, or falſe pretences? The demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Truth to every mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or the Imperious dominion over other mens faith and conſciences, under pretence of Infallibility?</p>
               <p>We ſay to men, If you will be with us, you ſhall ſee what you doe: we require your obedience to what we demonſtrate to be Gods will, for you to believe and doe, yet know your ſalvation is concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſuch obedience, and be it at your ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt peril to gainſay.</p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſaith to men, If you will come to me, you muſt put out your Eyes, reſign up your Reaſon and Underſtanding, and with implicite Faith give abſolute ſubmiſſion and obedience to my Definitions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:61464:46"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Dividing from the Roman Church is not a dividing from the Catholike.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANother of their maine Objections upon our diviſion from them, is, That, whatever the Doctrine or Faith be which we retained, we divided from the whole <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> holding Communion with no part of it. To the ſame purpoſe is that which Cardinal <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> (in his Letter to M. <hi>Caſaubon,</hi> and in his <hi>firſt book against the Kings Letter</hi>) alledgeth, That to be Catholike, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the note of Schiſm, is not ſufficient to hold the ſame Faith with the Catholike Church (for ſo did the <hi>Donatiſts</hi>) but to hold Communion alſo with it; which the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> not doing, were Schiſmaticks: And in like manner he would conclude us to be.</p>
               <p>Our Anſwer in generall is briefly this, That we did not divide from the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, and that to a Communion with it is not required a full agreement in belief and practiſe with other parts of it: No nor an actual Communion with them alwaies, and ſimply neceſſary: and that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:61464:46"/>our Caſe and the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> is different, as St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s and their caſe was.</p>
               <p>Now to clear theſe more fully. We ſay firſt: It was neither our intent (when we reformed) to divide from the Catholike Church, or any part of it, neither did we. We onely ſought to reforme our ſelves, leaving them to themſelves. We had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to doe only with the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> which being a particular Church, as it may utterly faile, without failing of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, ſo may it ſurely be in ſuch a meaſure corrupted, that it deſerves to be divided from. Yet our aime and intent was only to leave the Errours and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions we practiſed with her, and ſo to leave her no farther than her Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was mixed with thoſe Superſtitious practiſes, <hi>i.e</hi> to leave her no farther than ſhe had left her ſelf (as we can prove) or receded from what ſhe was for belief and practiſe in the more antient and purer Times.</p>
               <p>Now here's the uſual miſtake, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Romaniſts part the common pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice againſt us; that they ſtill take the <hi>Roman Church</hi> and her Communion for the <hi>Catholike,</hi> and what they meet with in the Fathers touching the <hi>Catholike
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:61464:47"/>Church</hi> to this or like purpoſe (that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with it is neceſſary, that there is no ſalvation out of it) they apply to the <hi>Roman,</hi> or touching Communion with the <hi>Roman</hi> Church or Biſhop, to the proving any man Catholike thereby: They appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate it to that Church as a ſpecial prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, when as the Fathers did alſo prove the like by communion with other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Biſhops, confeſſedly Catholike, although not ſo frequently, becauſe Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church and Biſhop of it was then of all other moſt eminent. Upon this double miſapplication, thoſe many Teſtimonies which Cardinal <hi>Perron</hi> (in his Epiſtle and Anſwer) has heaped up out of St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> and others, come to no purpoſe: For to be <hi>Extra Eceleſiam Romanam,</hi> is not preſently to be <hi>Extra Catholicam.</hi> For though it was a good argument of old, when that Church was eminently and confeſſedly ſound, to conclude affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, as the Fathers often did) ſuch were good Catholiques, becauſe in Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with that Church; yet now ſince <hi>Rome</hi> is notoriouſly corrupt and unſound, the argument will not hold, to conclude Affirmatively. Much leſſe will it hold Negatively, to argue, ſuch are no Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:61464:47"/>becauſe not in Communion with <hi>Rome.</hi> Nay when <hi>Rome</hi> of old was ſound in Belief and Doctrine, it did not alwaies conclude the Negative (as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by the Inſtances below of the <hi>Aſian</hi> and <hi>Afriean</hi> Churches out of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the <hi>Roman</hi>) much leſſe can it conclude Negatively now.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>The Greek Church, a Church, and part of the Catholick.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FUrthermore, beſides the <hi>Roman</hi> we acknowledge other Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches parts of the Catholique, and we ſay wee are not out of Communion with them, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is by an actuall declaring of Non-communion to each other: For though wee agree not with thoſe Churches, in all doctrines and practiſes (which is not <hi>De facto,</hi> neceſſary to the holding of Communion 'twixt parts of the Catholick) yet we holding them ſtill parts of the Catholick Church, and they us, and not pronouncing Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communion to each other, we both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the Unity or Matrice (as <hi>Cyprian</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:61464:48"/>phraſes it) of the Catholike Church.</p>
               <p>Now as to our opinion of the Greek Church, we conceive, their denying the proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt to be <hi>from</hi> the Son, but yeelding it to be <hi>by</hi> the Son, to be onely a difference in form of ſpeech, not of any Heretical meaning, as they are acquitted by ſome learned Romaniſts.</p>
               <p>And for their opinion and judgement of us, we ſay, that Cenſure of <hi>Jeremias</hi> one of their Patriarchs, (which the Romaniſts object againſt us as condemning the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Doctrine in many points) is not found to be warranted by any Authority of the Greek Church: and to it we may oppoſe the judgement of <hi>Cyril</hi> their late Patriarch, who approves our Church and doctrine.</p>
               <p>But they ask, ſeeing we left the <hi>Roman,</hi> why did we not joyne to the <hi>Greek,</hi> or ſome other Church, or part of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> We were joyned with them in the Catholick Church, (as ſaid before) but if by joyning our ſelves to ſome other Church, they meane holding and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as that Church doth, we ſay againe (as above) ſuch agreement between the parts of the Catholick, is not neceſſary
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:61464:48"/>to Catholick Communion. 2. We ſay, it was not neceſſary for us. Firſt, becauſe we were a National Church, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not bound to joyn ſo, as to put our ſelves under any particular Church of one denomination. Private perſons indeed are bound ſo to be joyned to one Church or other which are parts of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. Secondly, becauſe our worke was Reformation, and caſting off the Romiſh Errours, and wee ſaw no particular Church, but needed Reformation very much; and therefore we could not joyne to any ſo as to agree with them in all do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and practiſes.</p>
               <p>Theſe conſiderations ſhew, the many Teſtimonies brought out of the Fathers by the Romaniſts, for neceſſity of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, come not home to our caſe. For as they are abuſed when applyed to the Communion of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> (as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove noted) ſo are they not altogether applicable to the Catholick Church now, as it ſtands in a condition far different from what it was in St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time. At the time of the Reformation, it was found divided in two parts, accuſing each other of Errour and Schiſm: It was our part then to conſider, what Errours we
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:61464:49"/>had received by communion with the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church,</hi> and finding them to be many and great, it was not for us to make any other part of the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> a rule or pattern of Reformation, but to look to Gods Word, and the Primitive practiſe, when the Catholike Church was in ſuch an intire eſtate, that the above mentioned Teſtimonies were truly appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to her. Which Church is by both ſides confeſſed and acknowledged to have been ſo right and ſound, that none could have cauſe to leave the Communion of any part of her; Which Church alſo muſt be acknowledged to be of more Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty than the preſent <hi>Romiſh</hi> or <hi>Greeke</hi> Church. From that Word of God was our Rule, from that Primitive Church was our pattern, and by holding to that rule, and pattern, as neare as we could, if we ceaſe to believe and practiſe many things as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth, or not agree in all doctrines and practiſes with other parts of the Catholique Church, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid for that to have no Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Catholike Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:61464:49"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>Of agreement and external Communion twixt the parts of the Catholike Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt further to cleare this point of actual communion and agreement betweene the parts of the Catholique Church by ſome Inſtances. In the points of <hi>keeping Eaſter,</hi> and <hi>Rebaptization,</hi> it is evident,</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the <hi>Aſian</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> in the one, and the <hi>African</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> in the other, did not agree for doctrine and practiſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that they could not commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate one with the other, not onely in the keeping <hi>Eaſter,</hi> or in the very practiſe of <hi>Rebaptization;</hi> but thoſe that held Rebaptization neceſſary, could not at all communicate with any of thoſe members of the Catholike Church, which had been received from hereſie, without being baptized again.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that upon the heat of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Biſhops (<hi>Victor</hi> and <hi>Stephen</hi>) in theſe two buſineſſes, it came to an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall denying of Communion with
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:61464:50"/>the <hi>Aſian and African</hi> Churches.</p>
               <p>What Cardinall <hi>Perron</hi> concludes upon thoſe Churches ſo ſtanding out, as to the point of Schiſm, he has not expreſly declared, notwithſtanding he treates of both their oppoſitions againſt the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> then being. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. &amp; 3.) Hee ſeemes indeed to leave the <hi>Aſians</hi> under Schiſme: but that is to take the Crown of Martyrdome from many of thoſe godly <hi>Aſian</hi> Biſhops. And we read, that as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and others reproved <hi>Victors</hi> Excommunicating of them, ſo they held them not cut off from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, and profeſſed they would not deny to communicate with them, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> witneſſeth <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Hiſt. Eccleſ.</hi> After-ages alſo have excuſed them: And the like charity (if the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts had it for us) might excuſe us; or rather commend what we have done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:61464:50"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>The want of that does not alwaies make guilty of Schiſm.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YEt hence appears, that which the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal</hi> often preſſeth, that all the Members of the Catholike Church muſt communicate one with another) is onely true of <hi>duty,</hi> ſo they ought to doe and keep themſelves; not of <hi>fact,</hi> or under neceſſity of being guilty of Schiſme, or cut off from the Communion of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church. For we ſee, that neither want of agreement in all doctrines and practiſes does it; nor yet all want of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall or external Communion does it; as when Communion is forborn, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed by one Church to another, without uncharitable denying of one the other to be parts of the Catholike. And the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Fathers ſpeaking of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, upon occaſion of the caſe between the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> and the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> are not to be extended to all actual <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communion,</hi> which often happened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween eminent perſons denying it to each other, and between ſeveral Churches do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the like, yet both remaining in the Catholike.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:61464:51"/>
               <p>To theſe two Inſtances out of Hiſtory, let me adde two other upon ſuppoſall. The errour in the beliefe and practiſe of Communicating Infants prevailed in the Catholike Church generally, and for many Ages, and was reformed without a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council. It muſt be ſuppoſed ſome one National Church did reforme it ſelf, in that belief and practiſe; and it muſt be acknowledged juſtly done; for the whole Catholike Church did accordingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme. Now ſuppoſe it had not, but ſtill perſiſted in that beliefe and practiſe; that National Church which firſt reformed, muſt either have returned to the errour it had juſtly left, or ſtood divided in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion to the reſt of the Catholike Church, at leaſt from thoſe parts of the Catholike Church, that held Infant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion neceſſary, upon the like place of Scripture, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.53. anſwerable, as they thought, to that other, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3 3 concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Baptiſm, which perſiſting in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, that one Sacrament was neceſſary to children as well as the other, could not have admitted thoſe, that reformed, as good Chriſtians, no more than thoſe that ſhould have de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yed Baptiſm to their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Now there did not follow a divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:61464:51"/>becauſe the reſt of the Church fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in the Reformation: But ſuppoſe they had not, I would then learn of the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> whether he would have accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that Nationall Church guilty of Schiſme, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the diviſion of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which had followed upon their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which they did juſtly, &amp; through the default of other Churches in not doing that, which they ſaw good cauſe to doe.</p>
               <p>He that will apply this to the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this National Church, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of the Roman Church in not doing the like, will ſee that want of external Communion does not alwaies cut off from the Catholike Church, and will ſee cauſe alſo of excuſing us.</p>
               <p>My ſecond Inſtance upon ſuppoſall, is from that which was intended in <hi>France.</hi> The League had divided the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes there; but that being broken, the King and his party endeavoured re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with the Pope; and finding him averſe, and ill to be dealt with, it was determined to ſet up in <hi>France</hi> a Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch, and to have no more to doe with the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> and the Perſon was deſigned for it, as the Hiſtory of thoſe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:61464:52"/>Times aſſures us. I would now learne of the <hi>Cardinal</hi> (who was at length the Kings Proxy in his reconcilement to <hi>Rome;</hi> and its like was privy to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne) had this been executed, with what part of the Catholike Church had they communicated? or had they been guilty of Schiſme? If it be ſaid, it was not done, yet it was reſolv'd on, and ſo near to the execution, that a Cardinal told the Pope, As <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeveth had loſt <hi>England,</hi> ſo <hi>Clement</hi> the eighth would loſe <hi>France.</hi> And as it was reſolv'd on, ſo it was thought reaſonable and juſt, by the more conſiderable part of Roman Catholikes in <hi>France (viz.</hi> thoſe that adhered to the King) and to be maintained, if done. So here's the difference, they in <hi>France</hi> had <hi>approved</hi> it, we in <hi>England did</hi> it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIX. <hi>Our caſe and that of the Donatiſts not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd now, that which was objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove by the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> that it's not enough for Catholikes to hold the ſame faith with the Catholike Church, but
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:61464:52"/>muſt hold Communion with it too: we grant moſt true; but then is that rule broken, when men hold not the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or forſake it, as the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> did: who as they had no cauſe in regard of the faith (by reaſon of any dangerous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines or practiſes impoſed on them) to ceaſe from communicating with any part of the Catholike Church, ſo they divided from the whole through the breach of charity, condemning it for no Church, and drawing the communion wholly to themſelves. And in ſome of thoſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences the <hi>Cardinal</hi> alledges out of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the breach or want of charity is expreſt as the reaſon of condem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing the <hi>Donatiſts.</hi> Now as for us, we had juſt cauſe in regard of <hi>the faith once delivered,</hi> to free it and our ſelves from errours and ſuperſtitions, not confining the Church within our Communion, or condemning other Churches as no parts of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. Therefore the caſe of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> cannot concern us, who offended not, either by breach of the Faith, or of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. But the cauſe of Diviſion, or breach of Communion muſt reſt upon the Roman Church, which had neither will to reform as ſhe <hi>ought,</hi> nor yet charity to beare with
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:61464:53"/>them that <hi>did;</hi> and the caſe of the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> does moſt fit that Church, which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitably condemnes <hi>all other,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines the Communion to <hi>her ſelf.</hi> For, as to the <hi>Cardinals</hi> making the caſe of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> and ours the ſame, I would learn of him: Whether, if the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> had onely uſed <hi>their</hi> liberty and judgement in that practiſe of rebaptizing Heretiques, leaving other Churches to their liberty, and (though thinking them in errour for admitting Heretiques without bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them, yet) willing to have Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them, as parts of the Catholike Church (ſaving the practiſes wherein they differed) whether then had they been guilty of Schiſme? If he ſay, Yea: then muſt he condemne Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and all the <hi>African Biſhops:</hi> For they went ſo far, yea farther, to an undervaluing of Pope <hi>Stephens</hi> heat againſt them; who had ſent out the ſentence of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation againſt the Biſhops of <hi>Cappadocia, Cilicia</hi> and <hi>Galatia</hi> (who were in the ſame cauſe with Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi>) and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bade Communion with Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and the <hi>Africans,</hi> and all that held rebap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tization.</p>
               <p>What ever the Cardinal judges of them
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:61464:53"/>as to the point of Schiſme, (for though in his third <hi>Book,</hi> third <hi>Chapter,</hi> he treats of the oppoſitions of Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi> and ſpeakes of the Popes condemning him, yet ſayes nothing directly, as to the judging of him in Schiſm, or out of the Communion of the Church) Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did not judge them ſo, no not when often preſſed by the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> with St. <hi>Cyprians</hi> example, he might with a ready anſwer have turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed off the weight of Authority by leaving the perſon under guilt of Schiſme, as one out of Communion of the Church: but this he did not alwaies ſpeaking honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of him, as of a worthy Martyr, and onely diſproving his reaſons for Rebapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation Nor did after-Ages judge him and the <hi>African</hi> Biſhops, though out of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with <hi>Rome,</hi> to be therefore guilty of Schiſme, condemning notwithſtanding the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> as notorious Schiſmaticks, becauſe in the one there was a bare want of external Communion with <hi>Rome,</hi> without an uncharitable breaking with, or condemning of either the <hi>Roman</hi> or the reſt of the Churches, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>id not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptize; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the other (<hi>viz.</hi> the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts) there was a wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:61464:54"/>with, and uncharitable condemning of the Church.</p>
               <p>By all which may appear: our caſe is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> is like that of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and his <hi>African Biſhops,</hi> want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing communion with the <hi>Roman,</hi> but not therefore out of communion with the <hi>Catholike.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And we have ſo much more advantage in the caſe, that the occaſion of their <hi>non Communion</hi> was the <hi>maintaining of an Errour,</hi> though <hi>tolerable;</hi> the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ours, the <hi>caſting off intolerable Errours.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>Of Hell-Gates not prevailing againſt the Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANother generall Objection they make againſt our dividing from them. If, ſay they, it was for ſuch dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Errours and Superſtitions, as the Proteſtants charge the Roman Church with, then had the Gates of Hell, contrary to our Saviours promiſe, prevailed againſt the Church.</p>
               <p>We anſwer, by denying the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:61464:54"/>For from the charging of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (which is but a part of the Catholike Church) with ſuch errours, it does not follow that Hell-gates have prevailed contrary to our Saviours pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; for they might have totally prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the Roman Church to an utter ſubverſion of it (as of other particular Churches) and yet our Saviours promiſe ſtood firm. How far they have prevailed againſt that Church, the examination of her doctrines for beliefe and practice makes appear. We acknowledge indeed, that Hel-Gates did not prevail againſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to a ſubverſion of the Faith in it, or to a totall infection of the members of it, with all the errours and ſuperſtitions that prevailed in it, and were advanced from time to time, chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by thoſe that had chiefe place in that Church.</p>
               <p>But as to the Catholike Church we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that the Gates of Hell ſhall never prevaile to a ſubverſion, either of all the parts of it, or of ſaving Faith in it: There ſhall alwaies be a Church, and that a Church wherein ſaving Faith ſhall be preſerved, and may be had. And ſo Saint <hi>Auguſtine de Symb. ad Catech. l.</hi> 1.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:61464:55"/>
                  <hi>c.</hi> 5. ſeemes to render the ſenſe of that promiſe, when he repeats it thus; <hi>The Gates of Hell ſhall not overthrow or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer it.</hi> And the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> ſeems plainly to acknowledge what Faith it is, againſt which the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail: Not the now Roman Faith (for by that the Gates of hel have far prevail'd upon the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) but the antient Apoſtolike Faith once delivered, in all Ages profeſſed, and by us Proteſtants re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. For being met at <hi>Trent</hi> to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh their new Faith, they beginne their meeting (as the Antient Councils did) with the confeſſion of the Chriſtian faith, repeating onely that Antient Apoſtolike Faith or Creed; and then adding, <hi>This is the firme and onely Foundation againſt which the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevaile. Seſſ. ſecund. Concil. Trid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Unto this paſſage I had in private this Reply, or cavil rather, returned; If the words of the Council import ſo much, then may the Church of Chriſt caſt off Baptiſm, and return to Circumciſion, and yet hold the foundation, becauſe profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that Faith. But this cavill, or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce, is,</p>
               <p>Firſt, inconſequent, as to the particular
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:61464:55"/>Inſtances, Baptiſm and Circumciſion: For the one, the <hi>Nicene Creed</hi> tels us what a neceſſary conjunction it hath with the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of Remiſſion of ſins in rendring the Articles, thus, <hi>I believe one Baptiſm for the Remiſſion of ſinnes;</hi> and for the other, the Apoſtle tels us, how inconſiſtent it is with the Faith of Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2.3.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it is impertinent, as to my application of that Confeſſion at <hi>Trent:</hi> for I alledged it not to ground any ſuch Inferences upon it againſt the whole Catholike Church, as if the Gates of Hell could prevail againſt it wholly, in all ſorts of Errours, ſaving the Verities and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of thoſe Articles of the Creed; but ſeeing they made that Creed the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their Faith at <hi>Trent,</hi> according to the manner of Antient Councils; and acknowledged it in plaine words to be the onely foundation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I inferre firſt, That a Church holding that Foundation, may groſly erre in other things not ſo immediate to it, and yet be a Church. And indeed the Romiſh Church for theſe many Ages has had no tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Plea to the title and being of a <hi>Church,</hi> but ſo far forth as has held that foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, however clogged with many Errours.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:61464:56"/>
               <p>Secondly, that according to this their confeſſion, their New and additional Faith of <hi>Trent</hi> is not that Catholike Faith againſt which, as pretended, the Gates of Hell cannot prevail.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, it ſhews, the intolerable boldneſſe of the Romiſh Church or Court, which after the <hi>Tridentine</hi> meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing feared not to adde their new Articles to that former Creed, (which they had confeſſed to be the onely foundation) as making up one entire Catholike Faith, and to ſubjoyn <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his Clauſe to it all, <hi>Haec eſt fides Catholica, extra quam, &amp;c. This is the Catholike Faith, without which no ſalvation</hi>— as appeares by <hi>Pius quartus</hi> his Bul, and the Oath which every Biſhop in that Church takes.</p>
               <p>But that the Catholike Church has a promiſe in that large ſenſe Cardinal <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> ſpeakes it <hi>(lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 18.) to continue perpetually pure and uncorrupted in her doctrine, we cannot ſay. We cannot ſay it in the Cardinal's ſenſe, for if we ſpeak of pure and uncorrupted doctrine, he meanes it of ſuch a priviledge and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from Errour as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> challenges, which is not neceſſary to the preſervation of the Catholike
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:61464:56"/>Church and Faith; or if we ſpeak of the Catholick Church, he takes it as moſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly appearing in the chief Paſtors, and their adherents, binding that priviledge and freedom to that ſucceſſion or thoſe that are chief in it: Whereas we grant the Catholike Church wholly according to all the Paſtors and Members of it, ſhall not be infected with any deſtructive or dangerous Errours, but that purity of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Doctrine ſhall be preſerved in it: Yet not bound as a Priviledge to any one Church (as to the <hi>Roman)</hi> or to thoſe that are for Number moſt, and for Place chief in the Church; but that in ſome part or other of the Catholike Church, and by ſome Paſtors it ſhall be preſerved and propagated: They that dreame of a Church alwayes ſo gloriouſly viſible, and ſo apparently holding out Purity of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Saving Truth (as the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts doe) to the end all men may readily finde out the true Church, and eaſily come to the knowledge of that Truth, do not conſider, that God doth ſomtimes for the ſins of Chriſtians, turning his grace into wantonneſſe, make his Word preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous (as 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.) and his ſaving Truth not to be found without difficulty, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:61464:57"/>diligent ſearch after it. We ſee the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers interpreted that promiſe <hi>(the Gates of Hell ſhall not—)</hi> of the <hi>not failing of the Church,</hi> never of the <hi>not erring</hi> of it; and we ſee by experience the contrary. As for example, the Millenary belief, and the excommunicating of Infants (both which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> acknowledge errours) did as generally prevail in the Catholike Church, as any error of their New Faith can be ſaid (which they boaſt often) to be the general belief and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the whole Church.</p>
               <p>We ſay then, The Gates of Hell can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prevaile to the overthrowing of the Fundamental ſaving Faith, or to the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting and extinguiſhing of the Purity of ſaving Doctrine abſolutely through the Catholike Church: but may prevaile very farre and generally over the viſible face of the Church Catholike; <hi>viz.</hi> as it ſhews it ſelf in the parts of it, all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches holding the Foundation: For theſe, conſidered, as above, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their more viſible, and conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous appearance in thoſe that are chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in them for place, and moſt for num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> loſe the purity of Saving Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> though holding the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:61464:57"/>admit of the Superſtructions of hay, ſtubble, and worſe: Errors in belief and practice: And though Hell-Gates may prevaile very farre and generally by Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtructures, yet are they ſuch (at leaſt in ſome particular Churches) as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation may bear: Such as may ſtill be convinced by the Doctrine of Saving Truth preſerved ſtill in the Church. For the Paſtors voice (as was ſaid above, <hi>cap.</hi> 12.) will be ſo heard alwaies in the Church, that the ſtrange voice of falſe Teachers and falſe Doctrines may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, and will by them that have eares to hear, and their ſenſes exerciſed to put a difference between good and evill, true and falſe.</p>
               <p>Now the Romiſh Church (with which we had to doe) had not preſerved the Faith entire without mixture of many Errours and Superſtitions; had not kept the foundation clear from ſuch burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and dangerous Superſtructures: yet has the fundamentall Faith in expreſſe termes been delivered downe in that Church, and ſuch ſaving knowledge, as was ſufficient to diſcern the Foundation from the Superſtructures; the true and ancient Faith, from the new erroneous
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:61464:58"/>Belief; the true Paſtors voice, from the ſtrange Doctrines of unwritten Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. To follow that voice, to caſt off thoſe Superſtructures, to contend for the Faith once delivered, and clear it from ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventitiall errours, that was our duty, and the work of our Reformation.</p>
               <q>And thus far againſt their generall plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pretences. Now to ſome Triall of their particular Doctrines of Belief and Practice, which we have caſt off, as er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous and ſuperſtitious.</q>
               <p>For the way of Triall, The Affirmative in thoſe Doctrines being theirs, it lies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to prove the Doctrines (affirmed by them) to be true and Catholike, by ſuch Rules as are allowable.</p>
               <p>The Rules admitted by both ſides, though not in equal rank, are <hi>Scripture,</hi> and <hi>conſent of Antiquity,</hi> gathered by the Writings of the Fathers, and the Acts of ancient Councils. We ſay, they cannot by theſe make good what they affirm, but ſhew that both make againſt them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:61464:58"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXI. <hi>Of the Tryall of Doctrines by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt for <hi>Scripture.</hi> Whatſoever is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in that <hi>Scripture,</hi> which both ſides admit as Canonical, is likewiſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by both ſides, as of divine Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. But ſuch Scripture is not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by them as a ſufficient Rule for the triall and judging of the controverted points; therefore they are neceſſitated to fly to <hi>Tradition;</hi> not that which delivers down to us the ſenſe of any Scripture, by the conſent of all Ages of the Church, but to unwritten Traditions, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver Doctrines of Beliefe and Practiſe that have not footing in Scriptures. This I note, becauſe they are ready to abuſe the unwary, by urging ſometimes the former ſort, to make them ſwallow unwritten Traditions upon the ſame pretence. For the former ſort we grant, as appears by the points of Chriſtianity not controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted between us, becauſe theſe points as they are grounded on Scripture, ſo are they brought down to us by the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:61464:59"/>and tradition of all Ages, as the confeſſed ſenſe of thoſe Scriptures on which they are grounded, and this not derogatory to the ſufficiency of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. But to their other ſort of Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>viz. unwritten</hi> (on which they ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ground their Doctrines rejected by us) we cannot admit as any ground of Faith or Worſhip: ſuch Traditions being uncertain, not poſſibly to be proved A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical, but received upon the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their preſent Church, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed generally inconſiſtent with Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. Yet are we to note, that in all the controverted points they pretend Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and alledge ſeveral places in every point; yea in thoſe points which they themſelves confeſs (as moſt of the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted points are by the moſt ingenuous Romaniſts confeſſed) to have no ground or footing in Scripture. To let paſſe the want of candor and plain dealing in this, we muſt obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> that their labouring to pretend Scripture for every Doctrine, is a tacite acknowledgement that doctrines of Faith and Religion ſhould have their ground there. For inſtance; Invocation of Saints they acknowledge not uſed in the Old
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:61464:59"/>Teſtament, yea and give us reaſon for it, becauſe the ſouls of the Patriarchs were not then in heaven, and ſo not to be Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, yet doe they alledge very many places for it out of the Old Teſtament to make a ſhew of Scripture. So for the New Teſtament. They acknowledge Invocation of Saints departed was not commanded or taught by the Apoſtles, or in their time; yea and give us reaſons why it was not publiſhed at firſt; becauſe (ſay <hi>Eckius, Copus, Salmeron.</hi>) It had been unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and dangerous for Jew and Gentile at firſt to have heard it, leſt they might think the Chriſtians ſet forth and worſhipped many Gods: or that the Apoſtles were ambitious of having ſuch honour done them after their death.</p>
               <p>It is then acknowledged not to have been ſo much as taught in that firſt Age, and yet will they again (when they come to maintain it) make the world believe it was alſo written then, and bring many places of the New Teſtament for a ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proof of it. So of <hi>Image-worſhip, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, Indulgences,</hi> and moſt of their Sacraments, the more ingenuous among them acknowledge (as our Authors have gathered their Teſtimonies) they have
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:61464:60"/>not ground in Scripture: and indeed if they truly had, why ſhould the Romaniſt ſo earneſtly contend for unwritten Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions to hold them by? yet muſt Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture be alledged for them all by every Controverſie-writer. Which conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as was obſerved) does acknowledge that Doctrines of Faith and Religion ſhould be grounded there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> that the neceſſity they have of reſting upon unwritten Traditions e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualized in Authority to the written Word of God, is a plain confeſſion, they cannot ſtand by the undoubted Word of God, nor have any certaine ground of their New faith which reſts upon preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unwritten Traditions, and theſe you muſt take upon the word of their own Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that the ſame neceſſity of reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon unwritten Traditions, forces them to lay upon Scripture Imputations of Imperfection and Inſufficiency, of darkneſſe and obſcurity, very unbeſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Teſtament of God; written by the dictate of Gods Spirit, and left us as a ſignification of his will, and a Rule for the direction of his Church.</p>
               <p>Let us then take leave a little more
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:61464:60"/>largely to ſpeake to theſe two points: of the ſufficient <hi>perfection</hi> of this written Rule, then of the ſufficient <hi>perspicuity</hi> of it. The one caſts off the neceſſity of their unwritten Tradition; the other, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of their Infallible Judge or Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter. And upon theſe indeed reſts the whole frame of the New Roman faith: and therefore worthy, of all other points, to be a little inſiſted on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXII. <hi>Sufficient perfection of the Scripture, as a Rule.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt then, of the ſufficient perfection of Scripture, which we ſay containes all things of themſelves neceſſary to be believed, or done to ſalvation. All ſuch things we ſay, it contains; not expreſly, and in ſo many words, but either ſo, or as deducible thence by evident and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient conſequence. The Romaniſts are forced to grant that the Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains plainly the <hi>prima credibilia</hi> (as ſome of them expreſſe it) the firſt and chiefe points of belief; or thoſe that are <hi>ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer neceſſaria,</hi> and <hi>omnia omnibus neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaria</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:61464:61"/>(as <hi>Bell.</hi> expreſſes it, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.) but they alſo ſay, that there are many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things neceſſary in belief and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe to ſalvation, not there contained, or thence deduced; therefore they adde Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions to make a ſupply.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIII. <hi>Of Traditions which we allow.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr Tradition, We allow,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Univerſal Tradition which brings down <hi>Scripture</hi> unto us, through the conſent of all Ages, for that Tradition is ſuppoſed in the reception of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. But we ſay, the Scripture contains all material objects of Faith <hi>neceſſary</hi> to Salvation, <hi>i.e.</hi> all things that had been ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for Chriſtians to believe and doe for Salvation, though there had been no Scripture.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we allow that kind of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which brings down the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of Scripture to us through all Ages of the Church. So the <hi>Creed</hi> may be called a Tradition, and other Catholike Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Church bringing downe the ſenſe of Scripture in any point of Faith.
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:61464:61"/>Now as the Scripture does ſuppoſe the former Tradition, ſo this kind ſuppoſes the Scriptures for its ground, delivering nothing but what is contained in them, and neither of theſe ſorts derogatory to the ſufficiency of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> we allow ſome Traditions that bring down <hi>matters of practiſe</hi> tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Order, Ceremony, Uſages in the Church, as of Faſts, or Feſtivals, or Rites about Sacraments, and the like: But ſuch if they be not contained in the Scripture, ſo neither are they within the limits of the queſtion; which concerns neceſſaries to ſalvation: ſuch we deny thoſe to be; and ſuch things as are neceſſary to believe to ſalvation, we deny to come down to us by unwritten Tradition: and what Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the Romaniſts pretend for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted points, we deny that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſuch things neceſſary, or to have been delivered down in all Ages; and therefore can be no ground for neceſſary faith, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we conſider the matter of them, or the uncertainty of them. Our Arguments briefly are,</p>
               <p n="1">I. Such as ſhew the Scriptures ſufficient for Salvation; as <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 39. <hi>for in them ye think ye have ſalvation.</hi> Where our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:61464:62"/>ſuppoſes, they thought true in it, or elſe his reaſon had not been good— for becauſe they might have Salvation by them, <hi>i. e.</hi> know all things neceſſary to it, therefore he bids them <hi>ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> and they ſhould find, they teſtified of him— So 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. expreſly, <hi>they are able to make wiſe unto ſalvation,</hi> &amp;c. They have two ſhifts here;</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Scripture is profitable to that end; for that word <hi>(Profitable)</hi> (the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts lay hold on) becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith there, <hi>All Scripture is profitable for doctrine,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo (ſay they) is every book <hi>profitable</hi> to that end, though not <hi>ſufficient,</hi> and ſo they will have the whole Scripture but partially profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
               <p>But we anſwer, <hi>Sufficiencie</hi> belongs to the whole Scripture, though in propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alſo to every Book. And the other expreſſions of the Apoſtle there, ſhew this to be onely a ſhift. For he ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that Scriptures <hi>are able to make wiſe to ſalvation;</hi> can that be ſaid to be able to make a man wiſe to ſuch a purpoſe, and onely to doe it in part, and imperfectly, teaching him onely ſome knowledges to that purpoſe? Alſo he ſaith after, <hi>ver.</hi> 17.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:61464:62"/>by the Scripture, <hi>The man of God is throughly furniſhed, or perfected to every good work, i.e.</hi> to Doctrine, Inſtruction, &amp;c. ſuch as he ſpoke of before; which muſt needs imply a <hi>ſufficiencie to that end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Their other ſhift is, That the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is ſaid to doe this, becauſe it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains many things plainly in it ſelf, and ſhews from whence we may have the reſt, <hi>i.e.</hi> from their Church. We anſwer, Had it ſhewn us that (which it does not) yet could not this ſhift be reaſonable here: For ſo the Law might have been ſaid to make us perfect, becauſe it ſhews us Chriſt, and was a <hi>School-maſter to him, Gal.</hi> 3. and <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> might have been ſaid to have perfected his Diſciples, by ſhewing them Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Such Arguments as forbid and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all Additions to the Scripture, and ſo imply the perfection and ſufficiency of it, and condemne their ſuper-added Traditions, as, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2. and <hi>cap</hi> 12.32. againſt adding to his precepts. And <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18. a Woe pronounced to him that addes. And <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.6. an Anathema to them that bring in another Goſpel beſide what they had received. And <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.15.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:61464:63"/>to a mans Teſtament none addes, much leſſe to Gods. And <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our expreſly condemnes the <hi>Phariſees</hi> that taught for Doctrines of Worſhip, the Traditions and Commandements of men.</p>
               <p>Now ſee, what ſhift they make with theſe places. One is, that the prohibition of adding concernes the whole Word of God written and unwritten, no man may adde to that. We anſwer, that the places of <hi>Deut.</hi> and of <hi>Rev.</hi> are expreſly of the written Word. Alſo that of <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. muſt be meant of the written: for that which is written beares the name of the <hi>Gespel,</hi> and of the <hi>Teſtament of God,</hi> and can we thinke it beares it parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally? Saint <hi>Aug. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>contra Lit. Petil.</hi> and elſwhere expreſly applies that of <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. to the Scripture, thereby excluding all doctrines of Faith not received from Scripture. And Saint <hi>Hier.</hi> upon 1. of <hi>Hag.</hi> relating to that place, ſaith, <hi>Percu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit Dei gladius</hi>— that ſword of God, or <hi>Anathema,</hi> ſtrikes through all thoſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, which <hi>abſque authoritate &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonio ſcripturae quaſi traditione Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licâ confingunt;</hi> without the authority and teſtimony of Scripture they hold
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:61464:63"/>forth under pretence of Apoſtolical Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. And for that other of Gods Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, The Romaniſts muſt ſuppoſe that God Almighty has done, as it fares with many men, who intending to write their Will, and having begun, and prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Title <hi>(This is my Will and Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment)</hi> and proceeded far in it, being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by haſtening death, leave the reſt by word of mouth: ſo will they have God to make a Will partly Written, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Nuncupatory. Now how derogatory this is to the providence of God, who ſees not?</p>
               <p>Another ſhift, That thoſe Traditions are onely forbid, which are contrary to what is written, and ſo no man may adde. We anſwer, The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. <hi>praeter, beſide that which ye have received,</hi> and <hi>Bell.</hi> expreſly interprets that <hi>praeter</hi> by <hi>contra;</hi> but in the judgement of Saint <hi>Aug.</hi> and St. <hi>Hier.</hi> in the places above cited it is enough to incurre the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema, if they teach any thing of faith, which is <hi>beſides</hi> that which is received from Scripture ſaith St. <hi>Aug.</hi> and <hi>abſque authoritate &amp; teſtimonio Scripturae,</hi> the authority and teſtimony of the Scripture, ſaith St. <hi>Hier.</hi> to which adde <hi>Tertul.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:61464:64"/>
                  <hi>Hermogenes, Non eſt ſcriptum, time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at vae illud ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icientibus,</hi> It is not written, Let him fear that curſe which is denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt them that adde. It was then enough to bring a man under the woe pronounced againſt them that added, if the thing they added was not written; and not onely becauſe it was contrary to what was written. But our Saviours ſpeech, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. taken from <hi>Iſ.</hi> 29.13. <hi>Their fear towards me is taught by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of men;</hi> ſhews that all Traditions, though not contrary to what is written, yet if they teach for <hi>Worſhip</hi> or <hi>Faith</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſalvation, that which is not commanded or written, they are to be condemned. For though the Phariſees <hi>Corban</hi> was directly againſt the written command, yet their ſuperſtitious waſhing was not. And upon that occaſion our Saviour condemnes them as to this point. To this very purpoſe is one of St. <hi>Baſil</hi>'s Ethick Rules, <hi>Quicquid extra Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram eſt, cum non ſit ex ſide peccatum eſt.</hi> He ſaies not <hi>contrà,</hi> againſt; but <hi>extra,</hi> beſides, or without Scripture; and being ſo, it cannot be of Faith, and therefore ſinfull, if ſo propounded and impoſed: And this excludes the Romiſh Traditions
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:61464:64"/>from being rules of Faith or Worſhip; beſides that they are to be challenged of contrariety and repugnancy to Scripture for the moſt part.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIV. <hi>Their Arguments againſt Scriptures ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie, and for Traditions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THeir Arguments for their Traditions and againſt the ſufficiency of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, are ſo many aſperſions caſt upon the undoubted Word of God, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out derogation to the Providence and Wiſdome of God, nor (for the moſt part) without ſome contradiction to themſelves.</p>
               <p>Their firſt concerns the purpoſe of God in it, That he did not purpoſe it to contain a perfect Rule, becauſe the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of holy Scripture had no command to write, but did it upon occaſion, or as <hi>Bel. (neceſſitate quadam coacti)</hi> upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions miniſtred, and urging them to write.</p>
               <p>We anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. If the neceſſity of the Churches call'd for Scripture, and urged them to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:61464:65"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:61464:65"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:61464:66"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:61464:66"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:61464:67"/>write, it ſhews of what concernment it is to the Church.</p>
               <p>But 2. though the neceſſity of the Church miniſtred the outward occaſion to ſome bookes, it ſuppoſes the purpoſe and ſpecial providence of God in apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to the work. Hear <hi>Bell.</hi> himſelf acknowledging, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Deo volente &amp; inſpirante Apoſelos ſcripſiſſe quae ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerunt,</hi> That the Apoſtles wrote what they did write, by the will and inſpiration of God. This is well, but this amounts not to a command, faith he: Being then preſt with St <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaying, <hi>Quicquid ille (Chriſtus) de ſuis dictis &amp; factis nos le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere voluit, hoc ſcribendum illis tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam manibus imperavit,</hi> Whatſoever Chriſt would have us read of his ſayings and deeds, that he commanded them to write. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de conſenſ. evang. c. ult.</hi> He is forced to confeſſe they had <hi>mandatum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum,</hi> an internal command to write— And now what needs more? for if they had <hi>had</hi> all of them as expreſſe outward command as Saint <hi>John</hi> had to write his Revelations, or as <hi>Moſes</hi> had to write what he had from God, it would not have made it more the purpoſe of God, than did the inward command: Nor would it
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:61464:67"/>have made <hi>Bellarmine</hi> any whit more granted the Scripture of the Apoſtles to be written for ſuch a Rule; for he does not grant it of <hi>Moſes</hi> Writings, though he had ſuch a command, and therefore we may leave it as a vaine reaſoning.</p>
               <p>But ſee what he ſaith of Scripture as written for a Rule, That it is a Rule, and <hi>Regula fidei Catholicae</hi> the Rule of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Faith; and <hi>Regula credendi certiſſima, &amp; tutiſſima,</hi> The Rule of Belief, and that moſt certain moſt ſafe. <hi>Bell.</hi> affirms <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. and this is well towards a perfect Rule; and there he inferres upon it, ſeeing it is ſo, <hi>ſun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> profecto non erit, qui eâ neglectâ ſpiritus interni, ſemper incerti, ſaepe fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacis, judicioſe commiſerit,</hi> He is not well adviſed, who neglecting Scripture, reſts upon the judgement of a private ſpirit, which is alwaies uncertain, often decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. How well might the inference been made ſo againſt unwritten Traditions, ſeeing the ſcripture is <hi>Regula fidei Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae, &amp; regula credendi certiſſima, tutiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima, ſanus profecto non erit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He is ill adviſed, who neglecting Scripture commits himſelf to unwritten Traditions, which are often deceitfull, alwaies uncertaine.</hi> But in his <hi>fourth Book cap</hi> 12. Scripture is
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:61464:68"/>with him but a partial Rule, unwritten Tradition is the other part: Nay, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes in the ſame Chapter, that it was the proper and chief end of Scripture to be a Rule, but to be <hi>utile quoddam commoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torium ad conſervaudam doctrinam ex prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatione acceptam; A profitable means to admoniſh and remember them of the doctrine they had heard preached:</hi> That profit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Scripture did afford, but the end of that remembrance, and conſerving of the Doctrine preached was, that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſhould be as a ſtanding Rule, or Guide to them, and ſo to us, that did not heare what the Apoſtles preached: To us it is not properly a Remembrancer, but a Guide and Rule; and that muſt be the chief end wherefore it was written.</p>
               <p>But this to note, how this engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for unwritten Tradition in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s fourth. Book, would not let him be conſtant to what he had fairly ſpoken of Scripture in his firſt. So it fares with moſt of them, Truth forces much from them, till they come to be confronted with an adverſary in defence of ſome point of their New Faith.</p>
               <p>Their ſecond ſort of Reaſoning againſt the ſufficiency of Scripture, is by enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:61464:68"/>of ſome things neceſſary to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, which are not contained (ſay they) in Scripture. As firſt, That Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is the Word of God, is neceſſary to be believed, but not contained, or ſhewn by Scripture: This is in every of their mouthes. Among the reſt, <hi>Bell.</hi> thus, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Scripture cannot ſhew it ſelf to be the Word of God, for the</hi> Alcoran <hi>affirms alſo of it ſelf the ſame, that it is the Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We anſwer,</p>
               <p>Firſt to the Impertinency of this Cavil, That (as it was ſaid above in the ſtating of the Queſtion) to believe Scripture to be the Word of God, is not of thoſe material objects of Faith which we ſay are contained in Scripture, and are ſuch as had been neceſſary for Chriſtians to believe, though there had been no Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; alſo that the Scripture being recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon Univerſal Tradition (as we ſaid) does not derogate from the ſufficiency of Scripture, for that is a Tradition which Scripture ſuppoſes, does not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude in this queſtion. For had the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture been never ſo full and ſufficient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Papiſts mind, <hi>i. e.</hi> had it plainly confirmed (if we may ſuppoſe
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:61464:69"/>ſuch a thing) all that they ſay is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be learnt by unwritten Tradition, yet would it not have contained this (that it is the Word of God) otherwiſe then it doth, but muſt ſuppoſe that univerſall Tradition ſtill to bring it down to us. But we alſo ſay; that although Scripture is ſo brought down to us, yet being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived upon ſuch Tradition, it diſcovers it ſelfe to be divine by it own light, or thoſe internal arguments (as they are called) which appear in it to thoſe that are verſed in it.</p>
               <p>And now ſee what <hi>Bellarmine</hi> does here acknowledge, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. he makes the title of the Chapter, <hi>Libri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is verbum Dei contineri,</hi> among other arg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he proves it excellently well by ſome reaſons drawne from Scripture it ſelfe, as by the conſpiration of the parts, the event of Prophecies, and the like, and there ſaith, <hi>Sacris-Scripturis nihil notius, nihil certius:</hi> Now, when he comes to contend for unwritten Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt Scripture: Scripture cannot ſhew it ſelfe to be the Word of God more than the <hi>Alcoran</hi> It had been well if <hi>Bell.</hi> had ſate down with his own diſhonour in contradicting himſelfe, and not uſed
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:61464:69"/>this odious inſtance of the <hi>Alcoran</hi> to Gods diſhonour.</p>
               <p>But as I noted at the beginning, their Neceſſity of reſting upon unwritten Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, forces them to caſt many aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions upon the undoubted Word of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God. Heare what others ſay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame ſcore, the Jeſuite <hi>Bailius</hi> in his Catechiſme, <hi>Without the Teſtimony of the Church, I would believe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture no more than my Livy; no more than Aeſops Fables,</hi> ſaith another. <hi>And how can it prove it ſelfe to be no Fable</hi> (ſaith another Romaniſt) <hi>more than any other writing that is mixed with Fables?</hi> To this purpoſe are thoſe other reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that ſall from them The Scripture, a <hi>mute letter,</hi> as if no ſenſe in it, but as the Church gives it, a <hi>noſe of wax,</hi> as if apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of it ſelf any way.</p>
               <p>This the language their Diſciples muſt learne, to ſpeake reproachfully of that Word which was written by the Holy ſpirit of God, given them to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and muſt judge them at the laſt day.</p>
               <p>Another of their Inſtances of things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, but not contained in Scripture, is <hi>Baptiſm of Infants.</hi> This generally objected
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:61464:70"/>by them all: And amongſt them I ſingle out <hi>Bell.</hi> to anſwer himſelfe, or (as I may ſay) contradict himſelf in it. For <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de baptiſ. c.</hi> 8. he proves it by places of Scripture, and ſaith, the argument is ſtrong and effectual, and cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyded, and that the thing is evident in Scripture. Now when he contends for Tradition againſt Scripture, This thing of <hi>Childrens Baptiſme</hi> muſt be one of them that is neceſſary, and not contained in Scripture. This is not ingenuous nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable, but enough to anſwer the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</p>
               <p>We ſay further, that <hi>Baptiſm of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> as to the practiſe of it, is not contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned expreſly in Scripture, <hi>i. e.</hi> it is no where commanded to be done, or ſaid, that they did doe it: But the grounds and neceſſity of it are ſufficiently deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Scripture, and that's enough for the doing of it; and that the Arguments from Scripture by <hi>Bel.</hi> and others alledged doe ſufficiently ſhew. And theſe are their chief Inſtances.</p>
               <p>Their third and laſt ſort of reaſoning is from places of Scripture expreſly naming Traditions, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The whole Goſpel was Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:61464:70"/>till it was written: Now if they will have theſe places make for them, they muſt ſhew thoſe Traditions mentioned, did contain things neceſſary to ſalvation, and no where written. It is plain they did not. The firſt concerns Rites and Orders in their Aſſemblies; and the other, if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written, concerned the coming of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, the falling away before it (the things ſpoken of in that Chapter, and not of neceſſity to know unto ſalvation) and that Tradition, if any more then was written touching thoſe points, being loſt, it appeares how well the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is to be truſted in this buſineſſe of unwritten Tradition, that cannot ſhew thoſe which were, nor prove thoſe ſhe has, to be delivered by the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Alſo from places of Scripture, which they will have to imply Tradition, as <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>I have yet many things to ſay to you,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. <hi>We speak wiſdome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the perfect:</hi> and that to <hi>Timothy, Custodi depoſitum—That good thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to thee keep</hi>— 2 Tim 1.14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe prove no more than the former place, unleſſe they can alſo prove and demonſtrate to us, that they concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned things not written, and yet neceſſary to ſalvation.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:61464:71"/>
               <p n="2">2. We muſt tell them that Hereticks of old did uſually pretend theſe very pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for their unwritten doctrines, and made the like Inferences as the Papiſts do St. <hi>Aug.</hi> upon <hi>John</hi> ſhews they would ſay, their doctrines were of the <hi>multa</hi> which Chriſt had to ſay, and <hi>Tert. de praeſcript. c.</hi> 5. tels us, Hereticks alledged, the Apoſtles delivered ſome things openly to all, ſome things ſecretly to a few (the very thing the Papiſts ſay) and they proved it (ſuth he) by St. <hi>Pauls</hi> ſaying to <hi>Timothy, Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di depoſitum.</hi> St. <hi>Iraen l</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. ſhews Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks alledged the ſcriptures were obſcure, not to be underſtood by thoſe that know not Tradition; alledging for it, that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. <hi>we ſpeak wiſdome,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Terp.</hi> in his Book <hi>de reſur.</hi> tels us, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks cannot ſtand if you binde them, <hi>de ſolis Scripturis quaeſtiones ſuas ſiſtere,</hi> to be judged by the Scriptures alone: and in the ſame book calls all Hereticks, <hi>Lucifu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas ſcripturarum,</hi> ſuch as fly the light of the ſcripture.</p>
               <p>And now we muſt ſay in the laſt place, their uſual objection of Hereticks alwaies alledging Scriptures and ſhunning Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is moſt vain, as appeares by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Teſtimonies. As for their alledging
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:61464:71"/>ſcripture, it made for the dignity and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of ſcripture; Hereticks well knowing the Authority Scripture had in the Church, and therefore that it was in vain to uſe other proofs without it, and ſo the Romaniſts are neceſſitated (as was ſaid above, <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.) to pretend it for the proving of thoſe points which they know, and ſometimes confeſſe are not grounded on ſcripture. As for Hereticks ſhunning Tradition, it is moſt true, they carefully ſhunned that Tradition which delivered down the ſenſe of ſcripture in the points of Faith through all Ages of the Church: for to ſhun that, was to ſhun the evidence and light of ſcripture. But as for unwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Traditions (ſuch as we and the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts contend about) they ſhelter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the darkneſſe of them, made great advantage (as we ſaw) by pretence of them, alledging the very ſame reaſons and places of ſcripture for them, as the Romaniſts do, and ſo we leave them both well agreed in this point.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:61464:72"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXV. <hi>The evidence of Antiquitie in the point.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw for the evidence of Antiquity. Though we are to ſpeake more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally to that trial by the Fathers after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, yet here in brief to this particular point. There is ſcarce one Father, but we bring him expreſly witneſſing (as we af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm) the fulneſſe and ſufficiency of ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture in all things neceſſary. <hi>Bell.</hi> in <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 11. ſets down very many of them, and admits them for the ſayings of thoſe Fathers, how then does hee decline them?</p>
               <p n="1">1. One of his General anſwers (and it is what others anſwer to) that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſpeake of <hi>omnia omnibus neceſſaria</hi> to be contained in ſcripture. This the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe teſtimonies of thoſe Fathers have extorted from him, which is no little pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to their cauſe (who equal tradition to the written Word, and plead the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of what is conveyed to us thereby) for if all things neceſſary for all be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in Scripture, then ſurely the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and faith delivered in unwritten
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:61464:72"/>Traditions are not neceſſary for all. They indeed that have given up their belief to all the dictates of that Church, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently neceſſitated to believe them, but we may be good Chriſtians and yet not believe them, becauſe not written, and not neceſſary it ſeemeth to all. That w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they can pretend to ſay here, is, that ſuch unwritten Traditions become neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be believed upon the propoſall of the Church, and to be by all believed, to whom they are ſufficiently propounded or made known. Indeed, of Scripture, we grant, All things there revealed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come upon ſufficient propoſal of them neceſſary to be believed as true; yet not all to be believed, as neceſſary in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſalvation. But of unwritten Traditions, we cannot ſay, Men are bound to believe them as true, upon the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of their Church, unleſſe they can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the teſtimony of their Church to be Infallible, or that ſhe propounds them upon full Catholike, or Univerſal Tradition, and conſent of all Ages; which they cannot doe: Much leſſe can we ſay, Men are bound upon the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of their Church to believe them, as containing things neceſſary in themſelves
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:61464:73"/>to ſalvation, unleſſe they can prove the contents of thoſe Traditions to be ſo, which is impoſſible; or that their Church can make new Articles of Faith, or thoſe things neceſſary to be believed to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which were not ſo in themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. This the ſober and moderate Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſt muſt and will deny.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He ſhifteth off their Teſtimonies, by reſtraining them to the particular thing there ſpoken of, as if they onely meant, the ſcripture was full to that point onely. When as indeed upon occaſion of ſome particular point, which they were proving, they ſpeak in general of the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of Scripture, ſaying, it contains all things neceſſary. Therefore to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way theſe, and all ſuch ſhifts which they bring to reſtraine what the Fathers ſpoke generally, We ſhew they ſpoke ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of the ſufficiency of Scripture, that they left no room for unwritten Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to come into the rule of Faith. This we ſhew unanſwerably, by the Fathers (alledged above, <hi>chap.</hi> 23.) arguing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatively (as <hi>Tertul.</hi> ſometimes) <hi>Non eſt ſcri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tum,</hi> therefore not to be received: and ſpeaking excluſively to all things not written, as, that we muſt not ſay or teach
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:61464:73"/>any thing of faith, <hi>praeterquam quod ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptum eſt,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine lib.</hi> 3. <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Lit Petil. Sine his Teſtibus,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> and <hi>citra Scipturam, in Pſal.</hi> 95. and <hi>abſque authoritate &amp; teſtimonio Scripturae,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Hier. in</hi> 1. <hi>cap. Hag.</hi> and, <hi>Quicquid extra Scripturam eſt, cùm non ſit ex fide, peccatum eſt, Baſil. in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis Eth.</hi> Such excluſive words <hi>(praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quàm, ſinè, citrà, abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, extrà)</hi> they uſe againſt admitting of unwritten Tradition for a Rule of Faith; which words and ſpeeches are not any way to be eluded.</p>
               <p>That they bring many ſayings out of the Fathers for Tradition, it is true, and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> boaſts in the number; but to what purpoſe? when they do but beat the aire, ſtrike us not. For they either meane the Scripture it ſelf, or Evangelical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine contained in, and delivered to the Church by the written Word, to which the name of Tradition is often given by the more ancient Fathers, <hi>Iraen. Tertul. Cyprian;</hi> or elſe they mean the forme of Doctrine and Belief delivered downe in the Church, which though they often call Tradition, yet is it written and contained in Scripture, and is but the explication of it, or the Traditive ſenſe, nothing to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:61464:74"/>the unwritten Traditions we ſpeak of; or elſe by unwritten Tradition (as they often mention that too) they imply things of Practiſe, and Rites, and Feſtivals, or Faſts and the like, not matters of Faith neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Salvation. And among theſe ſome Fathers avouch ſuch for Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Traditions which the Romaniſts will not allow, as ſtanding at Prayer between Eaſter and Whitſontide, and every Lords day, and the Trine immerſion in Baptiſm. In a word, where the Fathers ſay, the Apoſtles left ſome things to us unwritten, let the Romaniſts ſhew us, if they can, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the particulars the Fathers ſpeak of, as ſo left us, any point of Faith neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſalvation. Indeed ſome of the more antient Fathers mention one, which (with ſome conſent) they held a point of Faith, and received by Tradition, <hi>viz.</hi> the Mille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary belief: but that was not a meer <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written Tradition,</hi> but rather a <hi>Traditive ſenſe</hi> of Scripture <hi>(Rev.</hi> 20.) and that a miſtaken one, and by the Romaniſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected; who know the Fathers were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in that Tradition by <hi>Papias,</hi> and we know the Romaniſts are deceived, or may very well in theirs. But let them ſhew, as I ſaid, in all the Teſtimonies of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:61464:74"/>the Fathers one of their neceſſary points of Faith among thoſe particulars, which the Fathers have mentioned (with any conſent) as delivered by unwritten Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which ſeeing they cannot doe, all their boaſting of Antiquity in this point is vaine, they meet onely with the <hi>Name</hi> of unwritten Tradition, not the <hi>Thing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVI. <hi>Of the Perspicuity and Interpretation of Scripture.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THus much of the <hi>Sufficiency of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi> Now of the <hi>Perspicuity and Interpretation of it.</hi> Scripture being the Rule of Faith, muſt in all reaſon, be both ſufficiently perfect, as wee have heard, and alſo ſufficiently clear and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous (as we ſhall ſee.) Their pretence of obſcurity and difficulty in Scripture (ſuch as they faſten on it) ſerves them to two purpoſes. To keep people from Reading it, and to ſet up an Infallible In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter of the ſenſe of it, or viſible Judge of all controverſies ariſing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bellar.</hi> handles this buſineſſe in <hi>lib.</hi> 3.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:61464:75"/>
                  <hi>de verbo dei,</hi> and propoſes two queſtions, neither of them ſtated aright. His firſt, <hi>Sintne Scripturae ſacrae per ſe facillimae &amp; apertiſſimae, an verò interpretatione indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant? cap.</hi> 1. His ſecond, <hi>An ab uno viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili communi judice Scripturae interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio petenda ſit, an uniuscujuſque Arbitrio relinquenda?</hi> Whereas we neither ſay, the Scripture needs no Interpretation, nor do we leave it to every mans pleaſure, or judgement. But we acknowledge, there are many hard places, and obſcure paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which need Interpretation; yet is there not ſuch a general obſcurity in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, but that private perſons may read it with profit: which both Scripture it ſelf and all the Fathers exhort the people to: becauſe what is neceſſary to life and faith, is for the moſt part plainly ſet down; therefore it is called <hi>A light to our feet and paths, Pſal.</hi> 119. and <hi>to make wiſe the ſimple, Pſal.</hi> 19.7. and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> bids Chriſtians <hi>attend to the word of Prophecie as a light ſhining in a dark place,</hi> 2 <hi>Epist.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Bell.</hi> anſwers to ſuch places, that the Scripture is a light when it is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood: And this is as much as if he had ſaid, a light is a light, if it be ſeen: For a light, if it be not put in a dark Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:61464:75"/>or under a Buſhel (as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſerves the Scripture to hide it from the people) will ſhew it ſelf: ſo will the Scripture, being a light, and a light ſhining, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid. Certainly it was the intent and duty of all the Apoſtles ſo to ſpeak, and ſo to write as to be underſtood. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> notes but ſome places in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles <hi>hard to be underſtood, which the unlearned and unſtable wreſt</hi>— 2 <hi>Epiſt. c.</hi> 3. Sure then thoſe that are not ſo, but come with minds and endeavours anſwerable, may read with profit, ſeeing his Epiſtles are for the moſt part, not hard to be underſtood.</p>
               <p>That which they reply here comes to this, that thoſe Churches to which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle wrote, were inſtructed aforehand by word of mouth, and ſo might more eaſily underſtand what was written after: We grant, they were praeinſtructed, and that it made them more fit to underſtand what was written: but as they had it, ſo Chriſtian people want it not now; and albeit their praeinſtruction might prepare them to a more eaſie underſtanding of paſſages relating to ſome particulars con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning things not neceſſary to ſalvation, as was that of Antichriſt, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. Of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:61464:76"/>which we may be ignorant, and of which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is ignorant notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all her Traditions: yet f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r things neceſſary delivered in the Apoſtles wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings (of which the queſtion proceeds) our people have as fitting and ſufficient means to underſtand as they had: For ſeeing their praeinſtruction was the firſt preaching of the Goſpel to them, the laying of the foundation, the delivering chiefly of things neceſſary for them to know unto ſalvation: I hope we are not deſtitute of ſuch fore-inſtruction to fit us for profitable reading of the ſcriptures, we are taught the principles of Chriſtian Religion, the Catholike Faith into which we and all Chriſtians are baptized: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, we have the help of the Goſpels and all other writings of Gods Word; and therefore why may not our Chriſtian people ſo premſtructed underſtand Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles (in all neceſſary points) as well and profitably as the people to whom they were written?</p>
               <p>Againe, take the Scripture as a Rule of direction, it argues that it muſt be cleare and plaine in what it is to direct us in. All men give ſuch Rules, as neere as they can, evident and cleare; and ſhall we
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:61464:76"/>deny it to the beſt of Rules, the Rule of Gods making and giving, the Rule of greateſt concernment to us? <hi>Bell.</hi> could ſay (when he meant to give Scripture its due, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.) that it was <hi>Regula cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi tutiſſima, certiſſima:</hi> And againe, becauſe it was a Rule, therefore it muſt be <hi>nota &amp; certa,</hi> which indeed is very good reaſon, both for the knowing of it to be our Rule, and for the evidence of it in thoſe things it is to direct us in. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of which things, it was neceſſary a Chriſtian ſhould have ſufficient evidence: as in the harder places of Scripture he has his exerciſe, to ſet an edge upon his endeavours, and keep him humble. And theſe very reaſons we finde given by the Fathers for the obſcurity we meet with in Scripture; that it is not ſuch, as to deter any from reading (for the Fathers fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently exhort all unto it) but to ſtirre up the more diligence in ſearching the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and to keep down Pride and ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceit, that people ſhould not truſt too much to their own underſtanding: but have cauſe to repair upon all occaſions to their Guides and Paſtors, whoſe mouthes preſerve knowledge now, as the Prieſts did under the Law.</p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:61464:77"/>
               <p>As therefore we ſaid, Scripture was a ſufficiently perfect rule of all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſalvation, containing them expreſly, or deducibly, ſo we ſay it is a ſufficiently cleare Rule, not onely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of what it delivers expreſly, but in regard of all neceſſary truths deducible; becauſe they may ſufficiently by evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and cleare conſequence be deduced thence.</p>
               <p>This clearneſſe then which (we attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to Scripture) does not exclude Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, or the skill and induſtry of the Guides of the Church for the deducing of many neceſſary divine Truths. All things neceſſary, we ſay, are there contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned expreſly, or thence deducible; and deducible, not all by every one that reads; but it is enough, if done by the Paſtors and Guides, which God appointed in his Church, to that purpoſe, uſing the means that are needfull to that purpoſe: ſuch as is Attention and Diligence in ſearch of the Scripture, collation of places, and obſerving the connexions: alſo ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and impartiality in the collection or deduction they make: alſo prayer and devotion for aſſiſtance in the Work.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Bellarmine</hi> propounded the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:61464:77"/>very careleſly, or enviouſly, as if we denying their viſible Infallible Judge or Interpreter, left the Scripture to be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted according to every mans pleaſure. There was enough ſaid above concerning the uſe of Reaſon and Judgement, which we leave to private men, in order to their own aſſent or believing; a private Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of diſcerning what is propounded to them, and manifeſted out of Gods Word. Which Judgement of theirs, as it ſuppoſes the help of, ſo it ſtands ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate to the publike Judgement of the Guides and Paſtors, God has ſet in his Church to judge for others, deducing out of Scripture, and manifeſting the truth to every mans conſcience, as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVII. <hi>Of a viſible Infallible Iudge or Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw the queſtion is, Whether be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the forementioned Guides and Paſtors, there be One viſible Judge or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter for all the Church, to whoſe ſentence all mens Judgements muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:61464:78"/>and every mans conſcience muſt acquieſce without further enquiry? <hi>i. e. a Judge or Interpreter Infallible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed ſuch a Judge or Umpire of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome would (if to be had) be a ready meanes to compoſe all differences, and reſtore truth and peace. But ſeeing it is onely a pretence and not a reality, we have no ſuch remedy left us: Nay, ſeeing it is pretended to by a Church which may erre as well as other particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and has erred as groſly, or more than any other, it is the greateſt hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance now of reſtoring truth and peace among Chriſtians: For that Church which pretends to the Infallibility cannot amend any Errour, and muſt uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly condemn all others which doe not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge her for ſuch, as ſhe pretends to be. So that which the Romaniſts would make the ſtay of Chriſtianity (the Infallibility and unerring priviledge of that Church) is the very bane of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom.</p>
               <p>But to come to the examination and deciſion of this Controverſie. We ſay the Catholike Church of Chriſt is, and will be Infallible in Fundamentals and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Truth neceſſary to the being and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:61464:78"/>continuing of a Church of Chriſt; and that is no more than to ſay, The Church ſhall not faile in being, or in ſaving Truth, but that in one part or other that ſaving Truth or Faith will be preſerved and profeſſed: But that there is, or ſhall be a Church of one denomination (as the <hi>Roman</hi>) Infallible in all her definitions, which ſhe propoſes <hi>de fide,</hi> is that we deny, and they cannot prove.</p>
               <p>We are next to obſerve, that although the Romaniſts would uſually ſhroud themſelves in this point of Infallibility, under the name of the Church Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, yet when brought to the tryal, they muſt, and doe faſten the Infallibility upon the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; endeavouring to ſhew by generall markes that the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church is not to be found but in the Roman Communion (which was obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved above, <hi>chap.</hi> 12. to be the drift of Cardinal <hi>Perron</hi>) and here they would willingly ſtay, and hold forth their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility under the name and priviledge of the Church, being loath to be put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Conteſtation 'twixt the Pope and a Generall Councill. But ſeeing their Church cannot ſpeak, or doe the office of a Judge or Interpreter, but by a Council
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:61464:79"/>or the Pope, therefore their Infallibility muſt reſt upon the one or other.</p>
               <p>And here we muſt obſerve how they ſtand d vided, and diſagree about the very foundation of their Faith, where to ſtate that Infallibility, upon which they profeſs to believe all they doe believe; and for want of which they uſually reproach us Proteſtants, that we cannot have any certainty of belief, or means of agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: when as they that pretend to ſuch unity and certainty in their belief, differ in the ground-worke of it, one ſide de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying and confuting the reaſons and motives of the other.</p>
               <p>Now to ſay, as they uſually reply, that they are certaine of the Definitions of their Church, being from Councils con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Pope, and ſo they have both agreeing. This does not ſalve the buſineſſe. For it is not certain, they ſhall alwaies agree, nor have they alwaies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed. Where then muſt the Infallibility reſt? What certainty of ſuch definitions as the Council makes without the Pope (ſo did the Councils of <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance</hi>) or that the Pope makes without a Council? The Romaniſts ſtand divided about the Definitions of thoſe two
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:61464:79"/>Councils. Againe, if they doe agree, what certainty is there of an Infallibility? For ſtill that muſt accrew to the definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, either upon the unerring judgement of the Council, making them, or of the Pope confirming them; and ſo it returns to the former difference, and thereupon to the former uncertainty, one ſide de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the reaſons of the other. The <hi>Sorboniſts</hi> and moderate Papiſts on the one part aſſerting, a Council is above the Pope, may judge and depoſe him; on the other part, the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and more rigid Papiſts maintaining the contrary. And this opinion of ſtating the Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity upon the Pope, is the more general a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</p>
               <p>But that we may come to a nearer tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of this Infallibility of Judgement in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſee what the certainty of their belief (which by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that pretended Infallibility, they boaſt of, and deny to us) will come to: Suppoſe then, they are all agreed that in their Church there is ſuch a priviledge of Infall bility, or not erring: Let us conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what is brought againſt it, what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for it.</p>
               <p>Their part being the Affirmative, ours
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:61464:80"/>the Negative, we challenge them, that they cannot prove it either by Scripture, or any convincing demonſtrative reaſon: Notwithſtanding they are bound to ſhew us it (according to their own conceſſions) expreſly contained in Scripture: For, they grant all things neceſſary for all to believe (and ſuch they hold this point of Infallibility) are ſo contained in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, it being one of their <hi>prima credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilia,</hi> and neceſſary for all to be believe. <hi>vid. c.</hi> 22. We, as Negatives, are proved, ſhew it is not imaginable, that a belief of that conſequence (the ground-worke of all Faith, the ſtay of the Church, as they will have it) ſhould be ſo ill provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for. That,</p>
               <p>Firſt, the four Evangeliſts writing the Goſpel of Chriſt for the uſe of the Church, and all Believers, ſhould, if they knew it, be ſo ſilent of it, and yet record many things of far ſmaller im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> when he had occaſion to ſpeak it, as when he wrote to the Romans, ſhould not give the leaſt hint of this priviledge, no not when he told them the priviledge of the Jews, <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>that to them were committed the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:61464:80"/>of God:</hi> How convenient had it been to have ſpoken this priviledge of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, that to them were entruſted the Oracles of Chriſt, and the interpretation of them? Again, when writing to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> he had occaſion to tell them of ſome, ſaying, <hi>I am of Paul, I of Cephas, I of Apollo,</hi> in ſtead of telling them, All muſt hold of <hi>Cephas</hi> (as the Roman Church has defined it of neceſſity to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to be ſubject to the Roman Biſhop the ſucceſſor of <hi>Cephas</hi>) he chides them for ſuch faction and diviſion. Or when he and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> agreed upon a diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of their Miniſtry, that one ſhould apply himſelfe to the <hi>Jews,</hi> the other to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> nothing ſhould be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Univerſal Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. Or when he reckoned up the ſeverall Orders as God had ſet them in his Church, <hi>Epheſ</hi> 4.11. it ſhould not been ſaid, Firſt <hi>Peter,</hi> then the Apoſtles, but <hi>Firſt Apoſtles, Secondarily Prophets,</hi> and after for ordering Miniſters of the Church, it ſhould be added, <hi>ſome Pastors and Teachers,</hi> without any inſinuation, that the Lord had given the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to be ſupream Paſtor, and Doctor of the Church.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:61464:81"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:61464:81"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:61464:82"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:61464:82"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:61464:83"/>
               <p>Thirdly, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe giving all diligence (as he ſaith <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.) to minde them of what was needfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his departure, ſhould not tell them whom they were to follow after he was gone.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that we ſhould have ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten warning of falſe Teachers (both in the Goſpels and Epiſtles) and nothing of this Remedy: So much of Antichriſts, and nothing of the Vicar of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, that the <hi>Aſian</hi> Biſhops in their oppoſition againſt Pope <hi>Victor,</hi> or that <hi>Cyprian</hi> and the <hi>African</hi> Biſhops in their oppoſition to Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi> ſhould not know this priviledge of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or not acknowledge it. If it be ſaid, Both <hi>Victor</hi> and <hi>Stephen</hi> judged right: Be it ſo, and let Cardinal <hi>Perron</hi> cry, <hi>Oh Providence, that after-Councils judged the ſame!</hi> (as he <hi>lib.</hi> 3. againſt the <hi>Kings Letter</hi>) yet does it not follow that they were infallible, or had Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall Juriſdiction to judge for the whole Church; Nor yet did they judge altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther right; for <hi>Victor</hi> did not judge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, when he concluded excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt ſo many famous Biſhops and Churches, upon a different time of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:61464:83"/>Eaſter; For albeit <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther famous Biſhops and after-Councils acknowledged the truth of the thing it ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> The obſerving of the Time of Eaſter, yet did they not approve his judgement in proceeding to an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication of, or rather a pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of <hi>Non-communion</hi> with thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: And if <hi>Stephen</hi> did generally with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, as it ſeemes he did, conclude all Heretikes to be received without rebaptization; after-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils did not <hi>judge the ſame,</hi> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the contrary upon ſome He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes; for ſome there were, that did not obſerve, but deſtroyed, what was eſſential to the Form of Baptiſm, and could not therefore be received without being baptized at their admiſſion. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, that Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and the Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> ſhould be ſo ill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in their Faith, as not to know or acknowledge this, but to hold ſo long a conteſtation with the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> in the buſineſſe of Appeales; or that the then Romiſh Biſhops, and their Proctors in that Cauſe, ſhould be ſo ignorant of this point, that in the former buſineſſe they ſhould neither alledge Infallibility of
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:61464:84"/>judgement belonging to the Pope of Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor produce any Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture for what they pleaded for, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pretend a Canon of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> which upon ſtrict examination could not appeare: for the true Canon of that Councell, which concerned the Pope, did not come home to the buſineſs. But the wits of later ages, eſpecially of this laſt which hath produced Jeſuties, have found out Scripture and reaſon for this Pretended Viſible Univerſall Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Judge. We ſhall examine them, but I muſt tell them (which I hinted above) that they are bound to ſhew us it expreſly in Scripture.</p>
               <p>For in the former controverſie, <hi>of the ſufficiency of Scripture,</hi> they grant (and muſt needs doe it) that the <hi>Prima Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibilia,</hi> or the <hi>Omnibus Neceſſaria,</hi> are contained expreſly there. Now this of the Infallibility of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> being the firſt thing to be believed by them, the ground and formal reaſon, upon which they believe all things elſe, they are bound to ſhew it expreſly ſet downe in Scripture. And doubtleſſe had there been ſuch a thing intended by our Saviour, he would have left it diſtinctly
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:61464:84"/>ſet down, that all might be directed to that Infallible Guide or Judge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bellar.</hi> to ſhew the certainty of their belief above the Proteſtants, delivers, the Propoſition of Faith (as he calls it, <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>de verbo Dei</hi>) in ſuch a ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme. <hi>That which is revealed in Scripture is true, But this is revealed in Scripture,</hi>— The firſt propoſition is granted on both ſides: of the ſecond (that this or that is revealed in Scripture) We, ſaith he, are certain. Why? becauſe of the teſtimony of the Church, Council, or Pope, of which we have <hi>apertas promiſſiones,</hi> plain, and clear promiſes in Scripture, that they cannot erre. But the Proteſtants know this or that to be revealed in Scripture by conjectures onely, or the judgement of a private Spirit. So he.</p>
               <p>This propoſition of Faith we ſhall ſpeak to bleow, <hi>chap.</hi> 28. Here I mention it, that to ſhew according to the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment above, they hold themſelves bound to produce cleare Scripture for this ground-work of their Faith; therefore he is forced to call them <hi>apert as promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiones.</hi> He names two in that place; the Firſt is from <hi>Acts</hi> 15.28. <hi>Viſu eſt Spiritui ſancto &amp; nobis.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:61464:85"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This if it concerns any thing, belongs to a Council, (therefore <hi>Bellar.</hi> put them all in together, Church, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, or Pope, for, as I noted above, they are not agreed where to fix) but what promiſe is here to Church or Councel? It is but a relation of what the Apoſtles ſaid, and might ſay it in their priviledge of Infallibility: and I hope none of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Councils preſumed to ſay it, as they ſaid it. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> was ill adviſed to give us this for a cleare promiſe, which is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther promiſe, nor yet cleare: for how does it appeare by any thing in the Text, how after-Councils might ſpeak ſo? Nay it is cleare they could not ſpeak it upon a priviledge of infallibility. For Councels (as <hi>Bel.</hi> ackdowledges, <hi>l.</hi> 2 <hi>de Concil.) nec habent, nec ſcribunt revelationes, ſed ex verbo Dei per ratiocinationem deducunt concluſiones. Neither have, nor propound revelations, but draw their Concluſions out of the word of God by diſcourſe.</hi> Now no men ever undertook to deliver Truth infallibly, which they beat out by reaſoning, and concluding upon diſcurſiſe meanes: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if <hi>Bellarmine</hi> inſtead or this <hi>(Viſum eſt ſpiritui ſancto &amp; nobis</hi>) had givien us that of <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>I am with you to the end,</hi>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:61464:85"/>or that of <hi>John</hi> 16. <hi>The spirit of truth will gvide you into all truth;</hi> he had given us a promiſe, but not cleare: a promiſe of guiding into all truth infallibly; ſo to them that received it then: but not clear for infallibility to after Councels or Guides of the Church: a promiſe indeed of aſſiſtance to them, for all neceſſary Truth, but yet conditionall, upon their doing their duty in uſing the meanes; which that all or the major part in every Council will do, is not certaine.</p>
               <p>His other clear promiſe is our Saviours praying for <hi>Peter, Luk.</hi> 22. ver. 32. <hi>Rogavi pro te nè deficiat fides tua;</hi> This may ſeem to concerne the Pope or Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> yet is there nothing in it of a cleare promiſe to them, whether we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the thing prayed for, or the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; The thing prayed for is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering or not failing of the ſaving faith by which <hi>Peter</hi> was rooted, and built upon CHRIST: which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree to all the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> for they may want that Faith, or faile in it, as they acknowledge. <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> grants this perſeverance was perſonall as to <hi>Peter;</hi> but ſaith hee, there is another thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:61464:86"/>which belongs to his Succeſſors, <hi>viz.</hi> That none in his Chair ſhould teach againſt the Faith. So <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Pont. cap.</hi> 3. or that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome, docens è ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedra,</hi> cannot erre. So <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de verbo Dei cap.</hi> 5. But how is this a clear promiſe now? or how can this be wreſted out of that our Saviour prayed for to <hi>Peter,</hi> by any force of reaſon? For thus the one muſt follow on the other. <hi>Peter</hi> had aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to perſevere in Faith, therefore all his Succeſſours (Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi>) have aſſurance infallibly to teach nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Catholike Faith, which is moſt incohaerent. For if that which was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly prayed for (<hi>Peters</hi> perſeverance) does not deſcend to his Succeſſors, how ſhall the conſequent of it? Nay how ſhall that which is altogether inconſequent to it, therefore deſcend unto them? For were it granted that they ſhould perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in ſaving-faith (the thing aſſured to <hi>Peter</hi>) yet would it by no meanes follow they could not erre: No more than it is true of every regenerate man perſerve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that he is infallible; but now it is granted they have no aſſurance of ſuch perſeverance in the faith, yet muſt it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low they have aſſurance of teaching
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:61464:86"/>nothing againſt it. Thus far then it is ſo clear a promiſe, that nothing ſeems more unreaſonable.</p>
               <p>Againe, if they would make it any way agree to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> it muſt be thus, Our Saviour prayed for <hi>Peter,</hi> that his Faith ſhould not faile, though he denyed him thrice, therefore <hi>Peters</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, though they deny the Faith in mouth, yet it ſhall not faile in heart (as they ſay it was with Pope <hi>Liberius,</hi> when he ſubſcribed to the <hi>Arrians.</hi>) But then this is clean contrary to what they would have out of it, which is an outward Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing or declaring of the Faith by defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitive ſentence, whatever the perſwaſion of the heart be: this they contend not for; yet this is that which was promiſed to <hi>Peter,</hi> this he had; the other (<hi>viz.</hi> outward profeſſion) he failed in. So clear yet is this promiſe. But now looke at the perſon, were there any thing here prayed for which might fit the Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity which the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> would have, yet what cleare conſequence can make that belong to them which St. <hi>Peter</hi> had? can they give us one place of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to aſſure us infallibly that <hi>Peter</hi> was at <hi>Rome,</hi> and governed that Church as
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:61464:87"/>the Biſhop of it, and dyed in that Sea? Is it not admirable that this ground-work of all their faith ſhould no where appeare in all Scripture? The Eccleſiaſtical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters indeed took him to be as Biſhop in that Sea, and ſo the Fathers generally ſpeake of him. But this amounts onely to a humane Teſtimony; and beſides they aſcribe the foundation and Government of that Church to Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> together with <hi>Peter;</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> we finde in Scripture to have written to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to preach to them, and dwell among them, yet muſt the pretenſions made from S. <hi>Peter</hi> be cleare notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Well, were this cleare by Divine Teſtimony, that the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> are S. <hi>Peters</hi> peculiar ſucceſſors; yet ſtill there is no ground for their beliefe of Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, unleſſe they can ſhew it clearly, that what belonged to Saint <hi>Peter</hi> (as to this point) is derived to all his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; and that the ſucceſſors of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtles in the Churches they founded and govern'd, muſt not enjoy what belonged to thoſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</p>
               <p>So much of theſe two cleare promiſes of <hi>Bell.</hi> had he had clearer, we ſhould
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:61464:87"/>doubtleſſe have heard of them. One place there is, which is often in their mouths, and ſerves for all purpoſes: for the Headſhip and univerſall Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility of Pope, Councils, and Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> and that is, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. <hi>Thou art Peter and upon this Rock</hi>— here the Church muſt be built upon Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> that's it they contend for. Cardinal <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> is much upon it (<hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.) and though that which he would there work out of it, is not expreſly Infallibility, but univerſall Juriſdiction or Headſhip, yet becauſe they both have the like foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon this place, it will be worthy to obſerve how he raiſes his worke upon it, by a witty indeed, but miſtaken phanſie. Thus it is, The Fathers at firſt did for the moſt part ſpeake of the Church here as built upon Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they did generally interpret it of the Confeſſion of <hi>Peter,</hi> that the Church was built on that. Now the Cardinall will have theſe interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons not to exclude, but inferre one the other, thus. The Church was built <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally</hi> on the Confeſſion of <hi>Peter, formally</hi> on <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe, or the Miniſtery of his
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:61464:88"/>perſon, <hi>i. e. Peters</hi> Confeſſion was the cauſe why our Saviour choſe him to lay the Foundation of the Miniſtry of his Church upon him. Now judge of the miſtake, in running upon <hi>Peters confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Peters confeſsion, i.e.</hi> the Faith which <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſed and uttered. For <hi>Peters confeſſion</hi> (as the Card. takes it in the notion of a meritorious cauſe) was a ſingle and tranſient act of that Faith which was in <hi>Peter,</hi> a Grace or Virtue; it was a <hi>confeſſing;</hi> but <hi>Peters Confeſſion,</hi> as the Fathers take it, when they ſay the Church was built on it, is underſtood materially, for the thing or truth confeſſed by <hi>Peter, viz. Chriſt the Son of God;</hi> the Confeſſion, or Faith required of the Eunuch at his Baptiſme, <hi>Act.</hi> 9. That he thus miſtakes, it appears alſo by his illuſtrating of it by the ſaying of St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> that <hi>Peter walked not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the waters, but Faith; which</hi> (ſaith the Cardinal) <hi>is not to deny that</hi> Peter <hi>did formally in perſon walk, but to ſhew the cauſe of his walking,</hi> viz. <hi>Faith, which he gave to the word of Chriſt;</hi> where plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Faith is taken for a Grace, Virtue, or Act of <hi>Peters.</hi> Now if we ſay the Church is built upon <hi>Peters</hi> Faith, will he ſay
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:61464:88"/>that Faith there is an Act or Virtue in <hi>Peter,</hi> or not rather taken for that Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like truth believed and confeſſed by <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Peters</hi> confeſſion of that Faith was no queſtion the cauſe that our Saviour beſtowed ſomething on him at that time: but that on which Chriſt ſayes there, He will build his Church, was <hi>Peters</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Faith or Truth confeſſed by him; and ſo its plaine the Fathers tooke it, for they oppoſed this Faith or Confeſſion (as the Cardinal acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges) againſt the Arrians, That <hi>Chriſt was the Sonne of the living God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bell.</hi> applyes the promiſe following (<hi>I will give thee the Keys,</hi> &amp;c.) to this buſines of the One viſible Interpreter or Judge, and will have <hi>(whatſoever thou looſeſt)</hi> to ſignifie not onely the relaxation of ſins, and their cenſures, but <hi>nodos omnes le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum—&amp; dogmatum</hi>—the diſpenſing with the tyes of Laws, and the explicating all the doubts and difficulties of Doctrine and Controverſie, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de verbo Dei cap.</hi> 5. And this is barely ſaid by him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further proof. Now when this promiſe of the Keyes is applyed to judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſinnes and offences, we know what
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:61464:89"/>
                  <hi>binding</hi> is as well as <hi>looſing;</hi> but when it is thus ſtretched to univerſall judgement in the interpretation of Scripture, defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning points of faith, diſpenſing with Lawes we cannot tell, unleſſe we thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, that as <hi>looſing</hi> her with <hi>Bell.</hi> is to explicate Scripture, ſo <hi>binding</hi> muſt be the obſcuring or involving the ſenſe of it; if <hi>looſing</hi> be againe the power of diſpenſing with Lawes, which binde men (as in point of marriage or the like) then of <hi>binding</hi> muſt be the forbidding of what God has made lawfull, as for Clergy to marry, or what he has commanded, as people to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament in both kindes. And the Pope it ſeems by vertue of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or power of Keyes may thus <hi>looſe,</hi> and <hi>binde,</hi> and not erre: yet theſe are their chiefe places of Scripture. Now let us come to their Reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt is from Gods providence, who was not ignorant how many difficulties, and controverſies would ariſe about the faith, and therefore would no doubt appoint ſuch a Judge. <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is to meaſure the wiſdome of God by the modell of our Reaſon: but the ſame reaſon may alſo tell us, it would have been more conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the Church to have had ſuch an
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:61464:89"/>Infallible Judge or Interpreter in every Nation, than one for the whole Church, which was to be ſpread over all the Earth; yea reaſon may further tell us, it had been ſuitable to his providence, expreſly to have told us, who that Infallible Judge was, and where we ſhould finde him. And it cannot be imagined in reaſon, but he would have done it, had he appointed any ſuch; for he was not ignorant, that many &amp; the greateſt controverſies would be about this Judge.</p>
               <p>He tells us plainly, <hi>There muſt be Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies:</hi> and the end wherefore; <hi>that they which are approved may be manifeſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. but not appointing withall this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy of an Infallible Judge; we muſt think it is, that approved faith may be of more price, and worth; <hi>gained</hi> with more earneſt enquirie, and diligence in ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture, &amp; uſing the like means: ſo alſo <hi>kept and held</hi> with greater care and watchfulneſſe; all which would have faln and grown remiſſe in the hearts of men, if to truſt all their belief upon an Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Guide, without any further enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:61464:90"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVIII. <hi>Of certainty of belief, and whether they or we have better means for it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Second reaſon is from certainty of belief, which they ſay the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants cannot have for want of ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility: but <hi>we are certain</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bell:</hi> in his Propoſition of Faith above-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned §. 27.) <hi>that this or that is revealed in Scripture, becauſe of the Teſtimony of the Church, Councel, or Pope, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now would I ask, firſt, whether they believe, that <hi>Chriſt is the Son of God, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the world,</hi> that <hi>He ſuffered,</hi> and <hi>now ſits at the right hand of God,</hi> or the like; becauſe the Church teſtifies it to be revealed in Scripture, or becauſe they ſee it evidently there themſelves. If they ſay, becauſe the Church teſtifies it; then it ſeems they cannot (which is falſe) or may not (which is worſe) believe God immediately, when he ſpeaks as plain as the Church can. If they ſay, becauſe they ſee it evidently there, then have they two formall reaſons of their belief, One, the immediate evidence of Scripture: The
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:61464:90"/>other, the Teſtimony of the Church. And if they can believe upon that immediate evidence or light of Scripture, then ſo may we alſo. And ſo we doe, not exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the light which the Church gives to the Scripture, where it needs; which light is not to us the reaſon of believing what we believe, but a means and help to ſee that which is contained in Scripture, and make it more evident to us.</p>
               <p>Again, I would ask, how they believe it to be revealed in Scripture, that the Church is Infallible? becauſe of the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Church? No, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay here, but muſt alledge for it plain Scripture <hi>(apert as promiſſiones, clear promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> as <hi>Bellar:</hi> called them) and muſt allow men the uſe of their reaſon &amp; judgment, upon the evidence of them. Well, if they may believe that great point, of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility of their Church, upon imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate evidence of Scripture, why may not we believe other points ſo too? or why doe they condemn the Proteſtants for believing every point of Religion upon the ſame ground, on which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves lay all their faith at once? for they believe the Churches Infallibility revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Scripture, becauſe they ſee it, as
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:61464:91"/>they ſay plainly promiſed there. Now if they believing the Infallibility of their Church upon immediate evidence of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture can have certainty of belief: why cannot we have like certainty upon the like evidence? if they cannot have cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in that particular, then can they not have any certainty in any thing elſe, which they believe, upon that belief of an Infallibility in their Church. Onely this they get by it, and muſt anſwer for it one day, that believing all things elſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſuppoſed Infallibility of their Church, they are made to believe many things to be revealed in Scripture, and to be the will of God, which are not; yea, to believe contrary to that which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, as the <hi>half communion</hi> for the people.</p>
               <p>Again, they that underſtood and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved what the Apoſtles preached, and wrote to them, did it without the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall means of an Infallible Interpreter, upon the evidence of what was ſpoken or written: and therefore ſo may we. Now to ſay, They that ſpoke and wrote were Infallible, and the other knew it to be ſo, is no more than what we ſay, Scripture is Infallible, that ſpeaks to us the ſame
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:61464:91"/>which they ſpoke and wrote, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we way as well underſtand and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it upon the ſame evidence.</p>
               <p>We doe not here (as I inſinuated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) exclude the exterior helps &amp; means which God has appointed for interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and clearing the Scriptures, ſuch as definitions of Councels, the judgment and practice of Primitive Ages, the skill and labour of the preſent Guides of the Church, which make for the clearing and evidencing of that which is contained in Scripture; but upon the evidence of that, or manifeſtation of the truth, out of that, is the ſtay or laſt reſolution of our Faith. <hi>Waldenſis,</hi> a learned writer in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> many years agoe, with divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, doe well apply that of the Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans to the Wowan (<hi>Now we believe, for we have heard him our ſelves, Joh.</hi> 4.42.) unto this laſt reſolution of Faith begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the Teſtimony of the Church, as the firſt motive, but ending and ſtaying upon Scripture; As they were firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and brought to Chriſt upon the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans ſaying, but believed indeed when they heard him themſelves: So the ſaying and judgment of the Church at our firſt coming and after is a great motive, and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:61464:92"/>light to us; but then indeed we believe when we hear him our ſelves; when we hear him ſpeak thus and thus to us in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
               <p>Now he that upon carefull and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall uſing the means God has appointed, does ſearch for the Truth, ſhall finde what he ſeeks, or not erre inpardonably: whereas the Romaniſt, receiving all upon a ſuppoſed infallible Teſtimony, ſeeks no further comes not to <hi>(audivimus ipſi, we have heard him our ſelves)</hi> blindly caſts his faith upon a falſe ground, and ſo is led to believe (as I ſaid) many things as revealed of God, which are not, and ſometimes the contrary to what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.</p>
               <p>Their third Reaſon is from pretence of Unity; which they ſay is preſerved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them by this means, but loſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Proteſtants for want of it; and they inſtance in the breaches, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of theſe our Times. <hi>Anſw.</hi> We had the ſame means for Unity which the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Church had (as was ſaid above, <hi>ch.</hi> 13.) and ſo long as we could freely uſe them (having the ſecular power to friend) <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> and <hi>ſchiſme</hi> was prevented, and Unity preſerved: but when the ſword of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:61464:92"/>prevailed, no marvail if Licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe grew bold, and caſt off the cords of obedience Eccleſiaſtical, as well as Civil. And we ſee this pretended Infallibility could not keep <hi>Burbon</hi> and his Army in order, but that they ſacked <hi>Rome,</hi> made the Pope their priſoner, and forced him to unworthy conditions. And we read that Hereticks of old (as Arrians, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) when they had the Emperours fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, bore down all before them: ſo that this means of Infallibility either could not keep them from breaking out, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing, or elſe (which indeed is the truth) there was no ſuch belief of an Infallibility in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in thoſe better Ages: nor was it ever made uſe of, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged againſt Hereticks to repreſs them. The judgment indeed of the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> was often alledged, as was alſo the judgment of other Churches and famous Biſhops, but this without implying an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibity in judging.</p>
               <p>Nay this pretence of Infallibility is ſo farre from being cauſe of Unity in the Catholick Church, that it has been the chief cauſe of diviſion, and of loſing more than they retain by it. The Greek Church ſtands diſ-joyned from the Roman, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:61464:93"/>of her challenging Univerſal ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and Infallibility; and therefore no more to be dealt with. And this has loſt all thoſe that in theſe later Ages have been divided from the Communion of the Roman Church, becauſe the pretenſe of Infallibility made her incorrigible, and cut off all hopes of her amending the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors they complained of, and deſired to have reformed. So that let them caſt up what they have loſt, and they will have no cauſe to boaſt of what they hold by it.</p>
               <p>Nay did the Romaniſts truly confeſſe what belief they have of this Infallible Judge, it would in all probability be found, that not the faith of ſuch Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, but the fear of Inquiſition, fire and faggot, keeps thoſe they have in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, at leaſt external.</p>
               <p>But ſome of them have ſaid, This Rule or way, if followed, does produce Unity: but the Proteſtants Rule of belief is not apt to doe it, but rather begets diviſion. <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true that their Infallibility (though not Real but pretended) where it is followed, <hi>i. e.</hi> indeed believed, will produce, according to the ſtrength of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roncous perſwaſions, an anſwerable effect
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:61464:93"/>in thoſe that are drawn to believe it: for ſuch muſt needs ſubmit to all things elſe. But being onely pretended, not reall, it cannot be apt to produce the effect, or hold men to them, but as we ſaid, has loſt many. Our Rule of believing upon evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Scripture, (gained by due uſe of the means appointed thereunto, (as above mentioned, in this <hi>Chap.</hi>) if conſcionably followed, will produce the effect of Unity and peaceable ſubmiſſion, and is more apt to do it. For therfore was Scripture given, that there might be <hi>one Faith:</hi> and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly not given with ſuch obſcurity, as to make men quarrel, but with ſuch evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as men not wanting to themſelves, may therby come to know that <hi>one faith,</hi> without ſuch a viſible Infallible Judge. And when any will deceive themſelves and prove obſtinate, the Church proceeds to reſtrain them by Eccleſiaſtical cenſure, even to excommunication, for preſerving Unity in the reſt. And other means the Antient Church had not, nor can the Roman goe farther in the way of the Church: for as for fire and faggot, it was the way of the Adverſaries of the Churcith.</p>
               <p>The Teſtimonies they cite out of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are all not concluding; They are
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:61464:94"/>ſuch as ſend Hereticks to the Church in general, as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts often: but this does not argue, that we ſhall finde any where in the Church a Viſible Infallible Guide. Otherwiſe we ſay, in every Church there are Guides and Paſtors of publik judgment, to whom inferiours muſt ſubmit, and the conſent of the Catholick Church is above that. Or elſe they are ſuch Teſtimonies, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the judgment of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> given in ſuch or ſuch cauſes, and required by other Biſhops or Churches. But this comes not home neither. For we finde the judgment of other Biſhops, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Fathers alledged, and required, and that by Popes themſelves. So was <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſius</hi> his judgment, deſired by <hi>Liberius,</hi> and <hi>Hieromes</hi> often by Pope <hi>Damaſus;</hi> and that in matter of doctrinal points, and with a great deal of ſubmiſſion to their judgment, as to be guided by it; (as appears in Pope <hi>Liberius</hi> Letter to <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi> and <hi>Damaſus</hi> to <hi>Hierome.</hi>)</p>
               <p>One place of <hi>Irenaeus</hi> is much cited by them, <hi>Ad quam propter potentiorem principalitatem, &amp;c.</hi> lib. 3. cap. 2. which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndeed makes againſt them: For this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mplies neither Univerſal juriſdiction,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:61464:94"/>nor Infallibility in the Romiſh Church: Neither did <hi>Irenaeus</hi> mean ſo much as the words by reaſon of the ill Latine Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, may ſeem to imply. For the Greek had it, (as I have met with it, and as the whole Context avouches it) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and is ill tranſlated <hi>potentiorem principalitatem,</hi> but rather ſounds <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter convenientiorem inſtitutionem, ſeu principium;</hi> That Church being from Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and therefore the moſt convenient example to ſhew the ſucceſſion of Paſtors and Doctrine. For from thence he fetches his argument to confute thoſe Hereticks, that being preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with Scripture did accuſe it (as he ſaith) of obſcurity, as not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of them who were ignorant of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; therefore he confutes them by the undeniable ſucceſſion of the Churches, and becauſe <hi>Longum eſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>omnium Eccleſiarum enumerare ſucceſſiones,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſingles out the Roman, as that which was <hi>maxima, omnibus cognita &amp; à glorioſiſſimis Apoſtolis Petro &amp; Paulo fundata &amp; inſtituta,</hi> (there is the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a more convenient beginning of ſucceſſion</hi> in that, than in other leſſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Churches) and by the doctrine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:61464:95"/>from the Apoſtles, and delivered down in that Church, he confounds the Hereticks. Now (ſaith he) with this Church (becauſe of ſuch a beginning and ſucceſſion) every Church ought to agree: and ſo they did then, and therefore it was needleſſe for him to inſtance in any other Church.</p>
               <p>Thus are we alſo willing to deal with the Romaniſts at this day. They being preſſed with Scripture, accuſe it of obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and ſay, (as thoſe Hereticks that <hi>Irenaeus</hi> had to deal with) It is not to be underſtood by them that are ignorant of Tradition; We therefore tell them of the Doctrine of Faith delivered down in all Churches, and bring them to the Antient Roman Church, which was glorious then for its foundation and preſervation of true doctrine, and tell them, becauſe of ſuch an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they ought to agree with it now: which they doe not in the main points between us and them controverted (as aboveſaid) and in this particular of an Infallible Univerſal Judge for the whole Church.</p>
               <p>¶ Thus farre we have proceeded upon the firſt and chief Rule of Triall, <hi>Scripture; the Sufficiency and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of it,</hi> Now to the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:61464:95"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXIX. <hi>Of Conſent of Antiquity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OUr ſecond Rule of Triall, is, <hi>Conſent of Antiquity.</hi> We ſay, the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts cannot prove their Doctrines by that, as they ought to doe, if they will have them paſſe for Catholick; for then according to <hi>Vincentius</hi> his Rule, <hi>ſemper &amp; ubique,</hi> they muſt be alwaies and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally held in the Church. Yet is there a pretence made to it, and great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and boaſting among them of the Fathers: not that they know, they have indeed advantage by them, as to the due proving of their cauſe, but becauſe the Proteſtants have freely and ingenuouſly ſpoken their Judgment of the Fathers and their authority. Therefore the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts make advantage of it with their own Proſelytes, as if the Proteſtants de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined all Triall that way. Now ſhould we ſpeak with that liberty of the Fathers writings, as they doe of the Scripture, loading it with imputations of obſcurity, imperfection, corruptions, &amp;c. it might I hope be ſo much more juſtifiable in us, as the divine authority of Scripture ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes all humane writings,</p>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:61464:96"/>
               <p>But this we profeſſe, however they are obliged to diſparage the written Word of God (and a miſerable cauſe it muſt be which obliges men to ſuch a plea) yet are not we obliged to detract any thing from the due worth of the Antient Fathers: for, take their Writings as they are, we averre that the Popiſh faith cannot prove it ſelf to be Catholick by them.</p>
               <p>Yet if we ſay, the Fathers were men, and ſubject to error, which the Scripture is not, we doe but ſay, what they oſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge themſelves. If we ſay, they have erred in ſeveral Ages, and that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them together with a general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent (as in the Millenary belief, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant communion, and the place of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Souls out of Heaven till the Day of Judgment) we doe but ſay, what the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſt cannot deny, who doe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Fathers erred in theſe.</p>
               <p>If therefore we ſay, they are no Rule of Faith to us, we doe but ſay, what they of the Ages following thought, that they were not bound to follow them in theſe errors, after they were once detected, and what the Romaniſts muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, for they alſo have forſaken them in theſe.</p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:61464:96"/>
               <p>If again we ſay, the Writings of the Fathers have come through ill hands un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, which have corrupted or maimed the true, and patched falſe and ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious writings to them, the Romaniſts cannot but acknowledge, we have great cauſe to think there was more providence of God in the preſerving of Scripture en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, than the Writings of the Fathers. Onely here is the miſchief again, they are obliged to ſpeak any caſualty that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to Scripture, and to make a noiſe of corruptions, obſcurity, &amp;c. becauſe they finde it too plain againſt them, and are afraid the people ſhould ſee it too; but of the Fathers writings more rarely doe they acknowledge any ſuch thing, not becauſe they have cauſe to joy of them, as plain and full for the Romiſh faith; but becauſe their advantage is by their forged writings, and the corruptions of the true ones; alſo becauſe thoſe writings came through their hands for ſeveral A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and ſo the falſe dealing, that has been uſed, becomes chargeable upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of their cauſe: Falſe dealing I ſay, what by the cunning of Monks that had thoſe Writings in Manuſcript, what by their ſeveral editions of the Fathers, what
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:61464:97"/>by their expurgatory Indexes. In all which it is eaſie to ſee what labouring there has been, to make the Antients ſpeake the Language of their preſent Church. Hence have they advantage, not truly, by the Writings of the Antients, but ſuch as ſerves to their purpoſe, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when to deal with thoſe that are leſſe learned; whom they can turn to this or that place in ſuch or ſuch a Father, knowing they are not able to judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the writing be ſuppoſititious, or the place corrupted, or whether the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther elſwhere expreſſes himſelf otherwiſe, or be contradicted by other Fathers, and there ſpeaks onely his private opinion.</p>
               <p>This caution <hi>Vincentius</hi> gives us in his Rules for Catholick doctrine, <hi>cap.</hi> 39. Whatever any, <hi>quamvis ſanctus, doctus, Epiſcopus, Martyr, praeter— vel contra</hi>— though holy, learned, though a Biſhop or Martyr, holds beſide or againſt the reſt of the Fathers: <hi>id inter proprias &amp; privatas opiniunculas</hi>— it muſt be ſevered from the Publick doctrine, and placed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong private opinions.</p>
               <p>Well, though all this makes for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage of the Proteſtants, that they have not the Fathers writings, as they
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:61464:97"/>came from their own hands and pens, but as through the hands of many Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries: yet take them as they are, with all the difficulties of finding what is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theirs, and what is the ſenſe of it, the Proteſtants never doubted to enter this kinde of triall by Antiquity; not ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or falling by every thing we meet with in one or moe Fathers, (for the Romaniſts will not ſo) but maintaining:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Romaniſt cannot prove his Affirmative by a full and ſufficient conſent or Teſtimony of Antiquity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That we have enough in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of Antiquity to diſcover the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty of the Romiſh doctrines, which may generally appeare upon this evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXX. <hi>Application of the Rule to their Doctrine in ſeveral points.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt, the great <hi>ſilence</hi> in the writings of the firſter Ages, touching the points of Romiſh faith; which cannot be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined would have been, if ſuch had been the doctrine of the Church, or the faith
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:61464:98"/>that all Chriſtians were to learn and hold; they call to us, to name Profeſſors of the Proteſtant doctrine in all Ages, but that is unreaſonable we ſhould be bound to it (our part being the Negative of what they erroneouſly affirm) yea, and impoſſible too, becauſe the errors we deny, were not affirmed or thought of in many Ages; and how then ſhould any expreſly appear againſt them? But it is moſt reaſonable and juſt, to exact of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who affirm <hi>Tranſubſtantiation, Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints, Purgatory, half Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, Image Worſhip, &amp;c.</hi> for Catholick doctrines, to ſhew and prove them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed in all Ages: at leaſt ſo profound a Silence as we finde in the firſt Ages, is ſufficient argument againſt them, yea and Silence when there was occaſion to vouch and defend them, had they been the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Chriſtian Church.</p>
               <p>As when we ſee ſo many Apologies written and declaring the faith and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Church; ſo many Books pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely written on that ſubject, <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> wrote two, his <hi>Ancoratus de fide Chriſtiana,</hi> and his <hi>Compendium fidei Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicae Eccleſiae, S. Auguſtine</hi> wrote three, one <hi>De vera Religione,</hi> where he ſayes at
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:61464:98"/>the beginning, <hi>haec eſt noſtris temporibus Christiana Religio,</hi> Another <hi>De doctrina Chriſtiana,</hi> and his <hi>Enchiridion</hi> to <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentius,</hi> of which he ſaith, <hi>ibi diligenter mihi videor complexus quo modo colendus ſit Deus;</hi> in which only he has one thing ſounding to the Popiſh doctrine, &amp; that is about helping the dead by Almes, or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and that was but his private opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion grounded upon a falſe ſuppoſal, not of Purgatory, but of common receptacles of all mens ſouls out of Heaven till the Day of Judgment, in the 109 Chapter of that Book. For that which he ſaith in the 70 Chap. <hi>Per Eleëmoſynas de peccatis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritis propitiandus eſt Deus,</hi> he qualifies himſelf in the ſame place, and excellently ſpeaks of the free reward of Good works in the 107 Chap. Now can it be Imagined that in ſuch Books purpoſely written, there ſhould be ſuch ſilence and preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the Romiſh doctrines of Faith, had they been the Doctrine of the Church?</p>
               <p>Again, in the firſt 300 years, when there was ſuch occaſion to urge and hold up their <hi>publick Penance</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> by it, alſo ſo much written and ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it; had they believed a Romiſh
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:61464:99"/>
                  <hi>Purgatory</hi> after this life, can we think but they would often have mentioned it alſo, and told the people of the pains they ſhould undergoe there, if not careful to perform due <hi>Penance</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> here?</p>
               <p>Alſo when occaſion was given by Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries to aſlert ſuch doctrines, had the Church known and profeſſed them: can it be imagined thoſe Fathers that anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thoſe Adverſaries ſhould be ſilent in the Cauſe? As for example, In the point of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> when <hi>Marcion</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med CHRIST had a body phantaſtick or in appearance onely, how obvious had it been for him (had Tranſubſtantiation been the doctrine of the Church) to have objected, that the ſigne of his Body in the Euchariſt, was but a body in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, the ſhew of bread onely, and his body there under any ſhape, figure, &amp;c. how neceſſary had it been for the Church to have maintained that point againſt him? it could not have eſcaped the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputation, had it been any doctrine of faith in the Church. Whereas on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>Tertullian</hi> takes it for granted, that the bread (which was the figure of his body) was a true body, and thence infers
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:61464:99"/>that Chriſts body (of which bread was the figure) was alſo true and real, <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>contra Marc. c.</hi> 40. So when the <hi>Eutichians</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the converſion of the Humane nature into the Divine, and drew ſome phraſes of the Doctors of the Church (which ſeemed to imply a converſion of the bread after conſecration) to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving or illuſtrating of it: had the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church been ſo, could they have declined the expreſſe maintenance of Tranſubſtantiation againſt that argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? whereas on the contrary we ſee the <hi>Eutychians</hi> confuted by <hi>Theodoret, Gelaſius</hi> and others, by denying plainly a ſubſtantial converſion of the bread, and ſo taking away the ground of the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and all belief of Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>So in the point of <hi>Invocation</hi> and <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Saints,</hi> when it was objected to <hi>Origer</hi> by <hi>Celſus</hi> in defence of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Invocating their <hi>Daemons</hi> &amp; <hi>Heroes</hi> (whom they held to be <hi>Internuncios &amp; intermedios,</hi> betwixt the ſupreme God and themſelves) that the Chriſtians alſo allowed the miniſtery of Angels, and that their Saints departed were <hi>Amici Dei.</hi> Had the Church then held Invocation
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:61464:100"/>of Angels or Saints departed, <hi>Origen</hi> had been bound to aſſert and maintain it, and not to anſwer as he doth, that Chriſtians invocated God only by their high Prieſt <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> and they that doe ſo, want not the Miniſtery or help of Angels, in his 8 Book againſt <hi>Celſus,</hi> and elſwhere. The very like does S. <hi>Auguſt:</hi> ſpeak of the Heathen <hi>Daemons</hi> and <hi>Heroes</hi> in his 8, &amp; 9 books <hi>de Civ: Dei.</hi> Shewing, the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> did not ſo to the <hi>Martyrs.</hi> And when it was objected to him by <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> the <hi>Manichaean,</hi> that inſtead of the heathen Idols they had ſet up the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, becauſe they reſorted to their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, and there offered up prayers and ſacrifice: Had the Church then held the Romiſh belief and practice of <hi>Saint-Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Invocation,</hi> could he have declined the maintenance of it? whereas he there and elſewhere diſclaims it in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe terms, and ſhews <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, in the end and purpoſe of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians reſorting to Martyrs Tombs, which was to offer up the Sacrifice, and worſhip and prayers to God onely, <hi>lib.</hi> 20. <hi>contra Fauſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, when the Invocating of Chriſt was uſed by the Church as an argument
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:61464:100"/>for his Godhead againſt the Arrians, would it have been good, if Invocating of Saints alſo had been the doctrine and practice of the Church? and if that ſhift of the Romaniſts had then been allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that they doe not invocate Saints as God, or with invocation which is due to God, but as friends of God and excellent inſtruments of his glory, had not the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians had a pat anſwer to the former ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, <hi>viz:</hi> That Chriſt was to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocated, yet not as God, but as the Son of God, after a more excellent way than any other creature is? But they that uſed the former argument feared no ſuch an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, becauſe Invocation and worſhip of Saints was then no doctrine of the Church.</p>
               <p>Thus much for the <hi>ſilence</hi> of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers when occaſion was given them to defend thoſe points, had they been do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Church.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we have Evidence againſt the Roman faith, by that which we meet with in the Fathers appliable to ſome points of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Sometimes we meet with the <hi>Name</hi> indeed which the Romiſh point bears, but not the <hi>Thing;</hi> as for example, in ſome
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:61464:101"/>few Fathers, there is mention of a <hi>purging fire</hi> after this life; but neither doe they agree upon the ſame thing among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor any of their conceits with that thing the Romaniſts call <hi>Purgatory.</hi> So we meet with the name of <hi>Oblation</hi> and <hi>Sacrifice</hi> in the Euchariſt but in ſenſes we admit of, not the Roman thing of a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Sacrifice.</hi> So we meet with <hi>prayers for the dead,</hi> which indeed was the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and practice of the firſter Ages, but it was not for relief of any Souls in a ſuppoſed purgatory, to which the Romiſh doctrine and practice of praying for the dead is bound. So for <hi>private confeſſion,</hi> we allow it in the ſenſe and way the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Church did perſwade and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times practice it, not as impoſed and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by the Roman.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sometimes we meet with <hi>phraſes</hi> in the Fathers favouring ſome Romiſh do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but then we ſhew by argument and reaſon from the ſame Fathers, that thoſe phraſes doe not ſpeak indeed the <hi>Romiſh ſenſe.</hi> As for <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> many hyperbolicall expreſſions, many ſpeeches founding the change and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elementation of the Bread; but we ſhew they could not mean a ſubſtantial change,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:61464:101"/>becauſe we finde them uſe like phraſes of the change of a Man in regeneration, of Water in Baptiſm, of Oyle in the Chriſm after conſecration; in all which no ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial change or converſion. Alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many of the Fathers in plain terms acknowledge, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> to be a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurative ſpeech; and becauſe it is clearly evinced out of them, that indeed they <hi>held</hi> the Bread remained in ſubſtance after conſecration. One inſtance whereof we had above, in this Chap: in their anſwer to the Eutychians. Another we may have from their ſaying, our bodies to be nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by the Body of Chriſt, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive increaſe by it. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> here ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges an hyperbolical improper ſpeech, and that they meant our bodies <hi>ex contactu corporis Chriſti</hi> did receive a diſpoſition to immortality; a figurative ſpeech indeed, taking the body of Chriſt ſacramentally, and ſpeaking of it what the ſacramental element does indeed: for our bodies are indeed nouriſhed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive increaſe by the Elements, and this implies neceſſarily the ſubſtantial remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them. But for <hi>Bellarmine</hi> his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, it is too impertinent; as if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving a diſpoſition to immortality,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:61464:102"/>could ſatisfie their ſaying, that our bodies are nouriſhed and receive increaſe, which we finde to be real upon the receiving the Elements as well as any other Bread or Wine; and to ſay they receive that diſpoſition <hi>ex contactu corporis Chriſti,</hi> is to ſay Chriſts body is touched by ours, when as this manner of the Romiſh real preſence enforces them to ſay, Chriſts body in the Sacrament is impalpable, and cannot be touched or felt.</p>
               <p>Let me adde here how Cardinal <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> in his Letter to Maſter <hi>Caſaubon,</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as it were Tranſubſtantiation, layes the whole <hi>Importance of the Sacrament</hi> on the real preſence, <hi>viz:</hi> our Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſubſtantial Union to the Body of Chriſt; citing S. <hi>Cyrill,</hi> who calls it the <hi>Knot of our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with God.</hi> Obſerve firſt, that Tranſubſtantiation it ſeems is not neceſſary to this <hi>importance of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> our Union with Chriſt: ſee we if their real preſence (which divided from Tranſubſtantiation muſt needs fall in with the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Conſubſtantiation) will be neceſſary to it. It is true that the <hi>impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Sacrament</hi> is our Union with Chriſt, and for that Union we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge there muſt be a real preſence of
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:61464:102"/>Chriſts body to thoſe it is united to in the Sacrament; and ſo a real preſence or Communication of the Body of Chriſt, we hold, and a real Union: but as this Union is ſpiritual, ſo is the Preſence too: yet real, yea moſt real, as when our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaid, <hi>My fleſh is meat indeed,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>John</hi> 6. it was really ſo, did really nouriſh, yet ſpiritually.</p>
               <p>Now ſecondly, would I know, how ſuch a real preſence as they contend for (<hi>viz:</hi> a corporal, carnal, or contradiſtinct to ſpiritual) can be neceſſary to the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Sacrament: for that real preſence being the bodily communication of Chriſts body, as it is not the thing of the Sacrament, or <hi>the importance</hi> of it, <hi>viz:</hi> our Union with Chriſt, (for all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy receivers have that bodily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of his <hi>body</hi> into their <hi>mouthes</hi> and <hi>ſtomacks</hi>) ſo cannot it be any help to, or pledge and aſſurance of our ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and true Union with Chriſt: for their real preſence communicates his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to our bodies, without any ſenſe and feeling nay againſt ſenſe, and ſo cannot be any pledge or ſacramental confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to us of receiving him ſpiritually: alſo it conveyes his body through the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:61464:103"/>mouth without any real eating, and ſo cannot be any repreſentation or aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of our ſpiritual eating: Laſtly, it makes his body ſtay a while in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, without any union or incorporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo cannot make any way to the working or aſſuring our reall Union with Chriſt, our nouriſhing by his body and blood. Of ſuch <hi>importance</hi> is their real preſence or bodily communication, that it makes for nothing but to deſtroy the Sacrament, and to take away the real eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sacramental bread, the real in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporation of it into our bodies, the real nouriſhment received by it: all which are neceſſary in the Sacrament, to teſtifie and help our ſpiritual eating of Chriſts body, our nouriſhing by it, our Union with him, which is the <hi>importance of the Sacrament.</hi> And this of our ſpiritual eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and union is well ſet out by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that have written upon <hi>John</hi> 6. eſpecially by S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> yea and well expreſſed by the Councel of <hi>Florence; Hujus Sacramenti effectus</hi> (or as the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, <hi>the importance of this Sacrament</hi>) <hi>quem in anima operatur dignè ſumentis, eſt adunatio hominis ad Chriſtum, The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of this Sacrament which it works upon
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:61464:103"/>the ſoul of the worthy Receiver, is the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a man to Chriſt,</hi> (and this I hope is a ſpiritual communication) and then further, <hi>Omnem effectum, quem materialis cibus &amp; potus quoad vitam agunt corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, hoc Idem quoad vitam ſpiritualem &amp; hoc Sacramentum operatur, Every effect, which material meat and drink hath, as to the bodily life, the ſame doth this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment work as to the ſpiritual life.</hi> What Proteſtant could have ſpoken better, to ſet out the ſpiritual communication of Chriſts body and blood, our incorporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into him, union with him, ſignified and wrought by the ſacramental commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, incorporation and nouriſhment of the Elements?</p>
               <p>Again, we oppoſe in ſome points the <hi>deeds</hi> of the Fathers againſt their <hi>phraſes. Phraſes</hi> may be careleſly (at firſt) or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratively ſpoken, and may in time be altered and corrupted, but <hi>deeds</hi> remain in Hiſtory, and <hi>deeds</hi> upon controverſie ſpeak the judgment indeed of the perſons intereſſed: ſuch we alledge. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, againſt thoſe many Eulogies and high expreſſions which the Fathers uſed to the magnifying of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and S. <hi>Peters</hi> Chair (abuſed now to prove
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:61464:104"/>that this <hi>Infallibility, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,</hi> and exorbitant power, challenged by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> was acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by Antiquity) we bring <hi>deeds,</hi> and thoſe upon conteſtation: as the ſtanding out of <hi>Polycrates</hi> and all the <hi>Aſian</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops againſt the ſentence of Pope <hi>Victor:</hi> alſo in the conteſtation between S. <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> and Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi> it is eaſily ſeen that <hi>Cyprian</hi> by all thoſe ſpeeches he had uſed to the magnifying of the Roman See (and many they alledge out of him) meant no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe, than to aſcribe to that See, what of late Ages they have challenged. So in the conteſtation between the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man See and the African Biſhops (among whom S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was one, and one that uſed to ſpeak ſometimes very high of the Roman Church) in the buſineſs of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals, we ſee their judgement by their <hi>deeds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſee alſo by this, how that which is ſpoken by the Fathers, may prove but uncertainly and unwarily ſpoken, when it comes to the Trial, and farre ſhort of that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would have us believe they meant. For it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but the Fathers often ſpeak with a Latitude, and apply things to the preſent
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:61464:104"/>advantage. As when they had to doe with Hereſies newly ſprung up, they uſually oppoſed the eminency of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (as then indeed it was eminent both for ſucceſſion and doctrine) ſetting it out with glorious Titles: or when the Faſtern Biſhops needed relief, (for the Weſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed peace for the moſt part of the four firſt Centuries, when the Eaſt was much troubled) and applied themſelves to <hi>Rome</hi> for help (as <hi>Athanaſius, Chryſoſtome,</hi> and others) that their cauſe might be judged in the Weſt by the Pope and his Councel, when they could have no juſtice in the Eaſt: no mervail if by ſuch applications, the Church and Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> gained many high Titles and acknowledgments from ſuch diſtreſſed perſons, and their Wel-wiſhers. But when it came to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation with <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf (as in the caſes above-mentioned, wherein <hi>Cyprian, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> and others, were engaged at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times) it is plainly ſeen that thoſe Teſtimonies which <hi>Cyprian, Auguſtine,</hi> and others had given in ſo high a ſtrain, meant not what they ſeemed at firſt ſight to atteſt, or what the Cardinal and other Romiſh writers bring them for.</p>
               <p>Now they muſt acknowledge this uſed
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:61464:105"/>ſometimes by the Fathers, to apply their ſpeech to the preſent advantage, (not indeed contradicting what they meant, but moderating what before they ſpake more unwarily) for the Cardinal obſerves the like of them, <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3. That before the Arrians aroſe, the Interpretation of that place <hi>of the Rock, Mat.</hi> 16. run upon the perſon of <hi>Peter:</hi> but afterwards the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers finding the advantage of the place againſt the Arrians, interpreted it of the Confeſſion which <hi>Peter</hi> made, that <hi>Chriſt was the Son of the living God:</hi> to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he there. And it comes all to this. The Fathers before ſpake unwarily, but afterward ſpake as they ſaw they had reaſon. Yet thus it fared in this great point of <hi>Romes</hi> greatneſs, for which they pretend the Fathers.</p>
               <p>Therefore to conclude the ſecond point: the Romaniſts have the ſhadow, the ſhell, the name, the phraſe many times, but we carry the ſubſtance, ſhew the thing, the ſenſe, the judgement, the deeds of Antiquity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Sometimes we meet with <hi>beginnings</hi> of opinions and practiſes in the compaſſe of the firſt four Ages, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> did after form into a fixt belief
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:61464:105"/>and practice; but it was not ſo then. Then indeed the ſeeds were ſcattered, out of the which by degrees ſprang ſome of this forbidden fruit, which the Roman Church now holds forth. As for Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, The opinion of a <hi>purging fire</hi> was then but in the wandring conceits of ſome few (as above inſinuated in this Chap.) and which is to be further noted, thoſe few into whoſe conceits it firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, were of the <hi>Greek</hi> Fathers; yet ſo little did it prevail in that Church, that to this day it is not improved into a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or belief of the Church among the <hi>Greeks.</hi> Which ſhews it reſted but in the conceit of ſome particular men.</p>
               <p>So for the point of <hi>Invocation,</hi> we finde beginning given to that practice in the fourth Century, by Rhetorical Apoſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe's uſed in their Orations for the Dead, by the exceſſe of devotion and honour that ſome were carried with towards the bleſſed Martyrs, breaking out ſometimes into compellations of them, and uttering their deſires to them, as if they had been preſent.</p>
               <p>Here we have a private practice begun by ſome few, not grounded upon any doctrine of the Church. And long time
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:61464:106"/>after it was, ere it crept into the Letanies or publick offices of the Church. So in the point of the <hi>half-Communion,</hi> we meet with ſome <hi>private</hi> practice, ſome receiving the bread only in a caſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, but <hi>publickly</hi> it was ever admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in both kindes, and alſo privately, where and when it could. And many expreſs declarations we meet with againſt receiving it in one kinde; and when it was received ſo, it was held an imperfect, and not full Communion; This is moſt plain in Antiquity for above 1000 years.</p>
               <p>And now whoever will examine well the flouriſh of Card: <hi>Perroun</hi> in his firſt book, <hi>cap.</hi> 18. (where running through all the points of Romiſh faith and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, he affirms the antient Church to have held and practiſed ſo) will no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion finde, that, what is there alledged, falls ſhort of proving the doctrine or practiſe of the ancient Church, and that the Card. often gives us the Name with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Thing, or the Phraſe without the Romiſh ſenſe, or ſome private opinion for the doctrine of the Church; or ſome beginning practiſe for an eſtabliſhed one; or a private practice for the practice of the Church. Beſides, there is no conſent
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:61464:106"/>of Fathers given in that Chapter upon any point.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXI. <hi>Card:</hi> Perrons <hi>two Rules for knowing who and what is Catholick according to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd here it will not be amiſſe to take a view of two of his Rules or Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, which in his Letter to Mr. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaubon</hi> he gives us, to ſhew what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to make a man or Church Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick now, according to the doctrines and practiſes of the antient Church. By which I cannot ſee how himſelf or his Church can ſtand, or challenge the name of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelick</hi> He there ſaith (in his ſecond ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation) <hi>That any ſhould paſſe for Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, it is needful they be conformable to the integrity of the belief of the Fathers,</hi> i.e. <hi>to believe all things they believed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that degree they believed them in,</hi> viz: <hi>to believe as neceſſary to ſalvation the things they believed to be ſo, and as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to ſalvation, the things they believed to be ſo, and as not repugnant to ſalvation, what they held ſo.</hi> This is one of his Rules.</p>
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:61464:107"/>
               <p>Here are ſtrict conditions; yet let us ſee how they or we ſtand bound to them. For the firſt, <hi>Things believed neceſſary to ſalvation.</hi> The Romaniſts cannot chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge us Proteſtants for not believing what they of the antient Church did ſo believe, with a due and full conſent. And for the points controverted (which they challenge us for not believing) let them, if they can, give us ſo general a conſent of Fathers for them, as we finde in thoſe former Ages agreeing in the Millenary belief, in the place of faithful Souls (out of Heaven) till the Day of Judgment, in the Communion given to Infants, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for their ſalvation, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and yet neither the Cardinal nor any Romaniſt holds himſelfe bound to believe in theſe things (put them in what rank they will, as <hi>neceſſary</hi> or <hi>profitable</hi>) as they more generally did of old for ſome Ages. If they ſay the Millenary b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief was rejected within the compaſſe of the four firſt Ages, For that is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of Time the Cardinal is pleaſed to allow in this tryal; True. But then it tells us, the ſucceeding Ages did not hold themſelves bound to believe all things as they before them did, nor doe the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:61464:107"/>hold themſelves bound to believe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that errour, or the two other of the place of Souls, or Infant Communion, which continued after, even to the end of the Ages fixed by the Cardinal. And will they have us Proteſtants bound to believe either what the Fathers did believe erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neouſly, or what the Romaniſts pleaſe to ſay the Fathers did believe, when we know they did not, or generally did not?</p>
               <p>And as for the other two points of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>things profitable to ſalvation,</hi> and <hi>things not repugnant,</hi> How will the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal poſſibly give us a conſent of Fathers in <hi>thoſe points?</hi> or if he had the confidence to have undertook it, ſeeing ſo many things of opinion, of Rites, and of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies fall under thoſe conditions of <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable or not repugnant</hi> to ſalvation, ſhall any Church be therefore not Catholick, becauſe it does not hold or practice in every ſuch thing, as the Church in thoſe Ages did? as for example, Trine immer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in Baptiſm, ſtanding in publick pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er betwixt Eaſter and Pentecoſt, and ſome other, not onely held and uſed by the Church of thoſe Ages, but affirmed by ſome Fathers of thoſe Ages to be of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:61464:108"/>Tradition, yet are they not held or practiſed by the Romiſh Church.</p>
               <p>The Cardinal his other Rule is in his fourth Obſervation in the ſame Letter, <hi>Let that be held</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as truly anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and to have the mark of the primitive Church, which is found to be believed and practiſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally by the Fathers of the Times of the four firſt Councels; and when it appears, that the things teſtified by them, were not held for doctrines and obſervances ſprung up in their time, but as perpetually practiſed in the Church from the Age of the Apoſtles; and that there is not found in the former Authors teſtimony against them, but in all places (where there is occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to mention them) agreeable and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable.</hi> So he. This indeed is reaſonable fair, as to the tryal between them and us: yet not this of it ſelf to give a ſufficient ground for belief; for how will it hold in the forementioned inſtances of Infant-Communion, and the places of mens Souls till the reſurrection, in which both they and we reject what was generally believed and practiſed in thoſe Ages? <hi>where ſtill by</hi> Generally, <hi>is meant, more generally believed or practiſed, and ſo the Cardinals word</hi> Univerſally, <hi>in his Rule is
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:61464:108"/>to be underſtood.</hi> But as to the points con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted: How can the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hold to this, or ſtand by it, when ſhe is never able to ſhew her doctrines ſo at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, believed, practiſed? nay when as we are able to ſhew <hi>the beginning</hi> of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them but ſpringing up in, or after thoſe Ages, as <hi>Purgatory, Invocation of Saints, Image-worſhip, Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, half-Communion?</hi> Nay when their own Authors give us reaſons why the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and thoſe of the firſt Age did not teach (as Chap. 21. was noted above) <hi>Invocation of Saints</hi> and <hi>Image-worſhip,</hi> to the firſt Chriſtians; yet muſt theſe paſſe for Catholick doctrines, univerſally believed and practiſed from the Age of the Apoſtles. <hi>A cauſe this, that needed the great wit of that Cardinal, to make Antiquity appear for it in ſo fair a ſhew, and then to perſwade men ſo far out of their wits, as to believe it did ſo indeed; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as theſe general Hints, that have been given from the beginning of the</hi> 30 <hi>Chap: may ſuffice to let any man, that hath rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, know, it can be no good appearance, which is made of Antiquity, but a cunning diſguiſe: and that the</hi> Trent <hi>Articles can be no Catholick or perpetual doctrine of the
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:61464:109"/>Church, but Novel-points of Romiſh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, creeping at firſt, (ſome in one Age, ſome in another) into Opinion or practice, and ſo by degrees gathering ſtrength, till they were aſſerted by the moſt and chiefeſt in that Communion, and defended for the doctrine of that Church, and at length coi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into Articles of. Faith, as the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick doctrine of all Ages, and of the whole Church.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:61464:109"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>OF the Diviſion of the Engliſh and Romiſh Church, upon the Reformation.</hi> 1</item>
               <item>Chap. I. <hi>We ſet not up a new Church, but were the ſame Christian Church before and after the Reformation.</hi> 4</item>
               <item>Chap. II. <hi>The demand of Profeſſors in all Ages. We can ſhew it better than they.</hi> 9</item>
               <item>Chap. III. <hi>How they and we are ſaid to differ in Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials.</hi> 12</item>
               <item>Chap. IV. <hi>Particular Churckes may reform; Espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when a General Councel cannot be expected.</hi> 15</item>
               <item>Chap. V. <hi>We not guilty of Schiſm. The guilt of the breach lies on the Romaniſts.</hi> 20</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:61464:110"/>
               <item>Chap. VI. <hi>How neceſſity of dividing Communion ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> 24</item>
               <item>Chap. VII. <hi>Sectaries cannot make the Plea that we doe.</hi> 28</item>
               <item>Chap. VIII. <hi>Of the uſe of Reaſon and Judgment in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e men.</hi> 31</item>
               <item>Chap. IX. <hi>Of diſſenting from the publick Judgment.</hi> 35</item>
               <item>Chap. X. <hi>Poſſibility of juſt diſſenting.</hi> 39</item>
               <item>Chap XI. <hi>How farre the Romaniſts leave men the uſe of their Reaſon and Judgment.</hi> 47</item>
               <item>Chap. XII. <hi>Of knowing the Church by the marks of</hi> Eminencie, Perpetuity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 51</item>
               <item>Chap. XIII. <hi>Our way opens not a gap to Sectaries.</hi> 57</item>
               <item>Chap. XIV. <hi>The Romaniſts vain pretence of Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> 63</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:61464:110"/>
               <item>Chap. XV. <hi>Dividing from the Roman Church is not a dividing from the Catholick.</hi> 66</item>
               <item>Chap. XVI. <hi>The Greek Church, a Church, and part of the Catholick.</hi> 69</item>
               <item>Chap. XVII. <hi>Of agreement and external Communion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the parts of the Catholick Church.</hi> 73</item>
               <item>Chap. XVIII. <hi>The want of that does not alwaies make guilty of Schiſm.</hi> 75</item>
               <item>Chap. XIX. <hi>Our caſe and that of the Donatiſts not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</hi> 78</item>
               <item>Chap. XX. <hi>Of Hell-Gates not prevailing againſt the Church.</hi> 82</item>
               <item>Chap. XXI. <hi>Of the Trial of Doctrines by Scripture.</hi> 91</item>
               <item>Chap. XXII. <hi>Sufficient perfection of the Scripture, as a Rule.</hi> 95</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:61464:111"/>
               <item>Chap. XXIII. <hi>Of Tradition, which we allow.</hi> 96</item>
               <item>Chap. XXIV. <hi>Their arguments againſt Scriptures ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, and for Traditions.</hi> 103</item>
               <item>Chap. XXV. <hi>The evidence of Antiquity in the point.</hi> 114</item>
               <item>Chap. XXVI. <hi>Of the Perspicuity and Interpretation of Scripture.</hi> 119</item>
               <item>Chap. XXVII. <hi>Of a viſible Infallible Judge or Interpreter.</hi> 125</item>
               <item>Chap. XXVIII. <hi>Of certainty of belief, and whether they or we have better means for it.</hi> 146</item>
               <item>Chap. XXIX. <hi>Of the other Rule of Trial, by Conſent of Antiquity, and the Romaniſts vain boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Fathers.</hi> 157</item>
               <item>Chap. XXX. <hi>Application of the Rule to their Doctrine in ſeveral p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ints.</hi> 161</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:61464:111"/>
               <item>CHAP. XXXI. <hi>Card:</hi> Perrons <hi>two Rules for knowing who and what is Catholick according to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity.</hi> 179</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>The end of the Table.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="printers_advertisment">
            <pb facs="tcp:61464:112"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61464:112"/>
            <p>¶ A Catalogue of ſome Books printed for <hi>Richard Royſton,</hi> at the Angel in Ivie-lane,</p>
            <p>By <hi>H. Ferne,</hi> D. D. <hi>Epiſcopacy and Presbytery conſidered,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sermon preached at the</hi> Iſle of Wight, <hi>before his Majeſtie,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>Now in the Preſſe,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Compendious Diſcourſe upon the Caſe, as it ſtands between the Church of</hi> England <hi>and of</hi> Rome <hi>on the one ſide; and again between the ſame Church of</hi> England, <hi>and thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, which (of what perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſoever) have divided from it, on the other ſide.</hi> Part I. in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
